We saw before with the XOR perceptron,
that adding a second layer of units allows the model to find
solutions to linearly inseparable problems.
Here is an example of a multilayer perceptron with three input units,
one output unit, and two units in the middle.
This middle layer is called the hidden layer.
Calculating the output of this network is the same as before,
except that now the activations of the hidden layer
are used as the input to the output layer.
The input to the hidden layer is the same as before,
it's these weights times the input values plus some bias term.
As before, again, you use
an activation function such as a sigmoid to calculate the output of the hidden layer.
The hidden layer activations are passed to
the output layer through the second set of weights.
Again, use an activation function to get the output of the network.
Stacking more and more layers like this helps the network learn more complex patterns.
This is where deep learning gets this name from and what makes it so powerful.
Deep stacks of hidden layers.