Why do we wrangle data?
Data is everywhere in the world offering
invaluable insights such as daily step counts for fitness app developers,
website engagement metrics for marketers,
and national health data for governments to address health crises.
All of them are examples of transforming raw information into actionable knowledge.
One of the first steps to making sense of data is gathering it.
Meaningful data that you can use right away is often hard to find in the real world.
You need to obtain and extract data so it can then be assessed for issues and cleaned.
Then you can finally start to answer questions with the clean data.
Sometimes we may gather data right from the source,
like gathering logs in the smartwatch in order to
figure out how many steps that we've been walking through out the day.
Other times data is provided to us, for example,
by the US Census Bureau or a state's health departments services portal.
We can use this information then to make
reliable conclusions regarding data and answer some interesting questions.
One of the most exciting things about data wrangling is the breadth of techniques that we
can use to be able to gather this data and to put it into actual code.
We've talked about how gathering is the first step towards data
wrangling and ultimately unlocking valuable insights from your data.
There are two key aspects of data gathering techniques.
One, the first step of data gathering is
obtaining data from different sources, like from APIs.
For example, imagine an organization that's
looking to analyze user groups for market insights.
They need data on competitors,
customer interests, pricing, and more.
We can't expect all this data to come from one neatly formatted source.
Then the second step is extracting the obtained data,
such as from.TXT and.CSV files into a format suitable for assessment and cleaning.
After that, we can then use this data to answer questions like
identifying top market opportunities for our hypothetical organization to invest in.