There are times when a data cleric can't download files from the Internet
manually or wants a way to do this more efficiently programmatically.
Let's take a look at a couple of methods where we can use
programmatic approaches towards data gathering to make this more efficient.
We're going to use the Request Library,
which is an HTTP library in Python that allows you to send HTTP requests easily.
Let's see an example of an HTTP request.
This is a GET request,
which is used to request data from a source,
like a URL from Wikipedia.
How do we know whether or not our request to get data from a URL has succeeded?
There are status codes that help us with that.
Codes between 200 and 299 indicate that
the request was successful and we got the data that we needed.
On the other hand, codes between 400-599 indicate errors.
You've probably encountered the infamous 404 error
when trying to access a website that no longer exists.
The requests library enables us to catch these errors to
understand when and why our programmatic requests fail.
Let's now take a look at how to do this in Python.
Let's take a brief look at how to use the request library to make an
HTTP get request to programmatically download files from the Internet.
For this demo, we're leveraging some movie reviews written by Roger Ebert in 2017.
Our first step is import the libraries that we're going to be using, requests and os.
Then we're going to go ahead and create a directory using
os.makedirs where we can store the files that we're going to programmatically download.
Note that we're going to create this directory if it doesn't already exist by
using os.path.exists to check whether or not the file path already exists.
Next, we've predefined a list of URLs of existing reviews.
Let's dive into the requests code.
For each of the URLs in this list,
we're going to go ahead and create a HTTP GET request using the
request.get(url) and then use the raise_for_status function to
raise an exception if this GET request is resulting in an error.
Then we're going to construct the file path for saving the content we'll download.
We're going to combine the folder name that we defined
earlier and the last part of the URL.
For example, for this first URL that we've got here,
the file path would be ebert_reviews_2017/1-the-wizard-of-oz-1939-film.txt.
Then here we're simply using Python's open function
to open the file specified by the file path in the binary write mode.
Why WB or binary mode?
Because the content of the response object that we're writing
here to the file retrieved from the URL is in bytes.
Finally, this file.write function is actually writing the binary content to the file.
It suceeded on the first three URLs,
but our code is failing on our fourth URL.
This is intentional.
Note how our URL here is erroneously specifying Bumblebee as part of the URL.
We can see how the requests library is immediately raising a 403 client error,
indicating the client is forbidden from accessing a valid URL.
For the other three URLs that we were able to save successfully,
through the os.listdir command,
we can actually check to see that these were successfully saved to our directory.
We can also use the built-in so-called magic command to actually load one of
these reviews into the current cell in
our Jupyter notebook to see that we were successful.