What is a text file?
Text files are files with text in them that use a specific character-set,
contain no rules for structure and no formatting like italics or bowling,
have no media like images or video,
and have lines of texts that are separated by
newline characters or backslash ends in Python.
Now, these characters are typically invisible in most software applications,
and it can be viewed and edited in simple text editors.
As we've talked about before,
flat files can be text files that have a specific tabular structure.
Whereas text files that fall out of
the flat file category can be either structured or unstructured.
Let's take a look at an example of a very popular corpus or
a collection of texts made up of individual text files.
The 20 newsgroup data,
which has about 20,000 documents partitioned across 20 newsgroups,
including topics like space or Mideast politics or computer graphics.
Here we have an example of the.TXT file for the computer graphics newsgroup,
which has about 975 messages in it.
Assuming this data is cleaned,
one cool thing that we can do is create a word cloud.
Take a look at this word cloud,
which is serving as a visual representation of the texts in our data-set.
A word cloud is showing us how frequently words are occurring
within the text by displaying them in different font sizes.
For example in a subset of the comp graphics newsgroup data-set,
we can see that the words graphics and subject are two very popular words.
This gives us an immediate understanding of
the dominant themes present in the text data-set.