Have you ever opened a document and seen garbled characters?
For example, take a look at the sample Wikipedia article on the page here,
and that's displayed with the wrong encoding.
That happens when your text editor,
browser or word processor is assuming the wrong encoding.
You simply need to select the right encoding to display the document properly.
Character sets and encodings are two things that
every programmer needs to be aware of when working with any text data.
A character set is a collection of characters,
symbols, or glyphs used in writing and communication.
It includes letters, digits, punctuation marks,
and other special characters that are found in various languages and scripts.
Encoding or a character encoding is a scheme that assigns
a unique numeric identifier or code point to each character and a character set.
These numeric identifiers are then represented in binary format,
a sequence of zeros and ones,
so that they can be stored and processed by computers.
Different encodings can be used to represent the same character set,
but they may assign different numeric identifiers to the characters.
Here's a few examples of popular character sets and encoding schemes.
ASCII is an older encoding scheme that handles symbols, letters, and digits,
and contains 128 characters including letters,
digits, punctuation, and control characters.
For example, the capital A has an ASCII value of 65,
while the digit 1 has an ASCII value of 49.
Unicode is a comprehensive character encoding standard that aims to
represent virtually all writing systems and characters used worldwide.
It is used by most modern systems.
Unicode covers not only letters, digits, and punctuation,
but also special symbols,
emojis and non-Latin scripts.
Unicode Transformation Format eight bit or UTF-8,
is a very popular encoding system.
It can handle symbols from multiple languages and support a lot of unique characters.
If you have a CSV file in UTF-8 format you can specify
the encoding scheme directly when reading the file through the encoding parameter.
When you encode a string in Python say using ASCII,
it turns the character string into a byte string,
or in other words, a sequence of bytes that are machine-readable.
The output of this would be a byte string as denoted by the b before the apostrophes.
Why are we still able to see hello world though?
Because Python 3 is automatically decoding the string from ASCII so we can read it.
Regarding decoding, when you decode a string in Python,
it turns from byte stream to a character string that is human-readable.
Similar to encode, you can decode a byte string by
using the decode function and specify the encoding scheme.
Now you can see that the b is gone from
the output and the output is just a string, hello world.
When I say string, it's worth noting Python three has one text type called STR,
which holds Unicode data.
Python 3 also has to by types; bytes and bytearray.
These objects are very similar however,
have one key difference.
A bytes object is immutable,
which means that once it is created,
it cannot be modified.
A bytesarray is mutable.
Once you create it, you can modify it.