In this demo, I'm going to show you how to read a few review text files in a folder.
We're going to go ahead and read each file line by line to extract the title,
URL, and text of each review.
We're going to then store this information in a Pandas DataFrame.
Now we have three Roger Ebert reviews
programmatically downloaded and we're going to use them.
They're in this directory here.
Note how if we double-click into one txt file with each dot txt file,
the first line is the title,
the second line is the URL,
and the third line and onwards is the review text.
Let's get started. We'll start with importing Pandas' and Python built-in glob module,
a library that helps with Unix style pathname pattern expansion.
This essentially means that we can use glob patterns to specify
sets of filenames using wildcard characters like asterisk,
which can be used to patch a string of any length.
It is a lot of information,
but you only need to remember the glob.glob.
The pattern ebert reviews 2017,
slash asterisk dot txt will find any file within
our reviews folder that has a dot txt extension regardless of the file's name.
The asterisk is a wildcard character.
It allows you to find and process all text files in
the directory without specifying each filename individually.
Now, let's go ahead and start our implementation.
First, we're going to go ahead and create an empty list,
text list to store information from each file in the directory.
Now what we're going to do is iterate through files in our directory.
We'll iterate through all the text files in
our reviews directory using the glob.glob function.
Next, we're going to go ahead and open the text file with
open ebert review encoding equals UTFE as file.
In Python 3, when opening texts to read,
you should always use open with
an encoding parameter to ensure that you get correctly decoded unicode,
or an error message.
Here we opened each text file using a path generated
from glob and pass it into a file handle called file.
Then we read the first line of the file, which is the title.
Since text files are separated by new line characters and
the file object returned from with open this file is an iterator,
we can read the file line by line using file dot readline.
In our text files,
the title is followed by a bit of whitespace,
which is actually the backslash end or the new line character.
We can get rid of that by slicing it off at the end of the string using
indexing by minus one which basically means keep everything but the last character.
Now we've got the movie title.
Next, we're going to go ahead and grab the URL,
which is the second line.
You're going to use dot readline
again to catch the second line and remove that newline character at the end.
Now, next with file dot read
everything from the third line and onwards is the review text,
so we can just read the rest of the file using the dot read function.
Now, it's time to get this into a DataFrame.
We add the title, review URL,
and review text that we just read
to a list of dictionaries and we give them proper names.
Next, what we're going to do is after iterating through all the files,
convert our text list,
or list of dictionaries into a Pandas DataFrame called df.
Here, as you can see, we're specifically
denoting the column names in the order of title,
review URL, and review text and
basically converting our list of dictionaries into a DataFrame.
Let's use df.head to print the first few rows of our DataFrame after running this code,
and we see that the title, URL,
and the review text columns are all populated
correctly with the data from our text files in our directory.