Let's take a look at this webpage now to learn more about APIs.
First, I'd like to show you how I can manually get the metadata of a particular book.
Right now I just navigated to the webpage I shared earlier in my browser.
Take a look at a small snippet of
the JSON file containing the metadata we can get from these pages.
We have some great info available,
including when the book was created,
the different files available, etc.
At the end of the file,
we can actually see information including the reviews, etc.
Now, there are two primary ways to use APIs,
and they're nicely illustrated by
the developer tools that the Internet Archive has put out there.
Let's go ahead and switch over to
a Jupyter Notebook to figure out how to wrangle this data.
One approach to use APIs is similar to what we've done with the request library,
where we make an HTTP GET request.
This method enables us to retrieve the desired data directly from
the API by sending a request and
receiving a response containing the relevant information.
First, let's go ahead and import our requests and
Python's inbuilt JSON library to save the JSON file we're going to get.
Let's create a HTTP GET request with
the request library to retrieve metadata from this particular books URL.
The books unique identifier is specified after the metadata tag.
The retrieved information is stored in an object called Book.
Now, if we run this code,
we see that Book is primarily containing the response code,
amongst other data and methods.
We then check for any exceptions that requests is raising using raise for status.
See, we're seeing here that it doesn't really raise any exceptions,
so we can go ahead and proceed.
Next, we convert the JSON formatted data from
the API response into a native Python data structure using dot-json.
The convert data is then assigned to a variable,
in this case, JSON data.
Now, here we can see that the JSON data
variable is containing the metadata of the book we selected,
which we previously saw as part of the webpage.
Now that we have all of this great data,
let's go ahead and save our JSON file.
We'll open the file path in book.json in write mode and define
the file object as f. We're then going to use the json.dump
function to save the data into the
book.json file by specifying the JSON data variable in the file object
f. Note that the Internet Archive
API does not require any authentication for users to retrieve metadata.
But some APIs may require authentication through an HTTP post method.
In that case, in addition to this,
you're actually required to provide your username and password for an account
you created with the website in order to be able to make a GET request for the data.
Let's talk about a second approach.
Now, the second approach to use APIs is using
a customized developer library for that particular data source if available.
For example, the Internet Archive has created
an Internet Archive library for using its API.
Here's a small snippet from their tutorials.
Here you can import get_item,
to retrieve the metadata of the item associated with the identifier,
and then store it in an object called book,
as we're doing here with our Language of Flowers book.
Then we can go ahead and iterate through
the key value pairs in the metadata attribute of the book object.
We can use dot items on the book's metadata because that is what contains
the key value pair as tuples in a list that we can then iterate through.
We can then print each key value pair to get the metadata of the book in a neat format.
How do you decide which option to use?
HTTP GET request is not always available,
particularly when a website or
a data source provider prohibits gathering through these means,
due to concerns like an overload of requests being sent to
the website or the website simply doesn't respond.
Using customized libraries is typically a more popular option,
as popular websites typically have their own library to work with their API,
as we saw with the Internet Archive.
Some other providers who have customized libraries are Wikipedia,
Twitter, or Spotify, and more.