Most data from APIs comes in JSON format,
so it's important we familiarize ourselves with the format.
JSON stands for JavaScript Object Notation,
and it is not flat files.
JSON is built on two key structures that differentiate it from flat files.
Let's consider the data on the right,
which is a snippet of data collected on a movie directed by Steven Spielberg.
The first structure is JSON objects.
JSON objects are a collection of key value pairs that are surrounded by curly braces.
Let's look into this object.
We have a key, "Directed by",
and its corresponding value is Steven Spielberg.
This is a key value pair.
Look at another key value pair.
We have the key, "Written by",
and its corresponding value is Melissa Mathison.
In Python, JSON objects are interpreted as
dictionaries and you can access them like you would a standard Python dictionary.
JSON object keys must be strings.
Notice that every key here Direct by, Produced,
by, Written by and Starring are all strings.
However, JSON object values can be any valid JSON datatype like numbers or a list.
Speaking up, this leads us to the second structure, JSON arrays.
A JSON array is an ordered list of values,
for example for the "Produced b"y key,
the value is a list of strings,
the array of producers: Kathleen Kennedy,
Steven Spielberg, surrounded by square brackets.
In Python, JSON arrays are interpreted and accessed like lists.
Now, values for both JSON objects and arrays can be any valid JSON datatype,
string, number, object, array, Boolean or null.
For example here we have a JSON object.
Note how we have the values for file count and item size as integers.
We also have a metadata key that contains its own JSON object.
Within it there are the media type and collection
keys and the collection key contains a list of strings.
This snippet is a great example of how JSON can
contain complicated data hierarchies where
objects or arrays are contained within other objects or arrays, we call it nesting.
This makes it very distinct from the flat file format.
For example take a look at how we may represent
the same data in a CSV format at the right.
Note how we lost the data hierarchies because the metadata key is missing.