I'd like to now walk you through how to gather JSON data using
the request library and access data within JSON files in Python.
We'll be looking at the JSON from the archive.org.item.
First, let's take a look at how we can use
Python's built-in json module to extract JSON data from a request.
We'll start with importing our request in JSON libraries and then making
an HTTP GET Request to the book on archive.org using the requests library.
Perfect. Now we want to access the output of this request which contains the json.
If I use the method book.content,
note how I get a byte string.
If I want the output of the request in Unicode,
I can go ahead and use the.text method so I can see the texts better.
Note how if we use the.text method,
the output is in a string format.
See the apostrophe before the curly braces.
How do we convert this string with a JSON object in it to just a Python object?
Here we're going to go ahead, scroll down and use the json.loads function,
which does just that, to de-serialize the string
that we're getting from the.text method into a Python dictionary.
Here using json.loads on book.text,
we have now a Python dictionary.
We'll take a moment to get back to inspecting the output of this in a bit.
I want to note a quick thing.
You can actually also use json.loads on the outputs of the.content method as well.
This is because you can also use.loads to
de-serialize bytes or byte arrays in addition to strings.
As we can see here,
it works just fine on our byte output as well.
Now, let's take a look at another option that is much more popular and simpler.
Here I'm making my HTTP GET Request again and using the.json
method of a response object from the request library to extract the JSON data.
Now we can see after just using.json,
it's ready to use.
Next let's actually inspect this data regarding metadata about the book more closely.
We have a lot of data and nesting that's taking place in this JSON.
Some data includes the number of files associated with the book,
like this thumbnail file.
In addition, we can also scroll down all the way here and
see additional information about the camera that was used for capturing the book,
the publisher, the date, etc.
Let's see now how to access some of this data.
Let's start with accessing one of the first attributes, the directory.
Scrolling up here, we can see that we have that
as one of our first attributes as part of the JSON file.
Note how I use the brackets to do so in order to access the dir key.
Let's actually move on to something a bit more complicated,
now that we can see that we can print the result in value for that key.
I want to show you how we can access the review title.
Here first, I have to access the metadata attribute as part of this huge JSON.
Now note that the metadata attribute is actually
a JSON object containing many key value pairs.
See the title key here, for example,
which is nestled within the metadata attribute.
That's what we need. To access it,
I need to use metadata and then title.
Let's look at what that looks like.
Now I'm able to get the full title of the book pro-grammatically.
Let's take a look at some of the reviews data for the book.
First, let's go ahead and use a similar methodology of accessing the reviews attribute.
Now the reviews key is containing a JSON array,
as you can see with the square brackets here,
with exactly one JSON object or element in it.
Let's access the only JSON object in this JSON array using the indexing value of zero.
Notice now how the square brackets are now disappeared from
our output since this is the only element in the list.
Now with JSON object reviews zero,
we now have one JSON object with many key value pairs.
Now one of these keys is review body.
Let's go ahead and see if we can access this.
I can access this by doing json_book_text,
indexing by reviews,
zero, and reviewbody to get the content of my review.
Now finally, I want to show you something really complicated.
Check out the files attribute,
which contains information about a number of
different file download options that archive.org provides for the book,
including the thumbnail, as we saw earlier,
options to download as a PDF,
and a zip file, etc.
Similarly, the structure of the files attribute in a JSON array is
now having multiple JSON objects in it rather than just one JSON object.
Let's task ourselves with finding out the size the Raw Cornell book Zip download option.
Here's where it is in the files attribute.
I want to access the size key to get the size of this particular zip file,
which is all the way over here.
Because this JSON array has multiple JSON objects or elements in it,
I need to actually go ahead and find the index of the element for the zip file first.
Let's go ahead to the top of this JSON and count.
For example, we'd be counting our index 0, 1,
2, 3, 4, 5, and 6.
We can see this is actually the sixth element.
Now that I've done this and I got this specific JSON object
for the Raw Cornell Book Zip using the integer index,
I can now access the size key then in order to get the size of the zip file.
Altogether the command is looking like this,
where we have our json_book_text indexing
by the files attribute and then indexing by the integer six,
giving us the data for the Raw Cornell Book Zip download option.
Then we have to index by the size attribute and then get the actual size of this file.
Finally, let's now compare JSON notation and Python dictionary notation.
Here I've got a dictionary.
Firstly, we see how accessing attributes in JSON and dictionaries,
it's actually pretty similar.
Look at how we can access the value hello in
this dictionary using the key in the bracket.
However, keys in JSON can only be strings, as you may recall,
whereas Python dictionary keys can be any hashable object, like a number.
How do you convert a Python dictionary to a JSON object?
You can use the json.dumps function,
which takes an object and produces a JSON string,
or in other words, serializes it.
Here, note how we are serializing our dictionary object.
Note that this is the opposite of what json.loads does with de-serializing.