Data on the Internet is not always accessible via APIs or a final neatly provided to you.
To get data on the Internet,
oftentimes data wrangler is needed to do web scraping,
which allows us to extract data from websites using code.
Often when web scraping,
you will gather HTML or HyperText Markup Language Files
which use tags to structure the page,
we'll be exploring this in more detail in an upcoming lesson.
In this demo, I'm going to show the fundamentals of
web scraping on how to gather HTML files.
Let's return to our archive.org example with our book entry.
The quick way to get HTML data is by saving the HTML file to your computer manually,
you can do this by clicking Save in your browser on the HTML page.
Now, when I load the file from my local system,
note that I can see many of the elements on my webpage.
Let's take a brief look at the source code up
the HTML file through the sublime text editor,
we can see that it's a very large file.
I'm going to go try searching for one of
the reviews that this book has using the subject title,
no color illustrations here,
so we can find it nestled within a bunch of HTML tags.
Let's take a look at how we can actually extract this type of information,
including the book's title programmatically as its preferred for scalability,
and reproducibility when dealing with these types of complex files.
Let's go ahead and switch over to our Jupyter notebook.
By now, you're familiar with how we can use
the request library to create an HTTP get request,
so let's go over how to download the HTML file programmatically.
First, we're going to go ahead and import our requests library,
then we'll create a variable specifying the URL of the book that we've been leveraging.
Next, let's go ahead and create an HTTP get request through the requests library.
Next, to Save the HTML to a file,
we're going to open the file path,
language-of-flowers.html in right binary mode,
specifying the file as the file object.
We're then going to write the response.content to the file, again,
we use the right binary mode because response.content is a binary string,
as we can see below here.
Now, let's open up the HTML again,
here you can see that most of the elements are clearly preserved as part of the webpage.
The complicated items such as archives,
book pages preview,
are missing though after we've saved the file.
We can also see that some of the thumbnail images,
and things like this are missing for which we may need to download additional files.
Now it's worth noting that websites are increasingly
using JavaScript in ways that may make web scraping more difficult,
there are more advanced tools outside of
the request library that may be needed but are out of scope for this course.
One such scraper,
MARCXML is a great web scraping tool that can, for example,
use WebDrivers is to switch the browsers that you use for your web scraping.
In the next section, we'll talk about parsing HTML files.