The Hypertext Markup Language or HTML,
is the language used to create documents for the worldwide web,
and you've likely encountered it hundreds of thousands of times without knowing.
Let's dive into the structure of an HTML file to better
understand how data wranglers extract value from these files.
HTML is just a collection of tags.
The label inside the angle brackets indicates the type of elements,
for example, in the highlighted box this is a title tag.
The content between the tags is generally what people will see in the browser.
The title of this webpage,
for example, is HTML structure.
Note how the first mention of the title tag is an angled brackets,
but the second mention after the HTML structure texts has an angle bracket,
a slash, the word title,
and then a closing angle bracket.
This second mention of title with a slash indicates that this is the end of the tag.
So the rest of the HTML isn't the full title,
it's just the words between the title tags.
There are different types of HTML elements.
Heading elements are used for section heading tags,
such as H1, H2, H3, and H4.
Paragraph elements are used for standard blocks of texts.
Image elements are used to embed images in a webpage,
and span elements are used to
group text within another block of texts, often for styling.
Let's take a look at two examples.
The first example you can see that this is a span texts looks
just like as if it had been placed in a P or a paragraph tag,
but without the extra blank line before and after.
For the second span tag,
we can change the style of the another span text.
We can define the color as red in hexadecimal.
Now, you can see in the webpage snippet on the right,
the another span text is red.
The head element contains metadata about the webpage,
like the page's title or its encoding,
in this case, UTF-8.
The body element contains the actual HTML,
which is where all the tags,
such as heading in paragraph tags take place.
The HTML tag is a container for all other HTML elements except for the doc-type tag.
All HTML files must start with
this doctype HTML tag to give
information to the browser that they should expect an HTML file.
Let's compare HTML files with a couple of popular file formats, starting with JSON.
JSON and HTML are similar in that you can have elements inside of elements,
but that's where the similarities end.
We can create a tree structure in HTML by putting elements inside elements.
To do this, we often use a div element as a container.
Div elements are used to group chunks of content together such as these H1 and P tags.
As you write HTML code,
the hierarchy that you can create can grow as wide or as deep as you need them to be.
HTML and JSON are used for different purposes.
HTML is used for building websites,
whereas JSON is used for communicating information,
for example through APIs.
JSON is capable of handling more complex data,
whereas HTML has a simpler structure.
HTML files have a much more complicated structure though compared to flat files.
For example, consider a short review written for the archive.org book item.
You can see how on the left the content is nestled within the different HTML elements,
including the reviewer name,
the stars, the subject of the review, and the content.
On the right, take a look at a flat file with the same content with the columns,
reviewer, stars, subject, and texts.
We would need to pass the HTML file on the left and
extract the information accordingly to get it into the format on the right.