In the first few sections of this lesson,
we'll explore obtaining data through
downloading files and extracting data from flat files,
which contains tabular data.
We'll discuss the data gathering phase,
unzipping files using Python,
extracting data from tab-separated and comma-separated files,
and how to programmatically download data files.
In the next few sections of this lesson,
we'll talk about alternative methods for obtaining data beyond downloading,
and extracting data from some popular data formats.
We'll talk about obtaining data through APIs and web scraping,
as well as extracting information from text files,
json files, and HTML files.
In the final few sections of this lesson,
we'll talk about how to work with relational and non-relational databases and formats.
Non-relational databases can contain data points
that are connected to or related to each other,
often organized in tables within the database,
making it simple to find and organize related pieces of information.
Unlike relational databases, data with
a non-relational databases doesn't have clearly defined relationships or connections.
For example think about text,
image and video formats.
Here we'll be discussing how to extract data from a SQL database,
which is a type of relational database that uses structured query language,
often shorten to SQL.
Then we'll learn about some concepts about non-relational data,
like non-relational databases and image formats.
Mastering these skills will set the stage for
the next phase of data wrangling assessment, so let's dive in.