For this demo, I'd like to introduce you to Beautiful Soup,
an HTML parser written in the Python programming language.
Beautiful Soup makes it easy to parse, navigate,
and extract information from HTML documents.
The name is derived from the Tag Soup,
which refers to the unstructured and difficult to parse
HTML found on a couple of websites.
Let's take a look at how to use
the Beautiful Soup library to extract data from an HTML file.
Here I'm using our HTML page on the book,
the language_of_flowers from archive.org
downloaded as an HTML file that we'll use for this demo.
I'm going to start by importing the Beautiful Soup library.
I'll then try to open the language_of_flowers_html page as the file object fp,
I'm then going to past this file object and the type of parser that I want to use,
which in this case it's an HTML parser to
the Beautiful Soup constructor assigning the result to the flower_soup variable.
Let's actually go ahead and look at Beautiful Soup's parsed output, flower_soup.
Note that we have a large HTML file here filled with many tags.
We'll be inspecting this in detail in a bit.
I would like to make this output a bit cleaner though,
by having a separate line for each tab.
Here what I can use is the pre-defined method that Beautiful Soup is offering that
prints the format in Unicode string of the HTML just for viewing purposes.
For example, although it's not obvious to see right away,
notice how in the original version before using predefine,
the title tags and the content are really all smushed in one line.
In the prettified version,
the title tags and the content between them is actually separated on different lines,
which makes it easier to understand what are
these tag being used for and what's going on between the tag.
Now, I could also switch over to
my text editor for a better way of viewing the HTML if I wanted to.
Let's now navigate the website.
Looking at the HTML of the webpage,
one of the first things that we may want to do is
programmatically extract the title of the webpage.
We can see that the title is neatly nestled within
the title tags in the first few lines of the HTML file.
We can use Beautiful Soup's find method to iterate over tags and
strings in the HTML document and find the first result where the title tag is used.
Let's go ahead and do this right now by using.find on
our flower_soup variable with the title text.
Now let's go ahead and print the output and we're able to
actually see the title along with the actual title tags.
But what is I only want to see the content between
the tags and not the actual HTML tags themselves?
Here I can use.text on the outputs of the final result
and then.strip to remove any leading and trailing spaces of the text.
Now we can actually see the content of the title without the HTML tags.
Let's try again on a different tag.
Here I want to look at the username of the person who uploaded the book on archive.
Now, there are multiple a tags that we're going to find as part of this HTML,
where an a tag is actually defining a hyperlink.
Now, what I'm going to go ahead and do is specify the specific class of
tag that I want to search for so that I can narrow down the results.
Assuming that I've already identified this beforehand,
I'm going to go ahead and specify to the find function my tag type as a
and the class of this tag as class = item-upload-info_uploader-name.
I've done just that here and provided it as input to the find function.
Now, take a look at the results after using.text on the output,
we see hank_b is the username of the uploader of the book, which is correct.
Let's look at an example of using one other function in Beautiful Soup, find all.
What happens if we have multiple items that we want to retrieve at once?
As an example, there are different collection items that this book is a part of.
Here in our case,
we actually have two;
Cornell University Library and American Libraries.
I want to get the texts nestled between the a tags with the class collection item.
As you can see here, the Cornell University Library and American
Library is pretty neatly nestled within this big a tag.
What I'm going to do is use Beautiful Soup to find all method specify
the tag that I want to search for as an a and the class as collection item.
Now what is this going to do is return
all results in the HTML that match these conditions,
assigning it to collection items.
As we can see, collection items is output is a list.
Let's actually iteratively print the items in
the list and we'll use.text on each of them.
We can now see that we programmatically extracted
the two collections that the book belongs to from the a tag.
Now, if we want to use the.find function on the same use case,
it will only return the first result,
as we can see below,
which is why we do need to use the find all function.
A tool like Beautiful Soup is really useful for
reproducible workflows when you may need to extract the same data in the future again,
or if you need to use the same functions on HTML files with similar tags and structures.
However, sometimes if you're performing a one-off analysis,
you don't necessarily need to use Beautiful Soup.
In some cases, you may just copy the data in your browser
manually and just paste it into your data application, like Google Sheets.
For certain applications, you can also use special functions to make this easier.
For example, Google Sheets has
an import HTML function that can pull a list or a table from the HTML page.
We'll be looking how to pull a table from a particular Wikipedia article looking at
total fertility rate in India from the late 19th century to the earliest 20th century.
You're wearing Google Sheets and we're going to go ahead and use
the import HTML function, specifying the URL,
the type of objects that we want to pull,
which is a table actually that's on this Wikipedia page,
and the index of the table.
This particular table that we're trying to pull is the fourth table in the page.
Going ahead and running the function,
we can see after a couple of moments that it is
successfully loading the data into Google Sheets for us.