Throughout this lesson, we've talked about ways you can
download and store data on your local system,
such as by using basic Python file handling,
pandas to CSV function, json.dumps, etc.
But these methods and data storage don't always match up to
industry production grade means because they are problematic for large datasets.
Don't have clear cut standards on how the data is
structured and can make sharing data cumbersome for large teams.
Let's talk about a popular way of storing data through
a much more popular option, databases.
A database is organized collection of data that is structured to facilitate the storage,
retrieval, modification, and deletion of data.
They have a lot of great features,
including being very fast for accessing and writing data.
Having administrative features like access controls and
checks to ensure data is entered in the appropriate format, etc.
There are two main types of databases.
Relational databases, which store datasets that are
related to each other in a structural, tabular manner.
SQL or Structured Query Language,
is the standard language for communicating with relational databases.
We also have non-relational databases,
which stores datasets that are complex,
and cannot be captured in a tabular format like images or video.
Take a look at an example of how
the tabular data at the right is stored in a relational database.
Very similar to the format we're familiar with in Microsoft Excel.
This data is containing IDs for each of the rows in the data, and account ID,
and occurred at column capturing the date and time of an interaction event and
the channel which contains values like direct, Twitter, etc.
This dataset can help us answer questions like
how many viewers access to my site in a particular time period,
and by what channel?
Now, let's take a look at an example of using a SQL query where I only
want to get the rows in this dataset where the channel is Twitter.
We can use the select clause to
identify which elements from the database we want to pull.
In this case, we use the asterisk
indicating all of them meeting the following conditions.
Next, we specify from.
Here we want to pull data from a table called web events,
which is the table depicted on the right.
Next, we specify where to filter our results to indicate the channel as Twitter.
Now, take a look at the results on the screen where we see
the filter results showing all the rows where the channel is Twitter.
In the context of data wrangling, databases,
and SQL come into play typically when gathering data, or storing data.
That is connecting to a database and importing data into
a pandas DataFrame or
the analagous data structure in your preferred programming language.
Or storing data onto a database after you gather the data or clean the data.
These tasks are especially necessary when you have large amounts of data,
which is where SQL and other databases Excel over flat files.