Let's now go through a demo showing how to perform,
connect, and interacting with a database.
Often in the workplace,
instead of having to download files,
create web pages, hidden API, etc.
You may be given a database right at the beginning of a project.
Here, assume that our data is fully gathered and is ready to
store so that we can use it later or pass it onto another colleague or team member.
We'll connect to a SQL light database using SQL Alchemy the database toolkit for Python.
We're going to go ahead and start by importing Pandas and SQL Alchemy.
We're then going to read in a Rotten Tomatoes dataset using read CSV into a DataFrame.
We'll use df.head to print the first three rows as part of our DataFrame.
Let's go ahead and connect to our database.
We're going to start by creating a SQL Alchemy engine and
an empty database called Best of RT.db.
Now this Best of RT db isn't going to show up in our Jupyter Notebook dashboard yet.
Let's go ahead and run the earlier pieces of code.
Now we've just created our SQL Alchemy engine.
Next, let's actually go ahead and do something with it.
Let's store the data in our Rotten Tomatoes dataset in our Best of RT database.
We're going to go ahead and do this using Pandas,
very helpful two SQL function.
Now with the two SQL DataFrame method,
we're going to specify the name of the table as RT table,
our SQL Alchemy engine that we created earlier as the engine,
we're going to set index to false,
which means the DataFrames index is not going to be written as a column.
We're also going to set it exists to replace.
If the table RT table already exists,
Pandas is just going to drop or remove
the existing table before inserting the new values that I'm asking it to.
Let's run this piece of code on the DF that we loaded earlier.
Now we're finished.
The output 89 is indicating the number of
rows that were affected by the two SQL function.
Everything is perfectly well done.
Now let's go ahead and do something new.
Let's read the data in our database back into a Pandas DataFrame.
We're going to do this now using Pandas, read SQL function.
The first argument that we pass to this function
is a SQL query that needs to be executed.
Here we select all of the roles as indicated by the asterisk from RT table.
We then also pass the SQL Alchemy connectable through
engine.connect as one of the required arguments for read SQL.
Let's go ahead and do that. There we go.
We've now officially read data from
our SQL database back into a Pandas DataFrame and again,
using the dot head method can successfully start to look at
the first three rows in our DataFrame and make sure everything was read correctly.