There are many other data storage formats
out there that data maybe gathered and stored in,
including Excel, Pickle,
HDF5, SAS and STATA files.
Pandas is helpfully compatible with many of these formats,
which helps make data gathering and manipulation easier.
But how do you know when to use which file format?
Different file formats come in handy for different types of data.
For example, flat files are useful for tabular data.
But what about images,
such as PNGs or JPEGs?
Let's take a look at how we can load and modify this data briefly.
In this demo I'm going to introduce the Python Pillow library for loading,
modifying, and saving image data.
It's a very popular image library for use cases like radiology images in healthcare,
for images used for interactive shopping experiences and more.
Here I've already pulled a goldfish image from
a very popular image dataset in the machine learning and AI space called ImageNet,
which contains about 14 million images in total.
Let's dive in.
First I'm going to go ahead and import
the image module from the Pillow library, which is called PIL.
I'm then going to go ahead and load my image into my notebook using image.open.
My image is called goldfish.JPEG,
and it's in the JPEG format.
I'm then going to use.show,
on the image object to show you the image in the notebook.
We can now see this image of a goldfish.
Let's check out the size of the image.
The width of our image is 376 pixels,
and the height is 263 pixels.
Now let's do a little bit of data manipulation.
Note how our goldfish is looking at the bottom-right corner of the image.
Let's flip our image upside down.
I'm going to use pillows transpose function,
and then provide the flip
top bottom parameter as input to actually flip our image from top to bottom.
I'm thinking use.show on this image,
and now running this code we can see that our goldfish image is flipped,
and now I'm officially looking at the top-right corner.
How do I save my image?
I can do this by using.save,
on the image object, im.
I'm also specifying my file path here.
Now if we go ahead and navigate back,
we can successfully see that the image would be saved as part of Jupitor.
Now as we're talking about complicated kinds of
data that don't have clear structure to them,
I'd like to introduce you to the idea of non-relational databases.
These are databases that can store data that is both structured and unstructured,
like text files or emails and media.
Let's take a look at MongoDB as an example,
which is a no SQL database or a database that doesn't only support SQL.
MongoDB as a non-relational database has a few unique features to it.
For data points that are related to each other,
it allows you to embed documents within other documents,
and store relationships between the data by including links within documents.
MongoDB also allows you to efficiently store and retrieve unstructured data,
like the data on the right taken from one of MongoDB tutorials.
If you were to store that in a relational database,
we would need multiple tables,
and would need to perform a join operation on
the tables to see all the information in one view.
MongoDB uses an alternative to JSON called BSON, or binary JSON.
Take a look at the JSON HelloWorld example here,
and BSON, where we see BSON is imposing a binary structure on JSON.
Now binary JSON can be traversed much more quickly compared to JSON,
and supports advanced types of data.
For example, it can differentiate between
integers or round numbers and floating point numbers,
or numbers with decimals.
While JSON cannot.