Data science experts and data analysts often approach data wrangling is a flexible,
multi-step process that offers various options.
For example, depending on the use case and the data itself,
some data wranglers choose to gather data from
many sources and combine their data before moving on to
the assessment and cleaning stages whereas
others choose to combine data after the cleaning stage.
There are a number of skills that you can learn to help you build this type of
decision-making expertise when presented with these choices.
Experts in this space also typically access different types of reliable data sources,
i.e, data sources that can be trusted.
Some examples of the sources used in industry include surveys,
data provided by governments,
data gathered by hospitals,
marketing data, and data gathered by Internet of Things devices.