First, let's talk about the easiest way to get data files on hand.
This is the case where an individual or an organization gathers the data
for you and simply hands over data files to you, the data wrangler.
They may do this by, for example,
sending the files via email or posting it on a Cloud storage service,
like Google Drive or Dropbox for you to download.
They may also host the data on a website or
a portal available to specific users or the general public.
When opening data files that were provided to you,
ensure that you know that the final is safe to open by checking this source
whether or not the file size seems accurate and potentially using a virus scanner.
Check the file extension as well and open it via the right application,
whether that's your operating systems notepad application,
Microsoft Excel, Google Sheets, or another application.