All the data gathering is the first step of a Data Wrangler workflow.
It can actually be incredibly complicated in order to get the data that you need,
and involves a number of different steps that you'll
need to identify as part of your workflows.
Why? Well, even if you're only working with files on hand,
you may have multiple data files from different sources,
multiple data files from the same source,
files dedicated to explain the variables in your data,
sometimes known as data dictionaries, and more.
Zip files, and.tar.gz files
for Unix systems are a popular way to compress multiple files,
and are useful for data gathering workflows.
Being able to programmatically unzip files is great for reproducible data workflows.
So another analyst doesn't have to perform many manual steps when reproducing your work.
Let's now take a look at how to programmatically unzip the file via Python.
Let's take a brief look at how to programmatically
unzip files with Python using the zip file module.
First, we start with importing the zip file module.
Then we're using a Python Context Manager to open the zip file,
which is a popular way in Python to efficiently manage resources that your programs need.
The width statement opens a zip file called file.zip in read mode,
and creates a zip file object called a zip_ref.
Then the extract all method is called on the zip_ref object to
extract all the files from the zip archive into a directory named targetdir.