We all understand the importance of reproducible workflows.
Programmatic approaches towards these are an excellent starting point.
Here are a couple of tips to keep in mind as you're going about your mingling.
One, ensure your folder names are descriptive and consistent.
Take a look at an example on the screen where we use the ISO date format, year,
month, and day, and provide a description of the type of data that would be contained.
Your use case may require a specific naming convention.
You may also consider using hyphens or underscores instead of spaces
in the zip file to make it easier to programmatically access your data folders.
Two, make sure the sub-files are also named constructively.
For example, if you're grouping data by time within the zip folder,
use the ISO date format for those individual folders and files too.
Three, create a clear and consistent structure of files within the zip folder.
For example, you may group all data corresponding to
a specific microscopy sample under a folder called 202303 Sample A,
or group all data collected in a single day under a folder titled, with the day.