If you're an avid computer user,
you've most probably already encountered flat files through.txt and.csv files.
Flat files are simple data files that have a uniform format.
There are a number of different types of files that fall
under the flat files category including text files,
comma separated values or.csv files,
and tab-separated values or.tsv files.
All of these types of files typically have a few things in common.
They are tabular data in plain text.
Each line is a single date record.
Each record has one or more values or fields.
These values or fields are separated by delimiters or
some character like tab spaces, comments, or semi-colons.
Let's look at an example flat file from Rotten Tomatoes.
Rotten Tomatoes is a popular website that provides reviews for movies and television.
They also provide rankings and additional metrics from critics,
such as the score that a critic attributed to a movie or a show.
Unfortunately, Rotten Tomatoes isn't providing a file to download,
so we're going to give it to you for this part of the lesson.
Now let's take a look at the data.
On the screen, you can see a small preview of our data.
We've pre-gathered the Rotten Tomatoes dataset on the top 100 movies with four columns.
The ranking of the movie,
the critic score attributed to the film,
the title of the movie,
and the number of critic ratings.
This dataset has 101 data records or rows,
each on a different line,
but I'm only showing you the first 11 rows here.
Why 11 and not 10?
Well, the first row is for the headers and the rest are the data records.
This file is a tsv file,
which stands for tab separated values,
meaning that it uses spaces to separate the different values within a single data record.
Take a brief look at how two different flat files look in a text editor.
On the left, we have the tsv file with the tab-separated values.
On the right, we've got the comma separated values or the csv file.
Again, with this file,
the first row represents
the header variable names and the subsequent lines are the data records,
with each line being one data record.
The data values within a record are delimited by tabs spaces or commas.
We know that.txt files can be a type of flat file,
for example they can contain data with a tabular structure and with delimiters.
The file to the left, for example,
looks very similar to a csv file,
but with the semicolon delimiter,
and it's a flat.txt file.
However,.txt files do not have to be flat files.
Here's an example to the right where we see
unstructured text content which is not a flat file.
Stay with us to learn more about how to wrangle this type of unstructured data.
It's also important to note that in.xls or
Microsoft Excel file contains much more advanced features like
multiple sheets and different types of formatting that make it different from
flat files that are storing data as part of a tabular structured.
Take a look at this example.
When you open a.xlxx file in Microsoft Excel,
the data appears in a tabular format.
However, the files are actually in a binary format,
specifically designed for Microsoft Excel.
If you attempt to load them in a text editor,
you will find that the content is not human-readable.