Let's now walk through a short demo of how to work with flat files i.e.
tsv and csv files in Python.
I have a very tiny synthetic dataset on
individuals taking intelligence and emotional quotient tests.
My data consists of just three variables,
the rank of a test-taker,
their name, and their test type, IQ and EQ.
First, we'll go ahead and import the pandas library.
We'll then take a look at opening
a tab-separated file with this data using Python's native open function.
Here we define an empty list.
Then we open the file using Python context manager.
With a line, with open tiny_tsv.tsv as tsv file,
the width statement is opening the tsv file named
tiny_tsv.tsv in read mode which is the default mode,
and creates a file object called tsv file.
Inside the loop, the current line is processed as follows.
We go ahead and use the Rstrip function in order to
remove the newline character backslash n from the end of the line.
We then also use the split method which takes a delimiter, in this case,
the tab character T and splits this line into a list of values based on this delimiter.
Tiny_tsv_list.append is going ahead and
appending the resulting list of values to the tiny_tsv_list.
Now after this loop completes,
tiny_tsv_list contains the data from the tsv file.
If we print the list,
we can now see our tsv is parsed with Python and nicely formatted as a list of lists.
Each inner list represents a row of data and
each value within the inner list corresponds to a column value.
However, the popular way of doing this is simply using the pandas library.
Here we're importing the pandas library.
Pandas is a popular data manipulation library in Python,
providing powerful data structures like DataFrames.
Next we're using the pd.read_csv function on the tiny_tsv.tsv file.
Although the function is named read_csv,
it can also read tsv files by specifying the separator or delimiter.
In this case, the separator is set to the tab character
indicating that the file uses tabs, to separate values.
This function is returning a DataFrame object containing the data from the tsv file,
which has been assigned to the variable df_tsv.
Let's see what df_tsv looks like.
This data is now displayed nicely in this type of tabular format.