We talk about confusion matrices in different contexts where we looked at
seven different male politicians from George Bush to Gerhard Schroeder,
and we ran an eigenface analysis,
extracting the principal components of the dataset,
and then reuse the eigenfaces to remap new faces to names in order to identify people.
I'll give you a typical output,
and we're going to study the output using confusion matrices.
Take the resulting features,
put it into a support vector machine,
and then go through the data and count how often any of
those people were predicted correctly or misclassified.
Just to [inaudible] everybody, in this example,
we follow the convention of putting the true names,
the true class labels on the left and the predicted runs on top.
For example, this number one over here was truly Donald Rumsfeld,
but was mistaken to be Colin Powell.
We know its Colin Powell because the same name is over here,
from Ariel Sharon to Tony Blair,
apply to the columns over here.
Ariel Sharon is on the left,
and Tony Blair is on the right.
We'll ask you a few questions now.
First, a simple one.
Which of those seven politicians was most frequent in our dataset?