You might not have noticed but in the previous lesson on
linear regression your predicted response variable was not constrained at all.
That means, that with the right inputs it was possible to predict the house that
has a negative price or that the height of an individual is 80 feet.
Using logistic regression as opposed to linear regression,
bounds our response to a probability between zero and one,
rather than any possible value like you saw with linear regression.
Mathematically, to perform logistic regression,
we need to change the labels of fraud or not,
success or failure and the other variables to only a one and zero outcome.
So, in the credit card transaction example,
you could call all the fraud cases one,
while all the non-fraud cases would be zero values.
Then, logistic regression is set up in a way where
our linear model will predict the log odds instead of predicting the response itself.
Here, P is the probability of a one value occurring.
So, this is a ratio of a probability of an event
occurring as compared to the probability of the event not occurring.
This is called the odds ratio and by taking
the log and equating this to our linear regression line,
we control our predictions to be between zero and one for the probability of a success.
With a bit of algebra,
you can change the equation using the log odds to look
like this and this solves for probability directly.
This function here is called the sigmoid.
The sigmoid function takes the value from
your linear regression line and maps it between zero and one as a probability.
Both of these equations are commonly
used to understand the setup for logistic regression.
Let us get some practice with this.