In this video, we're going to work through
the logistic regression solution here that shows
both how you fit the logistic regression model
as well as how you might interpret some of the results from it.
Let's go ahead and do this together.
The first part here is importing our libraries and reading in the dataset.
Just go ahead and run that. You can see this is the dataset that we're working with.
Each transaction has its own row.
Then there's three things that we know about that transaction.
We know how long it took,
whether or not it was a weekend or a weekday,
and then whether or not it's fraud or not.
This first part actually,
is just looking at creating some of
the dummy variables we're going to need to fit into the x metric of our model.
This first thing is basically just saying, hey,
create a dummy variable for the day,
this day column, and then pull the week day off and store that back onto the DataFrame.
We could actually look at just pulling this get_dummies part, it can be useful.
You can see this returns two columns,
a weekday and a weekend.
This part here is just pulling the weekday column
off of this and then storing it into the DataFrame weekday portion.
You'll notice that weekday,
if we look up here,
if it's a weekend, weekday is zero.
Then here in row three,
you can see we have a weekday and that gets a one.
The weekend is just the opposite.
If weekday is a zero,
then weekend is a one and these are redundant.
We only need one of these and so it doesn't really matter which one you keep.
But in this case,
we kept the weekday down here. That's what that looks like.
Basically, it's storing the 0,
1 values back onto our original DataFrame.
Then similarly, we can run get_dummies on fraud.
Again, it can be useful to just look at this part.
If we look at the get_dummies for fraud,
basically false and true come back.
Similar to week day,
if this value is a one,
then this value is a zero.
There's no cases where it's both false is one and true is one.
The idea here is we're adding two columns back onto our DataFrame,
one, when it's false, these are in order.
If it's false then it's not fraud and so that goes into the not fraud column.
If it's true, then that goes into the fraud column,
and then I'm basically just dropping that not fraud column right after that.
Because if we're going to predict whether or not it's fraud,
we can just use this fraud column,
we don't need both of them.
We could also do something similar to here,
where we just pull off the true and then store it into the fraud column if we wanted to.
These two lines basically do the same thing as this weekday line,
but just with the fraud column.
Then what we can do is we can take a look at our DataFrame again just to understand.
But you can see it has all the original columns that we had before,
but now we've added this fraud column and
this weekday column to the end, so we can use those.
Instead of having the word versions of these things,
we need number of values that we can pass into our models.
This next part is just looking at some summary statistics about these things.
Here we have the average for the fraud,
we have the average for the weekday.
What proportion of weekdays are in the dataset,
what proportion of frauds are in the dataset,
and then what's the average duration for both fraud and not fraud?
If we take a look at this, we can see that about 1% of the dataset is fraud, 34,
35% of transactions happen on weekdays,
and the average duration for when a transaction isn't fraud is about 30 minutes,
whereas when it is fraud it's closer to five.
That could be a good telltale sign that that might be useful in a model for
predicting whether something's fraud or not is the duration.
With that we can fit a logistic regression model.
Here what we're doing is just adding that intercept in and then basically this is
saying predict the fraud column using the intercept,
the weekday, and the duration.
Use this column, this column, and the intercept,
which is just ones as a placeholder and predict this fraud column or not.
That's what this part is doing.
We can ignore the warnings up here.
But the idea is that when we fit this,
we get a bunch of coefficients that we can
interpret and we get p values associated with them.
You can see that the weekday,
and the duration are both statistically significant.
The P values are very small for these things.
They're both statistically significant in predicting whether or not something is fraud.
They're both useful for predicting if something is fraud.
If someone were to ask,
based on the duration of this transaction,
do you think it's fraud or not?
We could say, yeah,
I know that duration is useful, and in particular,
what I see up here is if it's a really fast transaction,
I think it's more likely to be fraud.
Then in terms of weekday, we'd say,
hey, if it's a weekday or a weekend,
does that tell you something about fraud.
The p value says, yeah, it does.
That's some of the ways we can use these results.
We could talk about interpreting these coefficients and some of the other videos.