If you dive back into the models we fit using Scikit-learn,
you'll notice we didn't get as much information back,
regarding the coefficients in terms of the p-values.
Even if you pulled the coefficients,
they don't actually match what was retrieved using the statsmodels library.
The shift from statistics to machine learning,
is one in which we care less about the relation of the inputs to the output,
and one where we care about predicting the output correctly regardless of the input.
The Scikit-learn library is one of
the most popular machine learning libraries and therefore,
the tools in this library,
are just aimed at the second point.