If you're preparing for a data scientist interview,
here's a question you need to be ready to answer.
If you're building a linear regression model with
a single independent variable and an intercept,
how many coefficients are you calculating?
In order to answer this question,
we have one independent variable which would have a coefficient attached to it,
and you'd also have an intercept
that doesn't have any independent variables attached to it.
You would have two coefficients in this linear model.
One of the coefficients would tell you how that independent variable
affects another the response variable of your model.
Then the intercept is this placeholder of where it would start.
You can imagine drawing this line.
The intercept is where the line starts,
and then the slope of this line is the other coefficient,
and along the x-axis is this independent variable that you're looking at.
Then along the y-axis is your response variable.
That's you want to relate age and height,
and you could have age on the x-axis,
height on the y-axis.
The most common height as the starting point and then for each year older,
how much taller do you get is the slope of this line,
and that's the other coefficient.
Where the line starts, the slope of the line.
Those are the two coefficients in the model.
Another question you'd want to be prepared for if
you're interviewing for a data scientist interview is,
does logistic regression predict a categorical target or numeric target?
The way that you answer this question is that it predicts a categorical target.
Logistic regression is aimed at predicting usually (1, 0) outcomes.
Yes, no outcomes. Did you make it or not?
But basically, these binary categories.
Linear regression is used for quantitative outcomes.
Which part of a linear regression result tells you whether
an independent variable is a statistically significant impact on the dependent variable.
In this case, this is the p-value,
and it's the p-value associated with that specific coefficient.
In a linear model,
you basically get all of your coefficients and a p-value attached to them.
Each of those p-values tells you if
that specific independent variable is
related to your response or your dependent variable.
Usually, we use a threshold like (0,
5), and if your p-value is less than that,
then that suggests that that particular variable
is responsible for a statistically significant impact on the response.
Which part of a linear regression result tells you whether
an independent variable has a practically significant impact on the dependent variable?
Practical dependence is usually related to
how high the impact is or how much the impact is on the response.
In these cases, it would be the coefficient themselves.
The p-value is the statistically significant.
But then let's say,
you want to know if you're developing a drug to make people live longer,
but it makes you live statistically significant longer by 37 seconds.
Well, that's statistically significant,
but it's not very practically significant and not going
to be able to do anything in those 37 seconds.
That's probably more meaningful than that you couldn't have done in the earlier parts.
But practical significance might say, Oh,
does it let me live 20 years or three year,
or 20 more years,
or 30 more days or depending on your situation.
But in any case, the practical significance
here is associated with the coefficient in the model.