I think it's really important,
and this is common with not just linear regression,
but with any statistical technique that you do.
Being very hyper aware of all
of the possible caveats of the analysis that you're doing is super important.
Almost everything that we do in the real-world is
just an estimation process with statistics, and therefore,
there are plenty of ways that you can answer things incorrectly or do
things wrong if you aren't aware of the assumptions or
some of the things that are associated with whatever technique you use,
whether that's a linear regression model,
whether it's hypothesis testing,
whether you're building confidence intervals,
whether you're using really complex methods like Monte Carlo methods,
or you're building really complex models like
ensemble-based methods or deep neural networks,
there are always assumptions being made.
So being hyper aware of what those assumptions are,
or some of the things that can go wrong with your analysis are
super important to make sure that you don't just drive
100% into some decision that has
this loophole that you weren't aware of or has this assumption that you weren't aware of.
I think, with really complex models,
you almost need to be more afraid of overfitting into certain situations,
and then thinking that's going to drive the right answer in every situation.
Then with simpler modeling techniques like linear regression,
you need to be more aware that the model is very simple,
and therefore, might drive to conclusions that are oversimplified and that
are not necessarily taking into account all of the complexities of the world.
They're on the two extremes.