In the last video you saw some output that had
the following information regarding the coefficients and our logistic regression model.
Similar to in the regression case,
we might use the p values here to help us understand if
a particular variable was
significant in helping us predict if a transaction was fraud or not.
Furthermore, we can interpret
these coefficients but not exactly in the way that you've seen before.
First, we need to exponentiation each of the coefficients.
Then, with quantitative variables we would say,
for a one unit increase in your explanatory variable,
we expect a multiplicative change in the odds of
being in the one category to be the exponential of your coefficient,
holding all other variables constant.
The way you encode dummy variables in
logistic regression is exactly the same as in multiple linear regression.
So interpreting the dummy variable coefficients is only
changed again by exponentiating the coefficient.
You can then interpret the exponentiated coefficient
attached to your dummy variable in a similar way as before.
In this category as compared to the baseline,
we expect a multiplicative change in the odds of being in the one category of this value,
holding all other variables constant.
This might seem confusing now but let's try it out and you'll see that it isn't so bad.