Congratulations, you've successfully gathered
your data and extracted it into the right format.
Now, it's important to assess your data for any issues before you're
ready to be able to unlock the value and the insight that you want out of your data.
Poor quality data can have a devastating impact on
a data wrangler and other stakeholders relying on the data that you've gathered.
Deal with issues can make findings from the data completely inaccurate and unusable.
It can also slow analysts significantly when trying to perform
downstream tasks like visualizing or modeling after data wrangling.
By addressing these issues upfront,
you'll ensure a smoother and more accurate analysis,
ultimately benefiting all parties involved.
During the data assessment phase,
data wranglers determine what tasks need to be done during cleaning.
Wranglers typically look for two types of bad data.
Dirty data, which is essentially data with
quality issues like missing data or incorrect data.
Data typically gets dirty due to issues when entering data records,
for example, or your data not following common rules and not being checked consistently.
Dirty data can sometimes put all your gathering efforts to waste if not treated.
For example, can lead you to form inaccurate conclusions about your data.
There's also messy data,
which is data that has specific structural issues.
There are many reasons that data gets messy and it can
happen during or after the gathering process.
For example, the data given to you is ambiguous or unclear.
Consider a medical practitioner that's jotting
down medical observations on a piece of paper.
How do you then transform this to a neat text or flat file?
Or let's say your data comes from multiple sources.
Think about customer data from multiple platforms such as a website,
mobile app, and social media.
The data may also be stored using different naming conventions,
date formats, or even currencies.
Messy data can slow you down when you analyze,
visualize, or model the data later.
To identify these data issues,
data wranglers typically use
both visual methods like looking at data through a spreadsheet software like Excel,
and programmatic assessment, like using [inaudible] to inspect the data.
What's the difference between data assessment and data exploration?
With data exploration, you typically look through your data without
a specific structure and try to familiarize yourself with it at a broader scale.
With data assessment,
data wranglers adopt a more systematic approach to pinpoint,
analyze, and quantify the data issues.
Now you may sometimes leverage data exploration during data assessment
and other times before or after the assessment process.