There are some common issues that make data messy.
Column header is being values rather than variable names.
Multiple variables being stored in one column,
variables being stored in both rows and columns.
Multiple types of observational units being stored in the same table,
and a single observational unit being stored in multiple tables.
Data wranglers can use them as
a basic guidance to figure out whether their data is messy.
In this section, we'll leverage the same concepts of directed and
non-directive visual assessment for data quality to identify issues with data structure.
Now, let's dive into these problems.
Take a look at this first example of untidy data.
Here, we have the score data for students who took
five tests with the scores ranging from 0-100.
We have the names of the students as the first column
and different ranges of test scores as part of the header.
Within the table, we have how many tests taken by
a student falling within each score range for example,
Amy scored less than 50 marks on one of her tests and scored
between 50-70 marks on four of her other tests.
Notice how the column headers at this dataset are values,
which makes it complicated to understand the data.
Nevertheless, programmatically parse it.
This can easily be detected visually by looking at the header of the table.
Take a look at the right table where the data has been restructured.
We now have three columns: one for the name of the student,
one for each of the test score categories,
and one for the frequency.
Now, take a look at the example on the left,
where we have two columns in our data set that are
supposed to correspond to a student's names and their test scores.
However, notice how in the name column the values
are structured and students names hyphen their age.
Here, we actually have two variables,
name and age, that are being stored in a single column.
If we wanted to access students age,
we would have to do unnecessary parsing of the name column just to get to these values.
We can instead separate out these columns as we see in the right,
so multiple variables are stored in separate columns.
Here's a very simple example of
another common data tidiness issue variables being stored in both rows and columns.
Here we have the student's name, their age,
and some optional tests that they can opt into,
and their test scores.
Notice how the category of tests A, B, C,
or D is stored across the column and the test scores are being stored across rows.
We can also see that there's a number of NA values for
students who decided not to take some of the optional tasks.
Overall pretty confusing.
Let's see one way that we can consolidate this data.
Take a look at the new DataFrame on the bottom.
Now we have student's name and age,
and we now have the test category as a separate column.
We also have the test score for the cases where students did take the test.
We can avoid unnecessary NA values with the score column.
We do see some duplicated grows, for example,
Marc and Naima's name and age are repeated multiple times,
which we may also need to clean during the cleaning stage.
I'd like to introduce a new movie ratings dataset to you,
where we have a couple of columns.
The movie ID corresponding to an ID associated with the movie,
the movie title of a viewer score,
the viewer or in other words,
the reviewer's name, their income, and their age.
Now, the context of this dataset may immediately appear to be confusing.
Here, we're defining the observational unit as an individual movie,
which includes data on its ID, title, and score.
Where is the viewers income and age coming into the picture?
This is a case of multiple types of observational units stored in the same table.
In this case, the viewer's information is
a separate observational unit, the individual viewer.
Let's separate this information into two tables.
On the table on the bottom left,
you can see we kept intact the movie ID,
title, and reviewers core columns.
On the right table, we have information about our viewer as the observational unit,
including their name, income, and age.
If we ever want to merge the two tables again for easier access to this information,
we can do so using the movie ID key.
Take a look at the two data tables on the screen.
The left one contains information on a movie,
it's ID and the viewer's name.
The table on the right,
also contains the movies ID,
but with columns corresponding to the review and rating.
At times when gathering data,
data may be split into many tables.
Just visually we can see here then we would be much more
simpler if both tables were combined using the ID key.
We could get all the information about
the individual movies i. e our observational unit in a single table.