In this short demo, let's go over a couple of
Pandas' methods for programmatically accessing data structure,
which often involves a combination of visual and programmatic assessment.
Again, we're picking on our synthetic clinical trial data,
this time looking at a couple of tables.
Here, the new table that we're adding in is our adverse reactions table that's centered
around telling us the adverse reactions that patients had as a result of the treatment.
In this demo, focusing on the patient's treatments and adverse reactions tables,
let's go ahead and take a look at
the first few rows of the tables using the dot head function.
Note how the adverse reactions tables,
including the name of patients,
their first name and their last name essentially,
as two individual columns and the adverse reaction.
We also have the visual inspection for the treatments DataFrame here as well.
Let's use one of the functions we're familiar with,.info.
We're going to start using.info to inspect our two tables.
Let's go ahead and skip over to the adverse reactions inspection.
Notice how there are only 34 entries in the adverse reactions DataFrame.
We can use a few other methods to closely
inspect some of the columns and shape information.
For example, let's get the.shape using
the.shape method on the adverse reactions DataFrame.
Here we're getting the dimensionality of the DataFrame showing us
that the table has 34 rows and three columns.
We can also use the columns method to get
all of the column labels in our dataset programmatically.
Finally, we can also use the.index method to
understand the index of the adverse reactions table,
in this case ranging from 0-34.
While this doesn't seem particularly useful for this dataset right now,
for datasets with more complex indexes and for operations like dropping duplicate rows,
it can be helpful to quickly access the index.
Now with all of this information that we've gathered,
we can start to make some assessments around the data structure.
We can start to determine that the adverse reaction column of
the adverse reactions table should actually be
included in the treatments table through visual assessment.
Why? Well, when looking at the treatments table here below,
we can see that the adverse reaction for that treatment
has same observational unit as the treatments table,
which is the treatment data for an individual patient.
Since the given name and surname columns are
present in both the adverse reactions and treatments tables,
when cleaning the dataset,
we can use these two variables to combine the two tables into a single table.
This is a case of an issue,
a single observational unit is being stored in multiple tables.
Here are a few additional issues.
We can visually see a case where variables are stored in both rows and columns.
In the treatment table, the Auralin and Novodra columns contain three variables.
Which treatment the patient is using,
Auralin or Novodra,
which is stored in the header row,
and the start dose and the end dose separated by the dash.
Let's use programmatic assessment to supplement our visual assessment.
We can programmatically verify that an individual patient is recorded as
taking only one drug by
checking that the corresponding column for the other drug is empty.
For instance, if a patient is taking Novodra,
their record should have values in the Novodra column and be empty in the Auralin column.
In other words, no patients should be taking both drugs simultaneously.
The Auralin and Novodra columns can both have values at the same time. Let's check this.
We can do this by getting the rows where
both the Auralin and Novodra columns are not empty in our treatments' DataFrame.
We can see that there are no cases of rows that are applying to this case.
In the cleaning stage,
we can actually simplify our data structure and
solve this issue by creating three new columns.
One for the treatment specifying Auralin or Novodra,
another for the starting dose,
and a third for the ending dose.
This updated structure will make it easier to analyze and work with the data while
ensuring that there are no inconsistencies
regarding patients taking both drugs simultaneously.
Let's take a look at the patient's DataFrame and actually turn to another issue.
We can visually see through the.head function and
issue of multiple variables being stored in one column.
The contact column in the patient's table contains two variables,
phone number, and email.
Let's investigate this further programmatically from a validity standpoint.
Are all the values in our data following the format of email,
no space by immediately followed by a phone number?
Using value counts, we can actually see
that one of the values in our dataset for example,
is actually violating this with the phone number first followed by the email.
Because of this, it's going to be challenging to use
string manipulation to parse and separate these.
Because there isn't any standard format that these combined data points are following.
We need to make sure that this issue is solved in
the cleaning stage by creating two columns,
one for the email address and the other for phone number.