To understand dirty data,
let's consider the idea of data-driven farming,
which ultimately helps the agricultural value chain.
Suppose we're gathering GPS data on crop yields at the beginning of a quarter,
this data is then going to be used to forecast
the equipments and resources needed for the quarter.
However, due to atmospheric interference,
the GPS data is inaccurate.
Without identifying this data issue and assessing its impact on the data,
we will make incorrect forecasts from the inaccurate data leading to losses.
Inaccurate data represents just one example of a data quality issue.
Low data quality or dirty data hinders data from being used for its intended purposes.
Ensuring high data quality is crucial for obtaining
reliable insights and driving informed decision-making.
Let's draw the same example to talk about messy data.
Our data gathering device is gathering GPS and geospacial data.
But when it stores this data,
it just jumbles all the information into one long line.
Here we have the latitude,
longitude, and date data all at once.
If we had 100 of different records
of this kind of data and just wanted to look at the dates.
It could be really hard to apply any kind of code to
this data because all the information is in one line.
A better way to organize this data is adapting it to a tabular format.
I could then have my latitude, longitude,
and date be individual columns and then focus only on the date column,
like performing additional assessment and cleaning
without having to deal with latitude and longitude.
Messy data, ie,
data with bad structure can be a roadblock for initial data inspection and assessment.
It's important to adapt and fix messy data into a structure
that your tools are compatible with so that the rest of the assessment;
cleaning and using of the data is much easier for you.