Every dataset can be dirty in its own way.
It's impossible to list all of the issues that you may encounter with
datasets that are out there in the wild after we've gathered them.
But we can attempt to categorize them into issues so
that we can more easily understand and identify them.
Here, I'm going to be showing you five different attributes or
dimensions of data quality corresponding to dirty datasets.
These are accuracy, completeness,
validity, consistency, and uniqueness.
How do you know when your data contains all the info you need?
Completeness is a metric that helps you understand whether your data is
sufficient for you to answer interesting questions or solve your problem.
Lack of completeness is typically shown in missing data.
For example, if you are assessing data gathered in a survey,
you might encounter missing values.
This could resolve from participants that didn't want to share their information,
so they skipped certain fields in your survey.
In your dataset, this missing data may be represented as NaN values,
signifying the absence of information in specific fields.
One common way to fix completeness issues is removing the missing data.
Alternatively, you can replace the missing values
with default values or non-zero replacements.
For example, when dealing with missing values in participants' age fields,
you could fill in the gaps with the average age of
all the participants who provided their age,
rather than having the missing data points as NANs.
This method helps maintain the integrity of your dataset while
minimizing the impact of missing data on urinalysis.
How well does your data meet certain constraints?
Validity is a metric helping you understand how well
your data conforms to a defined set of rules for data,
which is also known as a schema.
These rules can be based on real-world constraints.
For example, if you are a health care practitioner gathering logs from a medical device,
are there certain invalid values that are not within the right range,
like 300 heartbeats per minute?
They can also be rules specific to your data.
For example, zip codes should be five integers,
like 12345, but not in a float format, 12345.0.
If data is not valid, it's not usable.
In some cases, if a data point doesn't meet the rules of your data,
you may even miss that it's there in the first place during assessment,
only to discover it during the later stage, like cleaning.
You can fix the validity issues by checking whether your data lies within
the right range and checking the data types of your variables.
How good is your data accurately representing the real world?
Accuracy is a metric that helps you understand whether your data
is accurately representing the reality that it aims to depict.
The danger with inaccurate data is that it can still pass validity tests.
But if you base your assumptions on it,
your findings could be completely wrong.
Consider the example where we're reporting data on patients' weights.
Due to a faulty scale,
all patients' weights in a given time period is
recorded as five lbs heavier than their true weight.
Although the values of the individual's weight will adhere to
the defined schema and perform well on the validity metric, it's still inaccurate.
It can be challenging to fix accuracy issues,
but there are two ways to do this.
One way is to keep checking the accuracy of
your data source to ensure the data isn't faulty.
The second approach is to cross-reference your data with other sources.
For example, you may confirm an email address is accurate by
associating it with the correct person on a subscription mail list.
How good is your data at matching data across sources and following standard rules?
Consistency is a metric that helps you understand two things.
Whether your data is following a standard format and whether
your data is info matches with information from other data sources.
Inconsistency also poses a unique danger because
inconsistent data can pass the validity and accuracy tests.
Consider two examples of inconsistency.
Let's talk about a tabular dataset where one column in your data
represents birth dates of patients in the month, date, year format.
Now another column represents sign-up dates of clients in the day, month, year format.
These columns are both valid and accurate individually.
But because of the lack of consistency in the format,
you cannot reuse the same assessment and cleaning
code to handle the date times for both columns,
even though they represent the same type of data.
Let's say now that the data within your dataset is consistent,
it denotes all data recordings coming from the year 2023.
However, another dataset stored elsewhere shows
the data recordings coming from year 2022. Which one is correct?
This data is both inconsistent and inaccurate.
Consistency can sometimes be easy to address.
In the first example, we would simply need to adopt
the same standard format within the data across the columns.
But fixing consistency issues can become challenging if the data is also inaccurate.
In such cases, ensuring accuracy and
cross-referencing data may be necessary before addressing consistency concerns.
How good is your data in not containing duplicate values?
Uniqueness is a metric that helps you understand whether
there is duplicate or overlapping values in your data.
Let's say you're collecting survey participant data on your marketing campaign.
In particular, your data has two rows.
One corresponds to the participant John K. Smith and other to John Smith,
but these are actually the same person.
Now you have two rows of data relating back to the same person.
Which row has the right information and which can be deleted?
Duplicated data can also unnecessarily
increase the size of your data, consuming valuable resources.
Additionally, it can cause downstream accuracy problems.
Detecting and removing duplicate data is crucial to
maintaining data quality and ensuring accurate insights.
Now there are some ways to prevent data duplication and overlaps,
including creating unique identifiers for each row,
line, or the equivalent in your data.
Other times, to fix uniqueness issues,
you can programmatically catch duplicate values and
remove the ones that are inaccurate or not needed regularly.