There are two types or styles of assessing your data, visual and programmatic.
Visual assessment is just opening your data and looking through it in
its entirety in Jupyter Notebook or via pandas,
a text editor, or a spreadsheet application, for example.
Programmatic assessment, like its name suggests,
uses code to view specific parts of the data,
like using functions or methods to summarize the data.
Like the df.info method, for example.
You can even plot the data.
When we assess data both visually and programmatically,
we'll get into the habit of identifying and documenting issues.
We can revisit whatever issues we found at the end of our assessment.
There are two primary types of visual assessment, directed visual assessment,
which involves systematically looking through each DataTable in
a Jupyter Notebook or spreadsheet application like Google Sheets or MS Excel.
Direct visual assessment can help detect issues such as missing values,
outliers, or inconsistencies in the data.
Suppose you are given a dataset in
a spreadsheet containing students test scores, names, and ages.
You can directly observe the data in the spreadsheet.
You may spot a student's age as 120,
which is likely an error that needs correcting.
In this case, you're directly looking at the raw data
and identifying potential issues or patterns.
Unfortunately, some datasets are so large that
spreadsheet programs will crash when trying to open them.
Sometimes you may need to truncate the data for viewing purposes,
for example, only view the first few rows.
Non-directed visual assessment is when you look at different portions of tables closely,
such as scrolling through the data in search of intriguing and relevant issues.
Upon spawning something noteworthy,
you can then narrow your focus to investigate that particular aspect in greater detail.
Take the previous example.
You begin scrolling through the student's data casually,
observing any patterns or anomalies that catch your eye.
While scrolling, you noticed several instances where
students have the same name and age but different test scores.
Intrigued by this auditing,
you decide to investigate further to determine whether these are
genuine cases of students with the same name and age,
or if there are data quality issues such as duplicate entries,
or inaccuracy that need to be addressed.
In this case, you are now focusing on particular issues or errors.
Let's take a look at a dataset example with the data of students names,
ages, and scores on a test that I'm calling testing.
Let's do some simple visual assessments.
After reading the CSV file,
I use the dot head function with the value 10 to show the first 10 rows of the DataFrame.
Truncating my view of the dataframe,
so I don't display 200 rows all at once.
Now let's take a look at the DataFrame starting with
direct visual assessment with the name column.
One of the first things that we can notice is this question mark character in Roway for
Liem Gibson's name that was most likely caused by an issue with
an accent character not being supported by the encoding format.
This is an accuracy issue.
We also see the case of a student's age in Row 7 being 120,
which is inaccurate and most likely due to a data entry error.
Let's now take a look at the Test A score column showing students scores on Test A.
Note how each data point is documented as numbers followed by an apostrophe.
This means that pandas will interpret this data as a string rather than a number,
which means we won't be able to use this data for calculations.
This is a validity issue and is likely due to
poor planning by whoever is recording this information.
Let me direct you to another issue in Row 6.
Note how the numbers for the age and test score columns are not numerical,
but are instead strings.
Whereas all of the other numbers in these columns are written
with integer digits like 14 and 95.
This is a consistency issue.
This will be a big problem downstream,
since the Row 7 may not be considered when we get
summary statistics like the average age of the test taker.
We can find another issue using non-directed visual assessment.
The missing NaN values showing us that our data is not complete.
One final issue I'd like to pinpoint is some students have the same name and
age but different test scores like Amy Linn reported for the same test.
We should only have one row for each student,
which is a uniqueness issue.