In this demo, we'll be looking at a synthetic dataset of
Phase 2 clinical trial data for a new innovative oral insulin called Auralin,
a proprietary capsule that can solve stomach lining issues.
Three hundred and fifty patients are participating in this trial.
Half of the patients are being treated with Auralin and the other
175 being treated with a popular injectable insulin called Novodra.
By comparing key metrics between these two drugs,
we can determine if Auralin is effective.
Now note that Auralin and Novodra are not real insulin products.
This clinical trial data was fabricated with the consultation of real doctors to ensure
plausibility and reflecting real data issues
in the healthcare domain for the purposes of this course.
Phase 2 trials are intended to test the efficacy and
the dose-response of a drug and identify adverse reactions.
We have three data tables as part of this dataset, the patient's table,
which is giving us important information about our hypothetical patients,
like their gender, name,
height, weight, address, etc,
the treatments table, which is providing us with
information on the detailed treatment information.
This table includes the names of patients who participated in clinical trials,
the dosage of Auralin and Novodra and the patient's blood
sugar or hemoglobin levels indicated by HbA1c.
The Auralin and Novodra columns contain many useful information points.
The first number before the dash in this column is
the baseline median daily dose of
insulin from the week prior to switching to Auralin or Novodra.
The second number after the dash is
the ending median daily dose of insulin at the end of the 24 weeks of treatment.
Now both are measured in units, short-form u,
which is the international unit of measurement and the standard measurement for insulin.
TheHbA1c start column is
the patient's HbA1c level at the beginning of the first week of treatment.
Similarly, theHbA1c end column is
the patient's hemoglobin level at the end of the last week of the treatment.
Here our HbA1C change column is
the change in patient's hemoglobin levels from the start of the treatment to the end,
ie, it's theHbA1c start column minus HbA1c end.
This variable is determining the effectiveness of our insulin.
Finally, we have our adverse reactions table which is telling us
the name of the patient and whether or not they had an adverse reaction.
In this demo, we'll look at programmatic assessment of data quality,
where we will use pandas, functions,
and methods to reveal our data's quality.
Here I'm going to start off this demo by importing the pandas library and loading
in the synthetic Phase 2 clinical trial data
set for the hypothetical oral insulin called Auralin.
Here I'm loading our patients and treatments data tables
using read CSV into a pandas DataFrames.
In practice, programmatic assessment is often
a combination of programming and visual inspection.
Let's go ahead and kick-start this by looking at the treatments DataFrame,
which has a number of variables that are corresponding to patient treatment.
To take a look at the first few rows of our data,
we can use the.head method that we're now familiar with,
which by default prints the first five rows.
Now, if we want to look at the last few rows of our data to validate it was
loaded correctly and get a glimpse of how the data is at the end of the DataFrame,
we can use the.tail method in
a similar way which is displaying the last few rows of our data.
Here's one other method for looking at rows in the DataFrame,.sample.
Dot sample is an example method of non-directed programmatic assessment,
which means randomly leveraging
programmatic assessments without any directed goal in mind.
Dot sample returns, a random sample of records from the table.
In this case, for example df.sample returns
one entry randomly from the dataset and df.sample 5,
returns five random entries.
It's easy to make incorrect assumptions
from just viewing the head and tail of the dataset.
Plugging samples randomly from everywhere
helps you get a good understanding of the inners of datasets.
Additionally, using programmatic assessments to view random samples of data can help you
decide what to look for with more pinpointed visual and programmatic assessments.
One issue with.sample is that
random rows are picked each time that you run the function,
so the rows are different every time.
If you would like to ensure your implementation is reproducible,
you can use random seeds with.sample and sending the random state to an integer.
For example here I set the random state to two.
If you run this code block multiple times,
the row selected randomly do not change after each run.