Now let's go ahead and start looking for data quality issues programmatically.
I'm going to go ahead and start by calling the dot info method
to print a concise summary of a DataFrame of the treatments table.
This function is going to return values,
information on the number of entries, number of columns,
number of entries that are not null for each column,
the datatypes of each column and memory usage for the entire DataFrame.
Let's start with looking at a completeness data quality issue.
Looking at the summary of the information that's returned by dot info,
we can see that there's only 171 HBA1C change entries
while there are 280 entries for the other columns.
This indicates a completeness issue.
We're missing some data.
Let's actually now go ahead and look at a validity issue instead.
Erroneous data types are validity issues because they don't
conform to the defined schema of what the table should be.
Pay attention to the datatypes or D types of columns and check
whether each variable has the correct datatype. Let's look at this here.
What is immediately notable is the auralin and novodra columns.
Their datatype is object.
If we scroll up to the data table,
we actually see here that they are formatted in
this interesting two digits plus character u format.
Ideally, the values for these two columns would be formatted
as integers to make it easier to access this information,
which makes it a validity issue.
Let's now take a look at an accuracy issue.
We'll identify this by using the dot described method,
which generates descriptive stats for the numerical data types in your pandas DataFrame,
including the count, mean, standard deviation,
minimum value, 20,
50 and 75% quartiles,
and the maximum value in your data.
Recall that our HBA1C change variable determines the effectiveness of our insulin.
In terms of controlling blood sugar,
this variable's value of around 0.4 is considered a success,
so 0.9 is a really big change that we're seeing here that is somewhat implausible,
especially given that the 75th percentile is at 0.92.
The gap between the 25th and 50 percentile is only 0.04,
while it's nearly 0.6 between the 50th and 75th percentile.
What's going on here? If we look at
our visual assessment of the treatments table, which we have here,
we'll see that this HBA1C change variable for this
0.97 entry for Elliot Richardson is actually calculated incorrectly.
How? Well, 7.56 in our start column minus 7.09 in our end column is 0.47 not 0.97.
This is an accuracy issue that is actually skewing our values
for the 75th percentile or quartile and our max values.
How could this have happened?
It could be that the healthcare professional who recorded
this change variable had bad penmanship and therefore was read as a nine.
This sometimes happens, especially if
Optical Character Recognition Software was
used for transferring paper records to electronic records.
This data and accuracy is important to clean because
HBA1C changes the key metric for our clinical trial,
the deemed success or failure of this oral insulin hinges on this variable.
While missing data is typically a completeness issue,
there's also one other hint validity issue that we need to diagnose.
We can actually use the dot is now function to identify NA values in our dataset.
We can get the sum of this result to get the number of NA values.
However, the output of this function using someone dot is now on our auralin
and novodra columns is showing that there is zero null entries for both of these columns.
But if we scroll up to our treatments visual assessment,
the entries with these dashes that we're seeing here should actually be null values.
This is revealing a common error in datasets.
Misrepresenting missing values is something else like a dash just slash NA or none.
These dashes aren't being picked up as null or non-values,
which can be problematic when doing calculations on the data.
Misrepresenting missing values is a validity issue.
For the last few methods I'd like to show you,
I'm going to switch over to our patient's table for more complex example of consistency,
uniqueness and completeness, and validity issues.
Let's get started with consistency.
Let's narrow down on the weight column in the patient's table using the describe method.
Notice how the minimum weight is 48 pounds,
which looks pretty low.
See the average value here seems to be about 173 lbs.
To identify this further and figure out what's going on,
we can use the sort values method to sort values.
Here we go ahead and do this for the weight column from low to high weight.
We can see a value of 48 lbs is the minimum here,
but it seems to be an outlier as the next value starts from 102 and onwards.
Let's now get this exact row from the database by using the min function on
this column and then identifying the row in
the DataFrame where the column value is at its min.
Here using pandas indexing,
we can go ahead and get this exact row,
including the patient ID and the weight of this patient.
Let's go ahead now and check this strange anomaly by making an assumption.
Maybe for this patient the weight is being locked in
kilograms instead of pounds. Let's test that.
Here we convert the weight of the patient from
kilograms into pounds using the conversion factor,
we then get the height of the patient and calculate the BMI using the formula for It,
703 times weight by height squared.
After doing all of these calculations,
the BMI is coming up to 19.055.
Take a look at the reported BMI,
which we can access by indexing for this particular row.
Here we can see that rounded up,
the value is pretty much equivalent.
This means that this anomaly of the patient's weight was actually recorded in kilograms,
whereas the rest of the dataset is actually indicating weight in pounds.
This is a consistency issue with the unit measurement of weight data.
It's important to clean because we need to report average metrics like weight,
height, and more in terms of each treatment arm of the clinical trial.
As part of our final issues,
let's take a look at uniqueness and validity on our patients DataFrame.
Here we're going to apply a method called value counts to get
the number of unique values in our surname and address columns.
Note how there are six duplicates for the last name Doe,
and six duplicates for 123 Main Street as a patient's address. What's going on here?
We can check the details using.duplicated.
Here we define the subset parameter as input to
this pandas function as the subset equals surname address.
We're only looking to retrieve rows that have
duplicate surnames and addresses from our patient's table.
Now we find that there are several John Does that are living at 123 Main Street in
New York with the zipcode 12345.0 and the email johndoe@email.com.
This is a uniqueness issue because we have multiple duplicated rows in the dataset and
a validity issue because this data doesn't conform to
the defined schema of one record per patient.