What is analytical data?
As you start to encounter more data in the real world,
you'll come across a popular form of data called analytical datasets.
While the definition of analytical data can be quite broad,
it boils down to datasets that help us perform analyses,
such as data used for visualization and storytelling,
exploratory data analysis, statistical analysis,
descriptive or inferential, and training machine learning models.
Analytical data is sometimes created on top of master data,
where master data represents the core data across an enterprise.
For example, a product's revenue data might be master data and
analytical data may be looking at aggregations or trends of that data over time.
Data tidiness is particularly important for analytical data sets.
Since analytical data is typically used to
power business workflows and involves big data,
having consistent data structure across different tables can
therefore be a crucial element of having good analytical data.
Let's talk about a few other concerns outside of tidiness that apply in analytical data,
starting with merging different data sources together.
Let's say we're data analysts at a software vendor and have
gathered data around the revenue and customer base at the company's products.
This data is in three tables corresponding to customers, sales, and products.
Let's say we want to merge these three data sources
so we can have a single data store that's easier to keep track of.
When we're merging this data,
what entity or object should be the focus of our final merge to the data source?
For example, are we trying to focus specifically on groups of customers asking,
do customers in the US prefer these products over customers in Malaysia?
And what are the sales look like?
Or are we focusing primarily on individual products,
asking which products are more likely to
generate higher sales based on the customer data?
Unit of analysis refers to the primary entity or object being focused in the analysis.
It is the basic element that's being measured, observed, or analyzed.
A unit of analysis can vary depending on a problem or question statement.
It typically constitutes,
what is a single record of our analysis?
Now, defining a unit of analysis can be critical because it allows
you to structure and organize your data wrangling workflows,
but also the individual units between your data and across
different data tables in a neat and easier manner,
allowing you to form more accurate investigations as a result of that data.
When designing an analytical dataset,
you may also consider opportunities for
enriching your dataset by merging in additional data.
For example, if your dataset has zip codes in it,
you can find rich public data about that zip code,
like the population or average age.
How do you connect different tables together?
You can do this by defining unique keys
or unique identifiers when creating your database.
A unique key is some type of identifier that is held in common
across all the different tables that will allow you to tie the different data together.
Finally, when designing analytical dataset,
particularly data such as time series data,
you may consider the resolution or granularity of data.
For example, do you want to collect data from
your temperature sensor every day, week, or month?
You may also consider the level of aggregation, for example,
high-level data about populations and their trends can be
aggregated based on states, countries, and continents.