Before we get too far on this journey,
let's talk about setting up your computer to complete this Nanodegree program.
In this lesson, we'll walk you through installing Anaconda with Python three,
which will use throughout the classroom.
Additionally, we have some notes on installing different text editors.
I personally use Atom.
However, you can use any text editor you think is best for you.
Matt and I will be teaming up to show you the different workflows we recommend,
as they're most common in industry.
If you already have your machine setup the way you like,
feel free to skip this whole lesson.
If you're setting up your computer for
the first time and get stuck on any part of this lesson,
reach out for help on Slack,
and we'll help you get through.
Don't worry, you'll be able to work through the program as you continue to get setup.
There are workspaces available in the classroom to get through
the program if you don't want to do the work locally.
However, we strongly recommend getting the setup on your local computer,
as it will prepare you for working in industry.