Independent component analysis is
a method similar to PCA and random projection and that it
takes a set of features and produces a different set that is useful in some way.
But it's different in that PCA works to maximize variance,
ICA assumes that the features are mixtures of independent sources and it
tries to isolate these independent sources that are mixed in this dataset.
The classic example used to explain ICA is something called the cocktail party problem.
Let's look at a variation of this problem.
So, let's say that three of your friends go to an art show and there are three curtains.
One of them opens up and there's a person playing a piano there.
They play a nice tune on the piano,
you're in there to listen to it so you assume that it sounded good.
Then after a little bit of time
another curtain is uncovered and there is a person playing the cello.
The piano is still playing and then cello starts
playing but they're playing two different pieces.
They don't really work together.
There's sort of mixing together, and then,
the third curtain is opened and then there's a TV turned
on and there's this sign wave noise coming in.
It's a little bit of a mess.
So, here your friends decide that "Okay.
This is kind of interesting. Let's take our phones out and record this."
So, they record let's say six seconds of audio for this.
This friend was closer to the piano so they have more piano and they're recording,
this person was closer to the TV so they had more TV.
You have these three recordings and then each of them has
a different level of the original source which you don't have.
You don't have these recordings.
[piano and cello with faint TV noise] The first one sounds like this,
where the TV noise is a little faint and you can hear the piano and then the cello.
The second one there's a little bit more cello, [same music but cello and TV noise are louder]
and the TV got louder and the third one we can even see it here that the TV is little. [same music but TV noise is minimal]
So, if you have only these three recordings,
is there a way for you to retrieve the original signals?,
Datasets? The answer is yes.
That's what an example of what independent component analysis allows you to do.
ICA takes these three samples
or this dataset of sort of three dimensions and we tell it "All right,
there are three original components that were in there.
Can you find them in here?"
It would output piano.
When it's able to work,
it is able to isolate them and then the second output would
be the cello and then the TV.
So, this is a type of problem called the blind
source separation and that's the problem that ICA solves.