When you are finished manipulating your data,
it is time to communicate your results.
In order to do so, we'll need some additional techniques.
Descriptive statistics can provide us with concise and comprehensive insights.
We'll start by using the group-by functionality to aggregate our data in different ways.
Then we'll practice summarizing our data through summation,
measures of center, and measures of spread.
Next, we'll spend time learning the functionality within
pandas to create quick and robust visualizations.
These include but are not limited to histograms,
scatter plots, box plots,
bar plots, and pie charts.
With those descriptive statistics and visualizations,
we'll start to think about what conclusions we can draw from them.
Conclusions are generally derived by asking questions about the summary statistics,
which are further explored and answered with visualizations.
Finally, we will learn about the ways to change
our visualizations to help build effective conclusions,
including altering visualizations by figure size,
labeling, color, and visualization type.
Visualization is such a fun and
exciting area because it brings out the creative spark in you.
Let's dive right in and get started.