During this lesson, we explored various techniques to summarize our data.
Techniques including groupby,
summation, measurements, etc, and spread.
These helped us understand how our data operates.
We use the pandas plot method to learn
different visualization techniques for data plotting.
Building on these objectives,
we highlighted the significance of drawing
conclusions with our statistics and visualizations.
By tailoring our visuals for better communication,
we were able to effectively communicate a cohesive story.
Hey, great job.
You now should be comfortable communicating with your data.
In fact, it may be the most important part about being a data analyst.