Groupby is one of my favorite functions in pandas.
It lets you group your data and aggregate information about
those groups or perform group-specific transformations.
In this section, we'll focus on using groupby
to get summary statistics about different groups of data.
This notebook I read in the CSV for census income data.
Previously, we learned that we can get summary statistics
on the whole dataset with functions like describe and mean.
From this, I can find the mean of the whole dataset.
But what if I wanted to find the mean for each work class in the data?
You can use the groupby function combined with a mean function to do this.
We can even split the data by
multiple columns by using a list of the columns we want to group by.
Here we are grouping by work class and race to visualize how groups have different means.
If we want to keep the columns we grouped by in the DataFrame,
we can specify the as index parameter to false.
In this example, we are keeping the columns and only
selecting the capital gains to derive the mean values from each group.
Experiment with this notebook provided to better understand how groupby works.
We'll be spending time working on our datasets to draw a conclusion soon.