In this video, we'll go through some of
the most common and useful plots you can create with pandas.
Note that the plot methods on a series or
DataFrame are just simple wrappers around matplotlib functions.
This is why you might see them used interchangeably,
pandas is nice for quick insights,
but you'll need to use matplotlib to really dive into
details and customize your visualizations.
We'll get into this more later on.
Let's first use census income data to practice plotting histograms,
bar charts, and pie charts in pandas.
A really useful line to include when visualizing in
Jupyter Notebooks is the matplotlib in-line statement.
This lets you view your plots in the notebook.
A quick way to view histograms for
all numerical columns in a DataFrame is the hist function,
which we could call directly on the pandas DataFrame.
That was way too crowded.
Let's make our figure size bigger.
Also, we can use a semicolon to suppress this unwanted output.
The hist function can also be called on a pandas series object.
We can plot a histogram for one specific column like this.
Or instead of using hist,
the more general plot function and specify the type of plot in a parameter.
Next, let's plot a bar chart for the education column.
For this, we need counts for each distinct value or bar.
This value counts function aggregates counts for each unique value in a column.
We can call the plot function on this result to create a bar chart.
Similarly, we also need value counts to plot pie charts.
Let's create a pie chart for the workclass column.
Awesome. Let's switch to
our cancer dataset to practice plotting scatter plots and box plots.
This next function is really cool for getting quick insight
into the relationships among numerical variables with scatter plots.
It also displays a histogram for each variable.
We can create a single scatter plot using this standard plot function,
with parameters to specify the columns to be used for the x and y-axis.
Finally, the plot function can also be used to create a boxplot.