Let's use descriptive statistics and visualizations to
address a question we posed with this cancer data earlier in the lesson.
Does the size of a tumor effect it's malignancy?
For this, we'd ideally compare the sizes of benign tumors with those of malignant tumors.
We can use masks to select all rows in the DataFrame that were diagnosed as malignant.
Then all rows diagnosed as benign and put them in separate DataFrames.
First, let's create a new DataFrame called df_m that contains only malignant tumors.
Here's a breakdown of how we got this.
This part here returns a panda series of booleans
indicating whether the value in the diagnosis columns is equal to
m and indexing the original DataFrame with
this mask will return all rows where the value and mask is true.
In other words, where the diagnosis is
m. Now that we have all the malignant tumors together in a DataFrame,
let's see summary statistics about the area feature,
which offers a good metric for size.
Let's do the same for all the benign tumors.
We can use the mean to compare these.
Although the summary statistics like the mean are helpful,
it would be nice to be able to compare the distributions of
the areas of malignant and benign tumors visually.
Here's an example using pandas to create
histograms for both distributions on the same plot.
Don't worry about understanding this code right now.
We'll learn how to create these histograms further in the lesson.
This visual suggests that there's a difference between
the distributions of areas for benign and malignant tumors.
We don't yet have the tools to conclude that these two distributions are
different or whether the size definitely affects the tumors malignancy.
However, we can observe from summary statistics and
these histograms that malignant tumors are generally larger in size then benign tumors.