Let's start with one classification example.
Let's say we are the admissions office at
a university and our job is to accept or reject students.
In order to evaluate students,
we have two pieces of information,
the results of a test and their grades in school.
Let's take a look at some sample students.
We'll start with student 1 who got 9/10 in the test and 8/10 in the grades.
That student did quite well and got accepted.
Then we have student 2 who got 3/10 in the test and 4/10 in the grades,
and that student got rejected.
Now we have a new student 3 who got 7/10 in the test and 6/10 in the grades,
and we're wondering if the student gets accepted or not.
Our first way to find this out is to plot students in a graph with
the horizontal axis corresponding to the score and
the test and the vertical axis corresponding to the grades,
and the students would fit here.
The students who got three and four gets located in the point that coordinates 3, 4,
and the student who got nine and eight gets located in the point which coordinates 9,8.
Now we'll do what we do in most of our algorithms,
which is to look at the previous data.
This is how the previous data looks.
These are all the previous students that got accepted or rejected.
The blue points correspond to students that got
accepted and the red points to students that got rejected.
We can see in this diagram that the students who
did well in the test and grades are more likely to
get accepted and the students who did poorly on both are more likely to get rejected.
Let's start with a quiz.
The quiz says, does the student 3 get accepted or rejected.
What do you think? Enter your answer below.