Correct. Well, it seems that this data can be nicely separated by a line,
which is this line over here,
and it seems that most students over the line get
accepted and most students under the line get rejected.
This line is going to be our model.
The model makes a couple of mistakes since there are
a few blue points that are under the line and a few red points over the line.
But we're not going to care about those.
We'll say that it's safe to predict that if a point is over the line,
the student gets accepted,
and if it's under the line,
then the student gets rejected.
Based on this model, we look at the new student and we see that
they're over here at the 0.76, which is above the line.
We can assume with some confidence that the student gets accepted.
If you answer, yes, that's the correct answer.
Now a question arises.
The question is, how do we find this line?
We can eyeball it,
but the computer can't.
We'll dedicate the rest of the section to show you algorithms that will find this line,
not only for this example,
but for much more general and complicated cases.