Now that you've seen how to fit a linear model in Python,
it's important that you can interpret the results that you obtain from the line you fit.
You might have noticed that the summary of the linear model
you retrieve from Python gave a lot of information.
Information in this portion,
we will discuss soon enough.
But for right now, let's look at this part of the results.
Right here, is an area that tells us about the model we fit.
Specifically, this is the intercept, and this is the slope.
We can build a linear model in this way.
The predicted house price is equal to 9,588 plus 348 times the area of the house.
So if somehow, a home had an area of zero,
we would predict that the model would cost 9,588.
For every one unit increase in the area,
we would predict that the price would increase by 348.
If the units on the price were dollars and on
your area were feet then the units here would match.
You will want all the data in a single column to
have the same units for your analysis to work correctly.
Additionally, these here are the 'P' values.
In regression, 'P' values are always given for testing if the parameter for
the intercept or the slope are equal to zero and the null hypothesis, like this.
Then in the alternative, by default,
Python and other software compute 'P' values using a not equal to.
These 'P' values can give a quick glimpse as to whether or not
a particular variable is useful for predicting the response.
The 'P' value here on the intercept isn't as useful as this one here,
which suggests that the area is statistically significant in relating to the price.
This will become more useful in the next lesson when we
look at many of these coefficients all at the same time.