The first type of regression we'll look at is called Simple Linear Regression.
And in these cases,
we're comparing only two quantitative variables.
And the most simple form of aggression,
we're interested in only of the relationship of two variables.
This could be price versus sales,
temperature versus humidity, height versus weight,
or hours studying versus test grade.
A common way to visualize these relationships is with a scatter plot.
The variable on this axis is called the response or dependent variable,
where the variable on this axis is called explanatory or independent variable.
The response variable is the one that we're interested in predicting,
while the explanatory variable is used to predict the response.
In the case of price versus sales,
we'll likely have more control over the price,
where sales is something that we want to predict based on the price.
Therefore, we would consider price to be
the explanatory variable and sales to be the response variable.
In linear progression, the way that we do this is by fitting a line to the data.
Before we get too far along with regression,
let's take a closer look at
scatter plots and what is known as the correlation coefficient.