When we fit line to a set of points,
we commonly define it by two values,
an intercept and a slope.
The Intercept tells us the predicted value of
the response when the explanatory variable is zero.
We commonly use this notation for the population and sample intercept values,
pronounced beta knot for the parameter and B0 for the statistic.
The slope tells us the predicted change in the response for
each additional one unit increase in the explanatory variable.
Similarly, the notation for the population
and sample slope values are notated in this way,
pronounced as beta one for the parameter,
and B1 for the statistic.
Once we've fit a line to these points,
we define it with this equation.
This point here at the beginning of the line is the intercept value,
that is, where the x value is equal to zero.
And if we were to increase by one along the x-axis, like this,
then the change along the y-axis in the line is the slope value,
one last important note on notation.
Commonly, you will see y,
and Y-hat values like these in regression.
These actually notate two different things.
Y-hat values define the values that we get from the fitted line,
but the y defines the actual data points.
So this value would be defined as y1, x1.
But if we were to go to the line,
we would define this as Y-hat_1, X1.
Now that you understand that there are two values that
define a line and how they're represented,
both in notation and visually, in the next video,
you'll see how we actually figure out what line best
fits the points and exactly what best means.