In the bi-variate case,
we're interested in finding a line that best allows us to
predict the response variable using the explanatory variable.
The main algorithm used to find the best line
is known as the least squares regression algorithm.
And the way the line is chosen is by minimizing the sum of
squared vertical distances between our fitted line and each of these points.
Let's look at how this works.
Imagine with the same set of points,
we are considering fitting these two lines.
The way we could decide between which of these two lines
we should choose is in looking at these distances.
But if we were to just use the sum of these values
the negatives and positives would end up cancelling out each line.
So instead of just summing these,
we sum the square of these distances,
and then finding the line that minimizes this.
The way we would notate this difference is like this,
and then our goal is to minimize this function which says,
for each of the data points in the data set,
look at the distance between the predicted and actual values,
square these, and then sum them all together.
And if our line creates a smaller value than for any other line,
then this is the line we want to use.
You might be thinking, why do we choose this function?
Why not just use the absolute value instead of the square?
Or why not use an exponential to turn all the values positive?
And the truth is that there are lots of functions we might choose to optimize on.
However, there are mathematical properties that make this particular function quite nice.
Some are based on the ideas of calculus and some are just based on tradition.
In most cases, you don't actually compute
these values yourself but this is what software,
like what you will be doing in Python, do by default.
And it tends to work pretty well for most data sets.
If you decide you want to optimize this problem in a different way,
then you will probably have to write the program yourself.