Now that we've looked at how linear regression works,
let's look at how we can do linear regression in Python.
There are two main libraries that are used to perform linear aggression in Python.
The first is statsmodels,
which we'll use in this lesson.
The second is scikit-learn.
Statsmodels is used in many cases due to the way that it resembles stats
output that you might see in languages more commonly
used by statisticians like R and SAS.
Alternatively, scikit-learn is very popular for lots of machine learning algorithms
because of its ease of making predictions
and quickly fitting many types of models to compare.
Because we are focused not only on creating our linear models in this course,
but also analyzing the coefficients and statistical significance of those coefficients,
we'll be using statsmodels for this course.
On the next page, we'll look at exactly how we might use
statsmodels to fit and analyze a linear model in Python.
We'll write code very similar to the documentation that you see here,
and we'll get output that looks just like this.
Lots of output that we can use to better understand our models.