In this video, we'll be looking at fitting a linear model to our data in Python.
We will be using the statsmodel library.
I've loaded the necessary libraries we'll be using
here as well as loading the data set using pandas.
It looks like if you don't have statsmodels installed,
you'll have to install that before we can get started.
Here, I've done a pip install.
At the end of this lesson,
you will be performing this process a few times on
different datasets to assure you are comfortable with this process,
and the provided results.
Before we fit our model,
we need to make sure to add a column for our intercept.
Unfortunately, statsmodels doesn't automatically do this,
and there are only rare cases where you will not want to add an intercept.
A link discussing this topic is provided in the instructor notes below.
Here, we are providing OLS method the Y and X variables.
OLS stands for ordinary least squares,
as this is the method we want to use.
First, we provide our Y,
and then a list of the X variables.
We then fit the model with this,
and finally, we can store our results and look at a summary.
In the remaining concepts,
we'll go through how to interpret some of
the most important information from this output.