As we saw earlier,
the decimal module provides decimal floating point
arithmetic with more precision and control over rounding.
Let's review how to do this one more way to
get the total price formatted the way that we would expect.
Let's go back to where we last used decimal and get context. We'll copy this.
Go down, we'll create a new cell,
and now what we'll do is we're going to set the precision to 10.
Then we're going to take our items from here.
We're going to copy and paste them here,
and then what we're going to do is that we're going to take decimal.
We're going to put that to the left of each of these items.
We'll close each of these off,
and we'll put a single quote around each item.
Then what we'll do is we will calculate the total price.
Total price, we'll copy that from earlier equals item 1 plus item 2 plus item 3,
then what we'll do is we'll print the total price.
But we're not going to use that.
The total price will equal the total price value,
which is defined up here.
Let's see what happens when we run this.
Here, we use the decimal class to define prices ensuring more precise arithmetic.
Now if we want to get that additional zero,
we'll add zero like that and we'll press "Enter".
We now get the two decimal places there.
When we set the precision to 10 decimal places using get context with precision,
the calculation of the total price then remains accurate without
floating point and accuracies to exactly what we specify, giving us 29.10.
The price that we would expect and are looking for here.
By understanding the accuracy,
limitations of floating point numbers and using appropriate techniques,
you can ensure your Python programs handle numeric data correctly and efficiently.
You also have just added
many different ways to work with these floating point numbers in Python.
Great work here. You'll use many of these methods as you proceed through the course.