In this next section,
we'll be learning about typecasting,
which is just a fancy word for converting a value from one data type to another.
This is useful when you need to perform operations between different types.
Example, if we wanted to count the number of fruits in your shopping cart.
We'll use integers, whole numbers to do this.
However, the names of the fruits,
such as banana, apple,
watermelon, orange, grapefruit,
and so on, are strings and not numbers.
If we tried to count strings, we can do that.
But if we tried to add the name of a number,
that just won't work because they are different entities,
numbers are not the same as strings.
When would we need to convert a value from one data type to another?
Let's review some common scenarios.
In terms of typecasting,
let's talk about converting to an integer with the int function.
Let's say you need to perform operations with
values that are currently strings representing numbers.
Strings that represent numbers can't be used directly in calculations. Think about it.
Could you add multiple or divide two words of a sentence together?
Words can't work like a number in a numeric equation.
We need to convert them to integers first.
To do this, we'll use the int function to convert a string to an integer.
Let's see an example of something like this.
We'll create a variable A,
and we'll set that equal to a string of one, two, three.
Then we're going to create a variable called B,
and we're going to use the int function to turn A into an integer.
We'll print B, and then we'll see what is created,
can you guess what the output of B is going to be if we print this?
If you guessed 123 as a number, you're right.
If we were to try to check the type of B,
let's see what that would be.
If we do print and we do type,
we put B in there, and then we hold on shift press Enter.
We'll see that the class of the data type is integer.
Now, if we were to do this same operation,
but check A, what do you think the data type would be for A?
If you said string, you're right.
That's how we're able to turn A,
which is a string into B,
which is an integer.
B is transformed into an integer or a number value while A remains a string,
a series of characters united by quotation marks, like we see here.
If we want to then test the data type of B,
the last line will print that class integer,
which confirms for us that we did this correctly,
and variable B is, in fact,
now an integer and not a string any longer.
Let's see another example of using the int function in action,
this time with user inputs.
We'll be converting inputs more in-depth in the next section.
But for now, just know that the input function is a way to
prompt a user or viewer to put in a value like a Popa box,
and then Python stores at value the user entered.
Imagine you have a user input their age as a string,
but you need to perform some quick calculations to figure out their age next year.
To do this in Python,
we'll first start a new cell and we'll say age string equals input, enter your age.
This is going to allow an input field to pop up one we call age string,
and that's going to show a prompt,
which says enter your age,
and that will allow for an input from the user.
Then age integer or age int is going to equal the integer of age.
Strings. Whatever the user inputs,
we're going to automatically turn that into an integer.
Next, age next year is going to equal age int plus one,
because this will be whatever the user inputs turned into an integer plus one value,
which is their age next year.
We'll go ahead and print the value once we receive that,
and we'll say next year,
you will be,
we'll take age next year because we're using a F string,
passing that variable as a temp literal,
and then say years old.
We'll close that out with quotations, close the parenthesis.
So let's review what we have so far.
First, we'll want the user to enter their age,
which we have with this input field.
Let's say they put in 30 as a string into the textbox.
When the variable age int is declared,
we want to make sure that age string is
an integer so that we can do math operations on it.
Can you guess what would happen if a user inputs
the word apple or 30 with quotes into the text box?
If we were to use Apple as our input into this text box and press ''Enter'',
we'll get invalid literal four int with base 10 apple.
Let's try this again. What if we tried to put 10 into this?
We'll also get invalid literal four int with base 10.
We need to make sure that what we put into the value
of age string is a number for this very reason.
With the int function, we extract the value out of age string,
which is what we put in here,
and set it as an integer.
In this way, when we set age next year,
right here, in this next variable,
we take the integer value of age int since we know it,
and it must be an integer,
and then add plus one to it,
incrementing it by a value of one.
When we ultimately print the value of the next year's statement,
that will be the value of the users enter age plus one.
If we put in 30 into this textbox,
can you guess what the final output would be?
If you said next year you will be 31 years old,
then you're correct. Great work.