Now let's take a look at converting to a floating point number with float.
Let's say you have numeric data as strings,
and you need decimals for making precise calculations,
like prices or measurements.
For example, $1.50 and $1 are very different numbers.
Or let's say we're dealing with huge numbers.
4.9 billion and 49 billion are very different.
We need to know if we are dealing with a decimal
or not because the difference could be quite drastic.
Strings with decimal points can't be used directly in calculations.
We need to convert them to float to handle these special cases,
which can be very important depending on the numbers we're dealing with at hand.
Let's talk about converting to a floating point number with the float function.
To do this, we'll use the float function to convert a string to a floating point number.
We'll first start with declaring a variable a,
and we'll set that equal to a string of 123.45.
Then we'll set a variable of b = float,
which is taking the float value of a.
If we were to print the value of b,
what do you think this will create?
If you said 123.45, you're right,
as this is now a number that Python can use in calculations,
rather than the original 123.45 string value,
which cannot be used in numerical calculations.
When we print the data type of b with type,
we can confirm the data type is now a float.
What do you think the output of type b will be?
If you said class float,
then you're absolutely right.
Let's also validate that this did actually change the data type going from a to b.
If we type this out, we see that a is a string,
and then that b is now afloat.
Let's consider a real world scenario where this might be useful and feel more real.
Suppose you're calculating the total price of items in a shopping cart,
where prices are input as strings.
When we calculate prices,
those can be recorded as strings in a catalog,
but we'll need to convert them to float data types
so that we can calculate them together to get the final price.
We'll create another cell, and we'll start this off with saying that
the price of a string is $19.99.
Then when we calculate a price variable,
we'll say that that is the float value of our price string.
The total price is then the price times three.
We're converting the price string from a string to a float using the float function,
and then we can multiply the price by three to get the total price for three items.
If we didn't convert the string to a float first,
Python wouldn't know how to multiply 19.99 as a string by three.
We need Python to read it as 19.99 as a floating point number times three, like this.
Then we'll create a print statement,
and we'll write an f string,
and we'll say the total price for three items is dollar sign,
we'll pass in a template literal,
and we'll pass in the total price.
We'll close this off with closed quotation marks,
and then we'll close it out with end [inaudible].
What would the final price here be? Let's find out.
If you said $59.97,
then you would be correct.
This demonstrates how converting strings to floats can be
essential for performing accurate calculations with decimal numbers.
By understanding and using typecasting with float,
you can ensure your Python programs handle numeric data correctly and efficiently.