When you order a meal at a restaurant,
you give your order, and then you
expect that the restaurant will give you something in return.
In this case, your meal.
But what if the restaurant only took in orders but never gave out a meal?
That restaurant wouldn't be around for very long.
In the same way, we need to think about that in our Python code,
and make sure that it returns the output we
expect it to and need it to every single time.
There are two fundamental functions in Python for interacting with the user.
The print function outputs text to the console,
while the input function reads a line of text from the user.
Consider the input function.
When we need a user to supply the function or program with an input,
such as your name or email,
or any other piece of data,
we're going to use the input function to prompt
the user to put in some text via an input box.
In this example, the input function prompts the user to enter their name.
When you're writing Python code,
print statements are incredibly helpful for logging,
and also for tracking what your functions and scripts are doing or maybe not doing.
This way, we can see what our Python program sees immensely
helpful for debugging if we're getting unexpected outputs and need to retrace our steps,
or figure out what's going on.
In this example, the print function outputs a greeting message.