Now that we've examined the print function,
let's expand on this a bit.
While the print function allows us to write a message to the console.
There are two additional keyword parameters we can pass into it,
called sep and end.
The sep parameter specifies the separator between multiple arguments,
and the end operator specifies what to print at the end.
When we think about parameters for a function class or method,
think of them as settings that we can use to customize the behavior of a certain action.
Settings can either be required,
meaning that you must specify what that settings is
value is or an error will occur or optional,
meaning that there will be a default value utilized,
but that can be overwritten by a custom value U pass in.
Think of it like ordering food at a fast food restaurant.
When you order a number one,
maybe that comes with a burger,
fries and a drink.
If you don't customize any of these inputs,
these three items will come with their defaults.
Perhaps a plain burger with ketchup,
small fries and a la soda.
But let's say that there is an optional value to upgrade
your meal to a number five for only $5 more.
The meals upgrade could be an optional parameter to either make the meal bigger,
it's included, or the meal stays the same.
It's not included, and the default is, don't upgrade.
When we think about the SEP and end, keyword parameters.
Let's take a look at an example of this inaction.
If we want to bring multiple elements together with a custom separator,
such as two strings.
This is what we would do. We'll say print,
Hello, and this will be our first item.
World, will be our second item.
We'll declare our sep keyword parameter,
and we're going to put this in quote,
and we're going to put a comma in there and then a space. We'll do another comma.
We'll say end, and then we'll add a exclamation point,
and then we'll close this out.
Can you guess what this will print? It prints?
Hello, comma world, exclamation point.
What is happening is we have multiple inputs as strings,
the hello and world,
and we use a sep parameter right here of comma space
to unite together both of those strings into
one single string with that defined character.
Then the end parameter,
which is to add an exclamation point to the end of the string.
Instead of needing to write a function to do all of this logic,
we can leverage the built in functionality of
these optional parameters in our print statements. How cool is that?