As you've started to see, working with the right variables is so important.
If an application asks you for your age
to surprise you on your birthday with an age-appropriate gift,
you'll need to make sure that the users can only upload an integer.
If they upload a string or a float decimal,
then it could throw off your app for your user and make it not work.
Thanks to int and float functions,
we can use these to convert strings to integers and floating point numbers respectively.
Let's see some examples.
In this example, the user will be prompted to input their age,
and this will only accept a number integer as an input.
In this example, the user will be prompted to input their height,
and this will only accept a float decimal as an input.
Then if you had those variables,
you can put them into a string and know that
the data types will make sense for your inputs.
As we see here, the int function converts the input string to an integer,
and the float function converts the input string to a floating-point number.
Let's look at the n function with an example.
Now, when we write age equals,
and then we have an input of enter your age with a space and an end parentheses,
and then another end parenthesis.
Now, when we execute this,
we'll be able to put in an age.
Now, notice how we can add in the input as a number at 21,
and then this works as expected and your age is 21.
But what happens if we don't write the number like that?
So if we execute this code,
and we were to put to space one as we'll
try adding a space between these two numbers and then press enter.
This leads to a value error.
If we were to write this again and execute the code.
If we were to enter a string into our input field,
such as hello world, and press enter.
We get another value error as it's
expecting a number input and not a string, but we put in a string.
This can be quite helpful, such as, for example,
telling the user in an application that they need to enter in a number
to proceed if they're putting in the wrong type of input.
Now let's look at the float function with an example.
Write height equals float input,
enter your height at a space,
and then end quotes parenthesis and then another end parentheses.
Now, when we execute this code,
notice how we can add in an input such as an integer, gamble 100.
Then this will work as expected.
If we press enter, this adds in the number and it prints out the string.
If we were to copy this code and run this again,
and we do 1.5 as a floating point number, and press enter.
This also works as expected.
But let's see an example where if we
put in foot and inches as quotation marks, for example.
Let's say we write one single five double quote for feet and inches,
and we were to press enter to enter in our height.
We're going to get a value error since Python is not
able to convert this string into a float.
To make this work, we need to either use a library to convert the string equivalent
of this to an integer or
floating point number to use before sending this two-input function.
As you see in these other two examples,
the int function converts the input string to an integer,
and the float function converts the input string to a floating point number.
Here and here. Now, let's combine inputs and outputs.
Let's say you want to convert the outputs together that you
have in other cells into a single string. How would we do that?
Remember our previous lesson on F strings.
We already have our age and height variables defined previously.
Let's execute those again.
When we run this, let's say we put 21 press enter,
we've now saved 21 to the age variable.
Now when we go down to height,
we can run this again,
we can save 1.5 press enter,
and now we've saved 1.52 our height variable.
So now what we will do is we'll start with a print statement
opener to take these values and put them as a final string.
So we'll do print, and then inside of the print statement,
we'll say F to define the opener of our F string,
and then we'll write text,
add in our variable inputs,
defined with squiggly brackets,
and then close the F string with a closing quotation mark,
and then close the print statement with that.
To write this, we'll say you are age years old,
and we'll define another variable input as a temple literal with height meters tall.
Now, when this print statement is executed,
it prints the text with the variable inputs.
So in this example, the int function converts the input string to
an integer and the float function converts the input string to a floating-point number.
And then when we bring these items together in an F string,
we're able to print a final statement like this.
As we see, you are 21 years old and 1.5 meters tall,
and that took the variable age
and variable height that we had saved the values of previously.
We can put that into a string like this with an F string.