Boolean expressions are used to evaluate
conditions that control the flow of our Python code programs.
They're essential for implementing logic,
such as determining if a user is eligible for a discount,
if a certain situation is occurring or not,
or if a certain value is returned to then do a follow up action.
Let's go through some Boolean expression examples.
First up, let's check if a user qualifies for a discount.
Imagine you run an online store and you want to
offer discounts to customers based on certain conditions.
Let's say a user qualifies for a discount if they have spent
more than $100 or if they are a loyalty program member.
You can use a Boolean expression to check these conditions.
Let's write some code to express what we would do for something like this.
We'll define a variable called total_spent,
and we'll set that equal to 120.50.
Then we'll do is_loyalty_member set to false, and that'll be our Boolean.
Now that we've defined our variables,
let's write a function that will check a certain condition.
Say qualifies_for_discount = total_spent,
and that's greater than 100, or is_loyalty_member.
Then we'll print the value of this function,
and we'll do an f string.
We'll say user qualifies for discount.
Put this in squiggly brackets,
and then we'll close that out.
Here, in this function,
we're going to check if the user qualifies for a discount called qualifies_for_discount,
where if the total spent is greater than 100,
then the discount applies,
and they are a loyalty_member.
That's the other condition that we'll check.
In this example, the total_spent is greater than
100 and checks out if the user has spent more than $100,
and is_loyalty_member checks if the user is a loyal program member.
The or operator combines these conditions together,
meaning the user qualifies for a discount if either condition is true,
which is evaluated to this value here.
Can you tell what the output is going to be here?
Let's find out. If you guess true,
you're right. Great job.