In this next example of Boolean expressions,
we're going to check if a number is within a certain range.
Boolean expressions can be used to check if
a value falls within a certain range of numbers.
For instance, let's check if a user's age is within the range
of 18-65 for eligibility in a certain program.
We'll first define a variable of age equaling to 25,
and then we'll write a function to check if the age is within the range that we specify,
and then write a range for the variable and then check it.
So we'll say is eligible equals age if that's greater than or equal to
18 and age is less than or equal to 65 to define our range.
Then we'll write a print statement to f string,
and we will check if user is eligible.
Then we'll put this variable in squiggly brackets.
We'll then close that up, and then let's review.
If age is greater than or equal to 18,
checks if the user's age is 18 or older.
This part, which is age is less than or equal to 65,
checks if the user's age is 65 or younger,
and the keyword combines both of them
together as an operator to ensure both conditions are true,
for is eligible to be evaluated.
What do you think the output of this will be?
Let's run it and see.
If you guess true, you're right. Great job.