As we continue to look at Boolean expressions,
let's look at checking multiple conditions at once.
You can also combine multiple Boolean expressions to create more complex conditions.
For example, let's check if a user is eligible for
a senior discount and whether they have a valid membership card or not.
To do this, we will define a variable called age and set that equal to 70.
We'll then set another variable called has membership card as Boolean,
and we'll set that equal to true.
Then we'll say qualifies_for_senior_discount,
and we'll set that equal to if age is greater than or
equal to 65 and has_membership_card.
Then we'll write a print statement, then f string,
and we'll say user qualifies for senior discount.
And then we'll pass in the value of
this function expression with squiggly brackets like this.
In this example, we're going to write a function to check if the user
qualifies for a senior discount based on a variable of age, which we defined here.
Now, we're going to check to see what's actually going on in this function.
Age must be greater than or equal to 65,
and that checks if the user's age is 65 or older.
Then has membership card is also used in
our Boolean expression to check if the user has a valid membership card,
which we defined up here.
The end operator is our Boolean expression,
and combines both of these conditions.
Meaning, the user qualifies for a senior discount only
if both conditions are true because we're using int.
What do you think this will evaluate to?
Let's find out. If you said true,
you're right. Great job.