Next up in our demos on Boolean Expressions,
we're going to talk about nested Boolean expressions.
Sometimes you will need to evaluate nested conditions.
For instance, let's determine if a user qualifies for a special offer based on their age,
spending, and membership status.
To do this, we'll create a new notebook,
and we'll say age is 30.
We'll send another variable called total_spent =
150.75 for $150.75 that was spent,
and we'll have a Boolean value called loyalty_member,
and we'll set that equal to true.
Then we're going to create a function expression that
will be called qualifies_for_special_offer.
We'll set that equal to some nested conditions.
For the first one, we'll say if age is greater than or equal to 18,
and age is less than or equal to 30.
We'll have another expression,
and we'll say total spent is greater than 100, or is_loyalty_number.
Then print a f string,
and we'll say user qualifies for a special offer.
Then we'll use our squiggly brackets and we'll
pass in the output of the function expression.
In this example, we're writing a function to check if a user qualifies
for a special offer based on total spent and their loyalty status.
Let's see what's actually going on in this example.
In the first condition,
right here, this is checking if the user's age is between 18-30.
Now, in this second expression,
we're checking if the user has spent more than $100,
or is a loyalty member,
so if this value is true.
The outer and operator,
which is right here, ensures that both groups,
this and this,
must be true for qualifies_for_special_offer to be true.
Can you guess what the output of this is going to be?
Let's run this and find out.
If you guess the output was true for this one,
you got it. Nice work.