We've just covered Boolean operators.
Now let's dive into another important set of operators called relational operators.
These operators compare values and return true or false.
They are often used in Boolean expressions to help us make decisions in our code.
Let's explore each one of these new operators with an example of it in action.
The equal to operator checks if two values are equal.
If they are, it returns true.
Otherwise, it returns false.
In this example, a and b both hold the value five,
so a == b evaluates to true.
The not equal to operator checks if two values are not equal.
If they are not equal, it returns true.
Otherwise, it returns false.
Here, a is five,
and b is three,
so a does not equal b.
Here, a is five,
and b is three,
so a!= b evaluates to true because they are different values.
The greater than operator checks if
a value on the left is greater than the value on the right.
If it is, it returns true.
Otherwise, it returns false.
In this example, a is greater than b,
so a > b evaluates to true.
The greater than or equal to operator checks if
the value on the left is greater than or equal to the value on the right.
If it is, it returns true,
otherwise, it returns false.
Here, a is equal to b,
so a >= b evaluates to true.
The less than operator checks if the value
on the left is less than the value on the right.
If it is, it returns true.
Otherwise, it returns false.
In this example, a is less than b,
so a < b evaluates to true.
The less than or equal to operator checks if the value on
the left is less than or equal to the value on the right.
If it is, it returns true.
Otherwise, it returns false.
Here, a is equal to b,
so a <= b evaluates to true.
Congrats, you've just learned a whole new set
of tools for relational operations in Python.
These operators are fundamental
in programming and will help you control the flow of your code.
Great work and keep it going as we move into the next video ahead.