In this section, we'll explore the accuracy of floating point numbers,
a topic that can be crucial for understanding why
some calculations might not produce the exact results you'd expect.
Floating point numbers are used to represent real numbers in computing.
But due to the way they are stored in memory,
they can sometimes lead to some surprising results.
Let's go check it out and see.
When we talk about floating point numbers,
we're referring to numbers that have decimal points.
These are used in calculations requiring precision,
like measurements or financial computations.
However, floating point numbers are stored in a binary format,
like we learned about earlier,
that can only approximate many real numbers,
leading to small errors in calculations.
When we think about basic floating point inaccuracy,
let's start with a simple example.
You might expect that adding 0.1 and 0.2 would give you 0.3.
But let's see what happens when we do that.
When we type print(0.1+0.2),
and then we set that = 0.3,
do you think will happen here?
If we execute this, we see that it evaluates as false.
In this example, we're adding 0.1 and 0.2 together,
and we would expect that the output would be 0.3.
However, the comparison of 0.1+0.2 evaluates to false.
Why is that? Isn't that so strange?
Now, let's print the value of this expression to see what
actually equals between this output here.
When we say print 0.1+0.2,
and we also say print 0.3.
Of course, this will equal 0.3,
but printing this results in 0.3000000,
whole bunch of zeros, and then 4.
Which is very close to 0.3,
but not exactly so unexpected.
This small difference arises because 0.1
and 0.2 cannot be represented precisely in binary,
which leads to a tiny error when calculating the sum.
To understand why this happens,
we need to delve into how computers represent numbers.
Computers use a binary system base two to represent data,
which works well for whole numbers,
like 1,2,3,4 and so on,
but can introduce inaccuracies for floating point decimal numbers,
like 0.1, 0.2, and so on.
In a binary system,
each digit represents a power of two,
similar to how each digit in the decimal system represents a power of 10.
However, some decimal fractions cannot be represented exactly as fractions.
The decimal number 0.1 is a repeating fraction in binary,
which is 0.00011001,
and so on, and it looks something like this.
Similarly, 0.2 is also a repeating fraction in binary,
and that's going to be 0.001100110011, and so on.
I would look something like that.
Also, these will continue on indefinitely.
When the computer stores and adds the binary numbers together,
it must truncate the repeating binary fractions to fit into a fixed number of bits.
This truncation introduces a small error because the tiny difference between
the binary representations are not exact leading to a number like this.
That's why when we add decimals like this,
it equals falls because it equals 0.3, but not exactly.
These small inaccuracies can accumulate in calculations,
especially in fields requiring high precision,
such as scientific computing, finance, and engineering.
Understanding this behavior is crucial for writing robust and accurate programs.
To mitigate floating point inaccuracies,
consider some of the following approaches.
Use the decimal module.
For financial calculations requiring high precision,
Python's decimal module can be a better choice than
floating point arithmetic, or try rounding.
Apply rounding to ensure numbers are rounded to the desired precision needed.