The decimal module provides decimal floating point
arithmetic with more precision and control over rounding.
In this example, we're going to be talking about using that decimal module.
However, we have to be careful about how we use it,
as you'll see in these examples here.
Let's take our original example that we had in the previous demo.
We'll set A equal to 0.1,
and we'll set b equal to 0.2.
When we print the sum of a plus b,
this unexpectedly will not equal 0.3 as we saw,
but will equal 0.300000004.
Which is not what we would want or expect.
This happens because 0.1 and 0.2 cannot
be represented exactly as binary floating point numbers.
Their binary representations are approximations,
and when you add these approximations together,
you get a result that is very close to,
but not exactly 0.3.
By using the decimal module from Python,
let's attempt to specify how we will
work with these decimal numbers in a different way now.
We will use the decimal module,
so we'll do from decimal import decimal.
Then we'll say A equals decimal,
and we'll do 0.1 B equals decimal,
0.2, and then we're going to say print A plus B to get the sum of A plus B.
Will this print 0.3 when we set A and B to the values of 0.1 and 0.2,
respectively and add them together using the decimal module?
What do you think? You think that since we are enforcing the decimal module,
this should now export 0.3,
but it actually gives us a completely different fraction instead.
Let's see what this will create.
This instead creates 0.3 a whole bunch of zeros,
and then 1665, 33453, so on.
This is even stranger.
How do we just add two decimals together?
This is something that was quite confusing to me when I started working with Python
since I thought this simple operation would have a simple answer.
Let's see how working with floats work in Python correctly.
Remember how we learned about numeric floats as strings that we need to convert.
Well, when we put the decimals inside of quotes and then use the decimal module,
this is a way that we can set Python to know
exactly the limit of the bits we want to work with.
Let's see an example of this where we'll take this code We'll copy it,
we'll paste it into here,
and we're going to make a couple modifications.
We're going to put single quote around 0.1 and a single quote around 0.2.
Then we're going to try printing A plus B.. What do you think this will output to?
This will output our expected 0.3 as expected,
a very simple fix here to get exactly what we were looking for.
Something else we can do is set the precision
with the get context function from the decimal module.
Let's see how to do this.
We can copy this previous cell and paste it in,
and then we're going to add another import,
and we're going to say, get context.
Now, in order to set the precision,
we're going to say get context,
and then we're going to say open parenthesis close parenthesis dot PREC
we're going to say equals one.
We're setting the precision of get context to equal one.
Now, when we do A equals decimal,
we can remove these single quotes around our floating points,
and we can still keep print as A plus B.
By setting the precision of the float value to one,
this means that we'll only have one decimal.
Can you tell what this is going to create and print out for us?
This leads to 0.3.
If you said 0.3, you're right.
Congrats. To expand upon our previous examples with floating point numbers,
let's expand this to financial calculations,
where suppose you're calculating the total cost of several items in a shopping cart,
and the prices are floating point numbers.
Even small inaccuracies can add up leading to incorrect totals.