Let's see an example of what this could look like.
For example, let's say that we have three different items.
Item 1 is $19.90,
item 2 is $5.70,
and item 3 is $3.50.
What we want to do is we want to calculate the total price.
We would say total price equals item 1 price.
We can copy this plus item 2 price plus item 3 price.
Then when we print,
we'll create an F string and we'll say total price is dollars.
Then what we'll do is we'll say total price with curly brackets,
and that will be passed in there.
Based on what you already know,
will this give us one of those strange repeating fractions?
What do you think? Absolutely. You got it.
It will give us 29.0999999 repeating,
which is not what we're looking for.
We are looking for 29.1,
but because of the way binaries are stored for these numbers with single decimals,
we get this repeating decimal here.
You may also notice that we're using this F something in quotations,
which is a method inside of the print statement that we just wrote?
This is known as an F string,
a way to embed expressions inside string literals using curly braces like this,
where we use this for total price,
making it easier to format strings dynamically.
This is a very powerful method we will be relying on throughout
this course for writing a phrase to the terminal that could include variables,
expressions, in addition to text strings.
Just know that this is a way to combine text and
variables together in the same output as one combined string.
Now we could round the values with
the round function like we're going to do in a second,
where we take an input and associate a certain number of decimal places to it,
such as one, two,
which we'd want to do in this case,
three, and so on.
Let's take our code from the previous cell with Control C,
and then we'll paste it into the bottom cell with Control V. Now,
what we can do is,
we're going to add the round function here around total price.
We will specify the number of decimal places we want,
which is two, and we'll keep everything the same.
While the round function does round a number 2 a specified number of decimal places,
what we're going to find out is that it doesn't control how
the number is displayed as a string.
When you print the rounded number,
Python automatically formats it,
and it may omit trailing zeros,
which we'll see in a second.
Do you see how now it's 29.1 as opposed to 29.10,
which is what we would actually want.
To ensure that the output always displays two dismal places,
we'll need to use string formatting,
which we'll see in a second.
This is an example of a precision issue with
floating point arithmetic that can surface when dealing with money,
as we've seen in this example and in this example.
To ensure the output is formatted to two decimal places,
we can use the.2f format specifier.
What we'll do is that we are going to copy our last cell.
We'll paste that in here, and now we're going to do a couple of things.
We're going to get rid of the round function.
Get rid of the specifier.
What we'll do is that we will take total price.
We'll do a colon period 2 and f. The
colon.2f method is a fancy Python formatting method right here.
That ensures the total price is displayed with two decimal places so that
we do ultimately get 29.10 as we would expect.
Even though this example works correctly, as we see here,
it's essential to be aware of potential and accuracies like we
just went through when performing many operations with floating point numbers.