Now, once we've covered the basics of NLP and transformer architecture,
let's briefly cover what are we going to do for the rest of the lesson.
In this lesson, we will be working on implementing a transformer model from scratch.
Instead of generating a text on any topic,
we'll limit our goals and create a model that can generate Shakespeare like poetry.
We will train it on the work of William Shakespeare an English poet,
and it should be able to start generating poetry that looks like his work.
Our model will have an architecture that is similar to
the one used in GPT models created by Open AI,
and we'll see how these models work step by step.
There will be a few major differences between our model and GPT models.
First of all, our model will be much smaller.
It will have a few order of magnitude less parameters,
but this also means that we will be able to train it
without spending a fortune on computers and electricity.
We will use a character level tokenizer instead of using
a sub-word tokenizer to keep our implementation simpler.
Finally, the model implementation will be focused
on understandability rather than performance.
Once we're done, we will be able to create an instance of our model,
provide a configuration that will include several parameters,
like context window size, and so on.
Then we will be able to generate text using our model and a provided prompt.
L suggested to write a phrase that Romeo,
which is one of the characters in the Shakespeare work, could have side.