If you recall how we handle training data for transformers,
we convert a single part of the training dataset into multiple training examples.
One issue is that since a model sees the whole input,
it can sheet when predicting the next word.
To fix this problem, we need to change the attention scores we are calculating to
ensure that our model can't look at the next token when it tries to predict it.
To make sure that our model can sheet during training,
we need to update the attention matrix and set all the highlighted values to 0.
How would we do this? A simple way is to assign
all values below this diagonal to the negative infinity.
If you recall the properties of the softmax function,
it converts small values into values close to 0.
In this case, it will convert negative infinity values to 0s.
Going back to our diagram of operations in the multi-head attention,
we will add the masking step after the matrix multiplication,
and we will apply softmax afterwards.
This approach when we are using a triangular mask is called masked multi-head attention,
and it is used in many transformer models, including GPT models.