Before we finally start working on the implementation of our model,
let's briefly refresh an important technique
we will be using throughout our implementation,
which is called the dropout layer.
If we have a feedforward neural network,
each output from a previous layer goes to all neurons of the next layer.
However, if we introduce a dropout layer in our neural network,
then during training, a certain percentage of
randomly selected inputs will be set to zero on each training iteration.
The list of disabled inputs will change from one iteration to the other.
This allows to ensure that our model does not
learn to depend heavily on any particular input feature.
This in turn helps the model to generalize better,
making it less likely to overfit.
Notice that the dropout layer is only enabled during training.
But when we are using the model to generate text,
the dropout layer will be disabled.
We won't need to implement the dropout layer ourselves since
it's already implemented by the dropout type in PyTorch.