In this video, we will build the multi head attention block,
the cornerstone component of our transformer model,
and we will build it from scratch using PyTorch.
I have to warn you that this will probably be the most involved part of the whole lesson,
but the rest of the implementation for our model should be much easier.
Before we start working on this implementation,
we need to define a configuration for our model.
This configuration will contain hyper parameters
for our model that will define its structure.
We will put this configuration into this dictionary,
and here are the parameters that we will define.
The first one is vocabulary_size,
which is the size of the vocabulary defined by our tokenizer.
This is a number of unique token IDs that it supports.
The second parameter is context_size,
which is the length of the context window.
If you recall, this is the maximum number of tokens,
our mode can see it once.
The next parameter is embedding_dim,
which is the size of embedding vectors.
Each token in the input sequence will be converted to an embedding vector of this size.
Next, we have the heads_num parameter,
which is a number of attention heads we will have in our model.
If you recall, we'll have multiple attention heads,
and each will be processing input independently.
Here we define how many of them we will have.
Layers_num is a number of layers or transformer blocks in our model.
The drop out rate is to configure how many outputs in drop out layers to set to zero.
In the last parameter called use_bias is a Boolean flag
indicating whether the linear transformations should include bias terms.
We also need to compute the size of the output
from each head to set dimensions of our model correctly.
If you recall, every head produces output for only a part of each embedding vector.
To calculate it, we divide the embedding vector size,
by the number of heads,
so all outputs from all heads together will produce a vector of the right size.
Now, let's see how to implement a single attention head.
To do this, we will define
the attention head class that will implement a single attention head.
To implement it, we need to inherit the module type and
define a constructor where we define all building blocks.
We first define matrices Q _weights,
K_weights, and V_weights,
and we will use them to convert input embedding vectors into Q,
K, and V matrices correspondingly.
We then define the dropout rate,
and we define the casual attention mask.
To define the attention mask,
we first create a square matrix of the context window size,
and we do it using the torch one function,
and then we pass it to the true function to only get the values below the main diagonal.
If you recall, this true function allows us to
set all values above the main diagonal to zero.
We then use the registered buffer method to save the casual attention mask.
This function allows us to register
a buffer that should not be considered a model parameter.
But it won't be trained during the model training,
but it would be part of a model state.
Now having the constructor implemented,
we will need to implement the forward method.
In this method, we'll receive an input,
which is a mini batch of converted input tokens.
Throughout this method, I'll write these comments to
specify the dimensions of different tensors,
so we can keep track of what is going on.
The input contains the following dimension.
B is the size of a mini batch,
C is the size of a context window,
and embedding_dim is the size of an embedding vector.
Using this input, we can compute matrices Q, K,
and V correspondingly, using our Q_weights,
K_weights, and V_weights.
Each of the separation will produce separate tensors of size B by C by head_size.
Now, having matrices Q and K,
we need to multiply them to compute attention scores.
To multiply them, however,
we first need to transpose matrix Q
so to make sure that we're doing the.product correctly.
As a result of this multiplication,
we will get a new tensor with dimensions P,
which is specialized by C by C. Then having the attention scores,
we need to apply the casual attention mask.
To do so use the mask fill method that will set
the positions where the mask is zero to negative infinity.
This will allow us to ignore these positions in the subsequent softmax step.
Then we also need to scale the attention scores as we've discussed before.
To do this, we divide it by the square root of the K,
which is the size of queries and keys.
The scaling allows us to make sure that attention scores don't become too large.
Finally, we will apply the softmax function to
the attention scores to convert the scores to probabilities,
ensuring they sum up to one.
We then multiply the attention scores and
V matrix to calculate new embedding vector values.
But we also need to apply the dropout to avoid overfitting.
Now, let's quickly test if it all works together.
To do this, I'll create a random input tensor with a batch size of 8,
the context window size,
and the embedding dimensionality that we will use,
and we'll use this input to test our attention head.
Now, to use this input,
we'll instantiate the attention head class using our configuration,
and then we'll pass this input tensor through the attention head to get some output.
Of course, passing random data through an interim model will return gibberish.
But what we can do, we can test that the outputs have the right dimensions.
If we look at the dimensions,
we see that there are eight,
which is our mini batch size that we selected by the context size by 64,
and 64 is actually the head size that we've calculated
here using the embeddings dimensions and the number of heads.
Now, so far, we only have a single attention head implemented.
Now we can implement multi head attention that combines multiple heads together.
To implement it, we again inherit from the module type.
We then create a list of attention head instances and we store them in this module list.
We also define an additional linear layer that will apply to each embedding vector.
Then we add another drop out layer for regularization.
Now, to implement the forward method, we first of all,
pass our input through all of our heads,
and then we get outputs from each one of these heads and store them into heads outputs.
We then concatenate the outputs along the last dimension,
and then we pass the results through the linear layer,
and we apply and drop out to the final output.
Now, that's it. That's the whole multi head attention block implemented.
Now we will instantiate
this multi head attention class using our configuration dictionary,
and we pass the same input tensor through
the multi head attention block to get the output.
Now, if you look at the shape of the output,
you will see that it looks similar to what we had before,
but now the size of the last dimension is 768,
which is also the size of our embedding vectors.
This means that we were able to create multi head attention with multiple heads,
pass the inputs through different heads and combine them together.
Now the size of the output is the same as
the size of the input we passed to the multi head attention.
Now, that's it. Now we have implemented multi head attention,
and now using this, we can build the rest of our model.