We have already covered how multi-head attention works in a transformer.
Now we will cover how to implement a transformer's block.
When we pass a prompt to a model,
we convert each input token into an embedding vector,
and then pass these vectors to multi-head attention block.
The output of the multi-head attention then goes to
the feed-forward network layer and the output
of this layer will be sent further to the next transformer block.
If you recall in one of the previous videos,
we discussed that a transformer model consists of multiple such blocks chained together.
Once we have this block implemented,
we will be almost done with the model implementation.
Let's now take a look at what happens in the feed-forward layer.
The feed-forward layer is applied to each embedding vector individually.
Each embedding vector is passed to a linear layer with
an output size that is four times larger than the input size.
To add non linearity to these transformations,
we will also apply the GELU activation function which we'll cover in a minute.
We then take this output and shrink
the output factor down to the original embedding size.
Now, let's also briefly talk about the GELU activation function that we will use.
It is similar to the ReLU activation function.
Here is a chart of the GELU activation function.
For comparison, here is a chart of the ReLU activation function.
As you can see, the GELU function has a smooth shape compared to the ReLU's sharp corner,
and this smooth shape allows to get better training results.
This is a gist of how a transformer block is organized,
but there are a few more details that we need to cover.
First, there are two residual connections in this block.
A residual connection is when we take an input to a certain block,
and we then add it to the out-put of the block before we pass the result forward.
Residual connections help with
the vanishing gradient problem that we've briefly covered before.
Just to remind you,
the vanishing gradient is the issue when
the gradient becomes very small in deep networks.
Using residual connections makes training deep neural network more efficient.
In addition to residual connections,
we have a few more extra components.
These include the layer normalization and the dropout layer.
We've already covered what is a dropout layer.
Now let's also briefly cover what is a layer normalization.
The layer normalization scales the output of
one layer so that the mean or average of the output values become zero,
and variance becomes equal to one.
Using layer normalization allows us to achieve faster training.
This layer is also implemented in Pytorch,
and we will use a type called layer norm for this.
This is it, just to recap,
every layer or block of a transformer model receives
an input that goes through multi-head attention and the feed-forward network.
Then to improve the training results,
we also use layer normalization,
dropout, and residual connections.
Now, once we've covered how it works,
let's go and implement it for our model.