Let's see how to implement a transformer block.
We've already implemented the attention block,
and now as you recall,
we now need to implement the feed-forward part of this block.
Once we have both of these blocks,
we can combine them together.
To define a feed-forward block,
we need to define a new class and inherit from the nn module type.
In this module, we define a sequence of linear layers.
First, we have a linear layer that projects the input dimension to four times its size.
We then have the activation function.
We then have another linear layer that projects the dimension back to the original size.
Then we add the dropout layer to prevent overfitting,
which I've included in this class.
All we need to do in the forward method is to pass
the input through all the linear layers we've just defined.
Now, let's run a quick test.
We will create an instance of the feed-forward block.
We will create a random input of the same size we've done
before and we will pass this input through this block.
If the print is the shape of the output,
it looks just as we expected.
It contains the batch size,
the context window size,
and the dimensionality of our embedding vectors.
Now having the feed-forward block and the multi-head attention block,
we can finally implement the transformer block, and to implement it,
I'll define the class called the block that will again inherit from the module class.
To implement it, I'll need to use the multi-head attention we've just
defined and the feed-forward block we've implemented in this demo.
We also need to add two normalization layers that we will use in this block.
In the forward method of this block,
we first normalize the input and we pass it through the multi-head attention layer.
We then add the original input to the output of the attention layer.
We then normalize this result and pass it to the feed-forward block.
Then we implement another residual connection when we add the output
of this block to the output of the feed-forward block. That's it.
Now let's try to pass some test data through
this transformer block and see if the dimensions of the outputs are still correct.
We create an instance of a transformer block.
We again create a test input of the same size as before.
We pass the input through the transformer block,
and then we look at the shape of the output,
which is exactly what we've expected.