Now, once we have implemented a single block,
let's take a look at how we can assemble everything into a single model.
We'll first walk through all the components of the model,
and in the next demo,
we will write it using PyTorch.
As we've discussed before,
to pass an input to our model.
We need to split it into tokens,
such as words, sub words, or individual characters.
Then we need to convert tokens into token IDs.
We then convert the token IDs into embedding vectors.
Then we add positional encoding values,
and the result of this sum are the input vectors we are sending to our model.
We then pass this input to the first layer of our network.
We then pass the output of this layer to the next layer, and so on.
The output from each layer has the same shape as the input,
but the value of embedding vectors change from layer to layer.
When we are training our model,
we will not pass just a single input.
We'll pass a batch of inputs together to use our resources more efficiently.
Finally, after the final layer of our model,
we need to convert the output into the next predicted token.
The output from the last layer will have the same number of embedding vectors,
and we need to convert it into tokens.
We do it in two steps.
First, we use a linear layer to convert each embedding vector into a new vector.
That contains prediction scores for each of the tokens in our vocabulary.
For example, 039, in this case is how confident
are model that it should generate token with 80 in this position.
The higher the prediction score,
the higher the model is confidence that it should use this token ID.
But we then want to convert these values into probability distributions.
As we've discussed before,
we can use the softmax function for this.
The output here will have the same shape as before,
but now these values will be probabilities our model have assigned for each token,
and the sum of probabilities for each position is equal to one.