Now once we have the Demo GPT model defined,
let's talk about how to train it.
It will be very similar to training other models.
On every iteration, using a data loader,
we will load a batch of inputs and targets,
and both inputs and targets will be tensors with token IDs.
We will then pass a batch of inputs to the model,
and it will return its predictions.
We'll use these predictions and use
the expected targets to calculate the loss for this batch.
Have any loss for a single batch,
we can calculate the gradients.
Using the optimizer instance,
we will update parameters of our model.
This is a single iteration for training our model.
We can now repeat this again and again using different batches of data.