In previous demos, we've built our model step by step,
and now it's time to implement the training code and train our model to generate text.
Most of the content in this particular demo won't be LM specific
and will mostly be implementing the standard by Torch model training loop.
First, to do this, we need to define a few high perameters for training.
We set the batch size to 64,
meaning that every training step will process 64 sequences at a time.
We then specify that we will train our model for 5,000 iterations,
and we will also evaluated every hundred iterations.
In this demo for validation,
we will try to generate some text and just
see how the result improves from one iteration to the other.
But later in one of the exercises,
you will implement calculating the validation loss.
Finally, we need to set the learning rate which controls how
much to adjust the model parameters during every training step.
Then we tokenize our text data,
and convert it into token IDs.
The encode method returns a one-dimensional tensor where every element is a token ID,
and then we put this tensor on the selected device,
which will be a GPU if we have one.
Now, having a tokenized text,
we create a data set for it.
We then create a random sampler that will randomly
select the training example from our dataset,
and we specify the number of training examples,
we want it to return.
This number is a number of training iterations.
Multiplied by the batch size.
Now to iterate over selected training examples,
we will create a data loader,
and we will also specify the batch size and the random sampler to use.
Next, we initialize the optimizer,
which will update model parameters during training.
Here we use Adam W,
which means Adam with way decay,
which usually gives better training results.
We also provide the learning rate that we've selected.
Finally, we need to implement the training loop.
We first iterate over many batches using our data loader.
For every iteration, we switch our model into the training mode,
and then from this mini batch,
we get the input and the targets.
We then pass the inputs to the model and our model return logits.
Using the logits and the targets,
we then need to calculate loss for this step.
But to do this, we'll first need to reshape
the logits and targets to calculate cross entropy.
Why do we need to reshape?
This is because we need to convert our data into
a shape that is expected by the cross entropy function.
For the targets, what we will do,
we will reshape it into a one-dimensional tensor.
Where we combine targets for all batches into one vector,
and every element is expected token ID.
For inputs, we do the same,
but every element will be a vector of loges,
and every logit is a score that our model
gives to a particular token ID from our vocabulary.
Then the cross entry function looks at the logits and checks if the model
is predicting the next token eight correctly for every position in every patch.
Given this data, it computes a loss
and using this loss with the compute back propagation,
and we run our optimizer to update our models parameters.
The final step in the training loop is we need to reset gradients before the next step,
and this is because we don't want to add gradients from different steps.
On the next step, we will have new inputs and targets,
and we want to compute new gradient values.
This particular parameter means that we are setting
gradients to none to reduce memory usage.
Finally, on every step,
we also print the step number and the loss we've calculated during this step.
Because this loss is a tensor to extract the number from it,
we need to use the item method.
Then every 100 iterations,
we also want to see how our model training is going.
For this, we generate output from our model using a simple prompt,
which in this case, is just a new line.
That's it, now let's start our model training, and for this,
I'll simply rerun all sales in this notebook.
As you can see, our model training was going for a few durations,
and we already got the first output from our model,
which is just a gibberish because it was just the first step in our training.
But as you also can see,
the loss is gradually decreasing.
I've let this model to train for a few hundred iterations and let's see what we've got.
First of all, we started with just generating rubbish,
and then if we scroll down a bit,
then it started to generate something similar to our input data,
and it even added the name of a character that is pronouncing a certain line.
But as you can see, the output still doesn't look like English.
But the loss is decreasing,
and if we look at another and if we scroll down a bit.
Now it generates something that is a bit more similar to English,
and it even got a few words correctly,
which is actually a small achievement because
these words are collected from individual tokens,
so to generate these words,
it needs to get a sequence of these token 80s correctly.
If we scroll down, now it starts with the name of a character,
and then some lines that it pronounced,
and even a few more words it got correctly like four and the and so on.
Now it managed to generate a whole phrase,
starting with the name of a character,
and this is a line this character pronounces.
Then as you can see, the more we train it,
the lower the loss gets.
If we let to train for a few thousand more iterations,
it will start generate text in the style of Shakespeare poems, and that's it.
That's our whole GPD model that we've
managed to implement in just a few hundred lines of code.