Now once we have a single block,
it's time to implement our transformer model.
To do this, we will again define a new class that inherits from the module type,
and to implement it,
we use all the types we've previously defined.
We'll start implementing this class with defining its building blocks.
If we recall to use our transformer model,
we first need to convert input token IDs into embedding vectors.
To do this, we'll use this embedding type.
This type will map each token ID to its own embedding vector.
The first parameter here is the number of embedding vectors,
which is the number of token IDs we have in our vocabulary.
The second parameter is dimensionality of embedding vectors.
We also need to implement the positional encoding that
produces embedding vectors for each position in the context window.
For this, we'll use the embedding type as well.
But the number of vectors in the stable is different.
We need a different vector for each position of the context window
so we pass the context size here for the number of vectors in this table.
We then create blocks for our model one by one and then combine them in the sequence.
This will allow us to apply these blocks one after the other.
We also add a final layer normalization,
and we also need to add one more component.
Remember that the output of each block consists of embedding vectors,
but we need to convert these vectors into predictions for token IDs.
To do this, we will add a linear layer that converts an embedding vector in
every position into prediction scores for what token ID should be generated.
We will pass the vocabulary size here,
since we need a prediction score for each of the token IDs in our vocabulary.
Now we need to implement the forward method,
and we first convert all token IDs into
embedding vectors and compute the positional encoding.
To compute it, we create a sequence of numbers from zero to the number of input tokens,
and then we pass it to this embedding layer.
We then add positional encoding to the embedding vectors.
To generate this sequence,
we need to get the number of input tokens from the input shape.
We then apply each transformer block one by one,
then we apply the normalization,
and finally, we convert embedding vectors into
logits for every position in the context window.
Now to test it, let's initialize our DemoGBT model using our configuration.
I will also move this model to GPU if it is available.
To test our model,
we encode a test phrase using our tokenizer and pass it to our model.
We need to use the unsqueeze method to add an extra dimension to our vector.
This is because the encode method returns a one dimensional tensor,
but our model expects a patch of inputs,
so we need to convert it into a two dimensional tensor,
and the output from our model will have the following shape.
In our case, the input had one sequence,
so we have a patch of Size 1.
This dimension is equal two because our input had two input tokens.
For every position, for this input phrase,
our model returned predictions for the next token ID,
and it gave prediction scores for every token in our vocabulary.
To rub this up, we need to define two more helper functions.
I'll first add a function called generate to create torch sequences using our model.
This function will receive a model to use,
a prompt converted to token IDs and the max number of tokens to generate.
What we'll do in this function,
we first initialize the output with the prompt IDs,
and on every iteration,
we pass the output we generated so far to our model to generate the next token.
We then get the logits from our model.
But we're only interested in logits in the latest position,
since this is the prediction for
the token that should be generated after the given prompt.
We only get these logits.
We then take these logits and we use
the softmax function to convert logits to probabilities.
You might think that at this stage,
we should get a token with the highest probability.
But it will lead to generating repetitive and boring outputs.
Instead, we sample the next token based on these probabilities,
instead of always taking the token with the highest probability.
This will generate a more interesting output,
and we will explore this aspect of LLMs in more details in some later videos.
Now, once we have the next token ID,
we add it to the output phrase,
and then we repeat this process.
Finally, we'll add another helper function.
This function will be called generate with prompt,
which will be a higher level of wrapper for the generate function.
It takes a prompt string,
and it encodes it using the tokenizer into token IDs.
It then takes this encoded prompt,
passes it with the model to the generate function,
and decode the result token IDs into a string.
We also call the eval method on our model to switch it into the inference mode.
Now, let's test our generate with prom function and
our transformer model and pass this prompt with the tokenizer and the model,
and see what we'll get.
As you can see, this function has worked.
We have the prompt at the beginning of the generated output.
But the remaining of the output is complete gibberish.
This is because we have not trained our model yet,
and this is exactly what we will do next.