Now let's take a look at how we can calculate
validation_loss for our model during training.
To do this, we first need to split our dataset into training and validation_dataset.
For this, we tokenize input text,
just as we did before,
and then we calculate how many tokens we want to use for training given this ratio.
We take this number of tokens as a training data,
and then we use the rest as validation_data.
Having training and validation_data,
we then create a validation_dataset,
and then we create a validation_dataloader.
Now we need to implement a function to calculate a validation_loss.
For this, we, first of all,
switch our model from training into the evaluation mode.
We should do this to run our model for inference, and this,
for example, deactivates the dropout layers we've added to our model.
Keep in mind that then we switch our model to
the training mode at the beginning of every training iteration.
We then create an iterator from our validation_dataset.
Then we run the loop for the specified number of batches,
and for every batch,
we do similar steps comparing to what we've done for the training.
We, first of all, get the inputs and targets.
We then pass these inputs to the model and get logits.
Then we reshape logits and targets,
and calculate the validation_loss using the cross_entropy function.
After this, we add the loss to the validation_loss on every iteration.
When the loop is finished,
we compute the average_loss by dividing
the total_loss by the number of batches we went through,
and then we return the average_loss.
Finally, we need to update our code to draw a chart of training and validation_losses.
First, we need to append training loss and training step to these two arrays,
and we need to use the item method to convert a tensor to a number,
and we do it for every training step.
Then we need to do the same for the validation_loss.
The reason why we need to store step number with loss values is because we calculate
training loss on every step and validation_loss only every 10 steps,
and we need to preserve step numbers for
the Matplotlib to correctly plot these charts and align values correctly.
I'll now rerun this notebook.
As you can see, we've got our training and validation_loss chart,
and if we wait for a few dozen iterations,
we will now see two lines on the chart,
one for the train loss and another for the validation_loss.