Before we start working on the transformer implementation,
we'll have a quick demo,
where we will cover PyTorch functions that we will use.
The goal of this demo is not to give you a comprehensive overview of PyTorch,
but it is to refresh your PyTorch knowledge.
In case if you don't know some of these functions,
it will make it easier for you to follow it later.
If you're already proficient with PyTorch,
you can just skip this section.
First, we'll see how we can create some random tensors,
which we will use for testing,
and we can do this using the torch rand function.
When we create a random tensor,
we can provide dimensions of a tensor that we want to create.
If we provide a single number like in this case,
it will create a random vector.
If we provide two numbers,
it will create a random tensor 5*5.
The other function the two will use is called ones,
and it allows us to create a tensor of specified dimensions that is filled with ones.
Just as with rant, if we provide a single number,
it will create a vector of size five as in this case,
or if we provide two numbers,
it will create a multi-dimensional tensor filled with ones.
If we need to create a tensor with a sequence of numbers,
we need to use the arrange function.
In this case, it will return a sequence of numbers from 0-9.
One interesting operation that we will need for
transformers is to create a triangular matrix,
where we have values only in the lower triangle of a square matrix.
To do this, we will use the trial function.
The way we need to use this function is we first of all need to create
another tensor and pass this tensor into the trill function.
What it will do, it will set zeros to all positions above the main diagonal.
While implementing transformers will also have to take multiple tensors
and create another tensor that joins values from existing tensors.
We can do this using the CAT function,
which stands for concatenation.
For example, in this particular case,
I have two tensors 2*2,
and I can either concatenate them along the rows or along the columns.
To concatenate them along the rows,
I need to pass them to the CAT function and specify dimension equal to zero.
Or if I do the same thing,
but specify dimension equal to one,
it will concatenate these tensors along the columns.
Now the last transformation that we will cover is called view.
What it allows us to do is to change the shape of a tensor that we have.
For example, in this case,
we have a vector with 12 numbers.
Using the view function,
we can transform it into 3*4 tensor,
all we need to do is to call the view function and specify the new dimensions.
We can also use a view to convert this two-dimensional tensor back into a vector.
In to do this, we need to call the view function
and specify the size of a vector we want to get.