Before we start implementing our model,
let's talk about how to prepare training data for it.
We'll first need to implement a tokenizer,
which will allow us to convert text into token IDs,
and we will look into how to do this in one of the next demos.
We'll also need to prepare a training dataset in a way
that will allow us to train our model to predict next token.
Remember that the goal of our model is to predict the next token.
Giving a single part of an input dataset,
we can generate several prediction tasks for our model at once.
Let's say we have a phrase.
The core innovation of transformers is the attention.
From this phrase, given the word the,
we want our model to predict core.
Given the that core,
we wanted to predict innovation,
and so on until given all input tokens except the last one,
we want our model to predict the last word.
The way we will represent this in our dataset is that inputs and
targets will be part of the same phrase but shifted by one position.
Of course, our model won't see words or tokens themselves.
Instead, we will convert tokens into token IDs.
Our training examples will look like this.
But when visualizing it,
it is easier to talk about the words rather than token IDs.
Now, when we perform a single training iteration,
we don't just send a single training example.
We will instead pick multiple random training examples and run our model on a set,
or, as it is usually called a training batch.
This allows to better utilize GPU resources during training.
In the next few videos,
we will talk about how to do this in Python.