Now, in this demo, we will implement a tokenizer for our transformer model.
As mentioned before, it will be a character based tokenizer,
which means that it will convert every character in an input string to a separate token.
Before we start working on it,
we need to add some Python touch boiler plate.
First of all, we add Python touch imports that we will use throughout this lesson.
Then we create a device variable which will be
assigned to Cuda if we have GPU available on this machine.
We will use it later to move our tensors and our models to GPU if it is available.
Now, before we start working on the tokenizer itself,
we need to load our dataset.
For the dataset, we will have this file called tiny Shakespeare that
contains all Shakespeare plays combined together into a single file.
We use the past type and the read text method,
we will get the text variable that will be
a long string that will contain all the Shakespeare play.
Now, if we look at the 4,000 characters in the string,
you will see that it contains a part of a Shakespeare play.
This is just the data that we need to train our model.
Now we can start building our tokenizer,
and first, I'll show you the interface that we will implement.
It will have a constructor that receives a vocabulary,
and a vocabulary will be just a list of
characters that our tokenizer will be able to process.
It will have a method to create a tokenizer from text.
It will have the encode method that will take
a string and convert it into a list of token IDs.
It will also have the decode method that does the opposite,
it receives a list of token IDs and converts them into a text.
The final method will return the vocabulary size or our tokenizer.
Let's start implementing these one by one.
The train from text method will receive the text
that we will use to get the list of unique characters.
It will use the set method to get all the distinct characters in the text.
It will then convert them into a list,
sort them and part to the chart tokenizer constructor.
Now, for the constructor,
our tokenizer will need to convert from characters to token IDs and vice versa.
For this, we'll have two different maps.
To construct these maps,
we will iterate over the list of characters.
For every character, we will get the character
itself and its position in this vocabulary.
Having these pairs of the position that we will make a token ID and the character,
we will create both of these maps.
In one, it will be a character to token ID,
and in the other one, it will be token ID to the character.
Now having these maps,
we can implement the encode and the code methods.
To implement the encode method,
we will iterate through every character in the input text,
and we will get the token ID for this character using our map.
We will append it to the list of token IDs.
Having this list of token IDs,
who will then convert it into a tensor using torch.tensor function.
The code method will work very similarly.
We will iterate through token IDs,
and the token IDs will be a tensor.
We first need to convert it into a list,
and then for every token,
we get the character for this token,
we append it to a list of characters,
and then we convert it into a string.
For the vocabulary size,
it will be very straightforward.
We will just get the length of one of these maps,
and they will have the same lens,
and both of them will have the same number of characters in now,
having our tokenizer implementation,
let's create an instance of our tokenizer and provide the whole training dataset into it,
we will get our tokenizer.
Now having a tokenizer,
let's try to encode the how world string into a list of token IDs.
If we run it, we get a tensor with different token IDs for this input string.
If you look closely, you will see that
character L is now represented as token ID number 50.
For every position where we had the L character.
We now have token AD equal to 50.
Having the list of tokens,
we can also decode it using the decode method.
If we pass the result of code into the decode method,
we will get our string back.
Now we can also get the vocabulary size, which was 65,
which means that our input data set only had 65 unique characters.
Now, one final thing that I'll show to you is I'll
show you the mapping between characters, and this is it.
This is our whole tokenizer implementation,
and having this tokenizer,
we can start processing our dataset,
and then we can start building our model.