Now, once we have a tokenizer,
we will look into how to handle datasets in PyTorch.
There are two types that PyTorch provides for us to work with datasets.
Dataset is a class that allows loading and processing data.
Data loader is a class that allows us to iterate over samples in a PyTorch dataset.
Let's look into these types one by one.
To define a dataset,
we first need to define a new class that inherits from
the dataset class that we import from the torch.utils.data.
As an example, let's see how we can implement a dataset that stores
a list of samples and allows to perform arbitrary transformations on that.
To implement a dataset,
we need to implement three methods.
A constructor that receives arbitrary parameters.
In this case, we have two parameters,
data to store and a transformation to apply.
The second method that we need to implement is len
that returns a number of elements in the dataset.
The final method we need to implement is get item that returns
an item from the provided position that is passed as the index parameter.
In this particular example,
our dataset receives a list of samples and a function to transform each sample.
The implementation of the len method just
needs to return the number of samples in the list.
In the getitem method,
we need to get a sample with the provided index,
apply transformation, and return the transformed result.
This is, of course, a very simple dataset,
but they can be arbitrary complex,
they can low data from external storage,
apply complex transformations, and so on.
Here's how we could use our dataset implementation.
Let's say we have a dataset of images.
To use it, we can create an instance of the custom dataset class we've just implemented,
pass a list of images,
and a function to transform each image before returning it.
In this case, we provide a function that resizes
each image before we get it from a dataset.
Having this class, we can get a number of samples in our dataset using the len function,
or we can get an image from a certain position in this dataset.
Additionally, we can iterate over samples in our dataset.
However, when training a model,
we usually don't use a single sample on every training iteration.
Using a single sample at a time is called stochastic gradient descent,
and it does not allow us to utilize resources in an efficient way.
The other issue is that the training loss will also
fluctuate greatly from one iteration to the other.
We want to use multiple examples on every training iteration.
Using the whole dataset on every iteration is called batch gradient descent.
But it is impractical in many cases.
Using the whole dataset is computationally expensive and will require a lot of memory.
Instead, in most cases,
models are trained using so called mini batches.
When on every training iteration,
we would use a small subset of training samples and train our model using this subset.
Each subset of samples used on a single iteration is called a mini-batch.
Using mini-batches is more manageable than using
a whole data set and leads to better results.
It also allows to utilize resources more efficiently,
allowing to train our model on multiple samples on every iteration.
To iterate other mini-batches from our dataset,
we need to use another type called DataLoader.
Here is how DataLoader and dataset types are used.
We first need to create an instance of a dataset to provide access to our data.
We then need to create an instance of DataLoader to iterate over the training data.
Then the training code can use DataLoader instance
to load a patch of data at a time and use it for training.
We don't need to implement a custom type to use a DataLoader.
We need to create an instance of the DataLoader type,
pass our dataset, and the size of a batch it should return.
Then we can iterate over the DataLoader instance to get our data split into batches.
On every iteration of the sloop,
the data variable will contain 64 elements
from the custom dataset that we can now use to train our model.