Now we will start building our model.
We will go through it step by step and learn about how every part of it is structured,
and we will gradually build it in PyTorch.
The first step of our model is to process the input that was sent to it.
We would need to tokenize the input and convert each token into a token ID.
Then we'll convert each token into a corresponding word embedding.
After this step, instead of having a vector with three token IDs,
we'll have a matrix with three vectors,
and each vector will be an embedding for a corresponding input token.
A few things to note about this output.
First, the word embeddings,
the model selects depends solely on the token IDs.
For the same token ID,
we will always get the same word embedding vector.
Second, these word embeddings will be trained together with our model.
We don't define them upfront.
They are defined during our models training.
To create an instance of this class,
we'll need to specify the size of our vocabulary, which in this case,
we arbitrary set to 10,000,
and we need to specify the size of each embedding vector which we'll set to 75.
Then we'll create an instance of the nn embedding and
provide both the vocabulary size and the size of the embedding vectors.
To use it, we need to get a list of token IDs we want to convert to embedding vectors.
Here we define arbitrary IDs, but in our code,
we will use a tokenizer to convert tokens into token IDs.
Then we pass token IDs to the instance of nn embedding.
Embedding will produce a tensor with four vectors,
each of size 75 which is the size of embedding vector we've selected.
As you can see from this shape,
the nn embedding returns an embedding vector per each input token ID.
Before we can send these embedding vectors to our model,
we need to do one more thing.
We need to take another matrix called
positional encoding and add it to the word embeddings.
Positional encoding is another matrix that allows us
to inject positional information about input tokens.
This information will help the model to understand the relative order of input tokens.
The positional encoding matrix is fixed and does not depend on the input.
We simply add the same values for every single set of word embeddings our model receives.
Where do we get these values?
In some models, including the ones that we will build,
these are trained together with other model parameters.
But in some other LLMs,
these are defined using a complex formula and don't change during training.