Before we dive into the transformer architecture,
we need to talk about the softmax function,
since we will use it in a few places when we will implement our model.
An important observation is that an output of
a neural network layer can contain pretty much any numerical values.
These raw output values are also called logits.
In some cases, we need to convert logits
produced by a model into a probability distribution.
To create a probability distribution from logits,
we need to make sure that every logit value will be converted into a value from
0-1 and that the sum of all result values should be equal to 1.
A common way to do this is to use the softmax function. Here is how it works.
When we want to convert logit to the probabilities, for every logit,
we need to take this logit value and raise e to the power of this logit value.
We have e^1.2, e^1.4, and so on.
Raising e, a positive number,
to any power will give us a positive number,
and we've immediately satisfied the first requirement making all outputs positive.
Now, how do we make sure that all output values of the softmax function sum up to one?
To do this, we first compute the sum of all these values we've got so
far that we write in this shorter mathematical notation.
Then having this sum,
we need to divide each value by the value of this sum.
This will make sure that the sum of result values will be equal to one.
That's it. That's how we compute the softmax function.
Now, once you are familiar with how softmax is calculated,
it will be easier to understand the mathematical notation, which looks like this.
Where for every output value,
we calculate the exponents and divide each one of them by the sum of all exponents.
The output of the softmax function is
a probability distribution that we can represent using a histogram.
Softmax function has some interesting properties.
If one input value is much larger than the rest,
softmax will return a probability that is
significantly higher than probabilities for other outputs.
In this case, softmax returns 0.9 for the largest value in the input.
For all the smaller logit values,
it will return probabilities that are close to zero.
If there are several logits with similar values,
softmax will return similar probability values for each one of them.