In this video, we will cover the core of how transformer models work.
Specifically, we will look into how
the attention mechanism is implemented in transformers.
To remind you, transformer models consist of multiple blocks.
Every block refines the embedding vectors for each
token using the context of other embedding vectors.
The way this is done is that an attention block first computes
attention scores and then updates
embedding values in each position using these attention scores.
Let's now look at how it is implemented step by step.
The first step in the attention block is to calculate a so called query matrix.
The way this is done is we take the matrix with
embedding vectors and multiply it by another matrix called W_Q.
It will produce a matrix with the same number of vectors,
but each vector will have a different smaller dimension.
This matrix is called queries or Q for short.
To make it easier, we will represent the queries matrix like this.
Where instead of displaying every value in this matrix,
we will just display an array of vectors for the Q matrix.
In addition to computing the Q matrix,
we need to compute another matrix called keys.
We do it in a similar way.
We take inputting embedding vectors and multiply them by another matrix called W_Q,
which produces the keys matrix or key for short.
What are the conceptual roles of these matrices?
We can think of them as if queries are asking
questions about other words in the sentence.
For example, those could be nouns looking for verbs,
and vectors in this matrix represent these questions,
and the role of the keys is to answer these questions asked by queries.
Having these two matrices,
we should find out what keys match to what queries.
To represent this in terms of matrix multiplications,
we would look for what queries are most similar to what keys.
We already know how to do this for vectors.
We can do this by computing a dot product between
each pair of vectors in Q and K matrices.
The larger the value of each dot product,
the more similar a pair of a key and the query is.
What we want to do is to compute dot products
between each pair of vectors in matrices Q and K,
and this will result in another matrix.
If you remember your linear algebra,
this should sound very familiar.
To compute a pairwise product between vectors in two matrices,
we need to multiply these two matrices,
and we also need to transpose the K matrix to make sure that dimensions match.
The result matrix will contain the attention scores.
However, one issue we discussed before
is that dot product can result in pretty much any value.
Before we can use these attention scores,
we need to convert them.
What we want to do is we want to make sure that
the sum of each column should equal to one,
and the greater the dot product result is,
the greater the result value in this column should be.
If you recall, we've already discussed that we
can use the softmax function just for this.
What we will do is we'll pass every column
of this resulting matrix through the softmax function.
Now, all values in each column will be between zero and one,
and they will sum up to one.
To help you to keep track of what we've done so far,
I'll show a small diagram of all operations we've already covered.
We first take the input matrix, with embedding vectors,
and then from the same input,
we want to get two matrices,
Q and K. We then perform a matrix multiplication between these two matrices,
and we apply the softmax function.
This results in the attention scores we can now use to update the embedding vectors.
To do this, we need to take the values of another matrix called V,
which we get in a similar way to how we got the matrices Q and K. Then we'll
multiply each vector in this matrix by the corresponding attention scores.
This multiplication of the V vectors by
this scores will give us a new embedding vector in every single position.
Specifically, to compute a new vector for Position 2,
we take the V_1 vector from the V matrix.
We multiply it by this 0.046 score,
then we get the V_2 vector,
we multiply it by the second score, and so on.
The weighted sum of all these vectors given
the attention scores is a new embedding vector for Position 2,
and we do this for all vectors in all positions.
Now, we can draw a complete diagram of computations in the attention block.
First, we compute matrices Q, K,
and V from input embedding vectors by multiplying them by different matrices.
We then multiply Q and K matrices
and use the softmax function to compute the attention scores.
After this, we use the attention scores and
the V matrix to get the updated embedding vectors.
In models like GPT,
we don't calculate attention scores just once.
What we've covered was a so called a single-head of attention.
Instead, this process is split in multiple similar computations or attention heads.
They do the same computations but with different parameters.
This is done because the words in a sentence can relate in different ways,
and having multiple-heads calculating
separate attention scores allow us to learn different relationships.
Each attention head outputs part of the result embedding vectors,
and we then concatenate them together to form new embedding vectors.
Now, once we've covered how the attention is calculated,
we can wrap up this video by looking at the formula of the attention.
We'll get this formula straight from the attention is all you need paper.
The attention is a formula of three matrices: Q,
K, and V. We've covered most of what it does.
We multiply matrices Q and K. One
thing we didn't cover yet is that we then divide the result by
the square root of the size of a vector in matrix
K. This is done to ensure that attention scores don't get too large.
We then apply the softmax function to calculate the attention scores.
Then we multiply the result by the V matrix.
I have to say it's a very short and concise way of representing this,
but I hope that once you went through these steps one by one,
this formula now makes more sense.