In the previous lessons,
you learned how to use univariate and bivariate plots to visualize your data,
one or two variables at a time.
In most of these cases,
you use position like in scatter plots,
or length like in bar charts for encoding your variables.
This is because our perception for values is most precise with these encodings.
This presents an issue for when we want to move on to multi-variate plots,
or plots of three, or more variables.
There will be ambiguity in value,
if we try to embed three positional dimensions into a flat, two-dimensional image.
Take for example this point on the three-dimensional axes here.
What does that point's value on x, y, and z?
Due to perspective, there are multiple possible values it could take.
We can resolve the ambiguity with additional markings,
but this is unreasonable if we have lots of data.
In this lesson, you will learn about encodings that can be
used to create effective multi-variate plots.
You will also see other techniques like fastening
that can expand on bivariate plots to make them multivariate.
You will also learn about additional techniques that will help you in your analysis.