As part of your bivariate exploration,
you might be interested in relationships between lots of variables.
You could explore these relationships two variables at a time,
but there are other techniques besides multi-variate plots to
explore multiple pairwise relationships at the same time.
In a plot matrix,
a grid of plots is generated.
Unlike a faceted plot where each subplot is based on one subset of the data,
each subplot in a plot matrix is based on the whole data,
but with two different variables on the axes.
Each row and column corresponds with one variable.
For example, this plot shows the relationship between sugars and fats.
Along the diagonal, the row variable and column variable match up.
A univariate plot of each variable is usually placed along this diagonal line.
A plot matrix is good for getting
a broad overview of pairwise relationships between variables.
Considering that the size of each subplot will be fairly small,
a plot matrix is best as
an initial exploratory tool to lead you to points of further interest.
You should follow up a plot matrix by generating
additional plots of specific variable sets on their own.
We can also adapt heatmaps to depict
the pairwise correlations between variables in our data.
Like the plot matrix,
each row and column corresponds with a single variable.
The value and color depicted in each cell is
the correlation between the corresponding row and column variables.
This is another good summary option for
exploration when starting with a lot of variables.