In this lesson, we're going to look at plot matrices.
Let's start by doing our normal imports.
What is a plot matrix?
Well, let's say we're interested in looking at
the pairwise relationships between all of our numeric variables.
Instead of plotting scatter plots one by one,
we might want to just inspect them all at once.
That is the subject of this lesson.
That's using what's called plot matrices.
Let's start by importing our normal functions for data analysis and visualization,
as well as loading our fuel economy dataset.
To create a plot matrix,
we can just use seaborns pair grid function.
Note that I'm only focusing on four specific variables here: highway efficiency,
city efficiency, engine size, and CO_2 emissions.
If we do not specify the variables parameter,
the V-A-R-S or vars parameter.
We will plot then a matrix of all numeric variables.
It's going to take a very long time to generate and it'll just be a lot to read.
Instead, I just want to focus on these here.
Also please note that I specify both the off-diagonal and diagonal elements.
For the off-diagonal elements,
I'm requesting seaborn to use scatter plots.
For the diagonal elements I'm going to use histograms.
For instance, if we look all of the rows and all of
the columns are in the same order as the order that we gave.
If we look along the diagonal,
we will see in this first row and column, highway efficiency.
This is a histogram of highway efficiency.
Then the next diagonal element is city efficiency and so on.
Looking at the first row and second column,
we see that highway is our y axis,
while city is our x-axis,
and if we scroll down here,
we see that the x label is correct.
Likewise, for the third column and first row,
we have highway versus engine displacement,
so we see the bivariate plot there.
Each row and each column works with a variable.
For the diagonals as I said,
we're only plotting one variable.
I chose to display a histogram but
a KDE or any other univariate plot would probably work well.
Note also that there's a symmetry in a pair grid
with x and y axes are flipped across the diagonal.
In this way, by looking at the first row and second column,
we see highway versus city efficiency.
But if we then go to the opposite cell or the symmetric cell,
we get city versus highway efficiency.
The bivariate plot is flipped.
For the diagonals, we only plot one variable.
In this case, I chose to display a histogram but
a KDE or other univariate plot would probably work well.
Another useful thing common in analysis is plotting a correlation matrix.
We do this by first extracting the correlation from
the data frame and then dropping this into a heatmap.
Here, we use the seaborn heatmap method and we just toss in the correlation.
In this case, I'm only selecting the columns that we used earlier.
Right here, this shows that city and
highway efficiency are highly correlated, which is not shocking.
It also shows that engine size and emissions are highly correlated,
which is also expected.
Fuel efficiency and engine size,
and therefore CO_2 emissions are highly anti-correlated.
One thing to note is I added a vmin which is a vertical minimum of negative 1.
This sets the minimum value of the color bar and seaborn.
Also for correlation matrix,
typically you want to make sure that they're square because they are
symmetric and so you can pass in the parameter square equals true.