This lesson will focus on a few aspects of feature engineering,
which is similar to things you may be familiar with from data wrangling.
In particular, we're going to look at the feature cross and also one-hot encoding.
We're also going to start by looking at a new dataset that
looks at a subsample of taxi rides in New York City.
This dataset comes from the New York City taxi and Limousine Commission and
it's packaged as part of seaborne and can be loaded directly from Jupiter.
You can find all of the other seaborne provided datasets
on seaborne GitHub page. Let's take a look.
We can start by doing our normal imports and then by using seaborne load dataset method.
We see here that this dataset has
6,400 different taxi rides split between 14 different feature columns.
Before we get too far into this,
you may like to take a minute and explore this dataset to get a feel for it.
Now, the feature crosses a broad category of
feature engineering where you combine multiple features.
Often these features are numeric.
For instance, in this case,
we may want to determine the distribution of trips.
We can do that by subtracting the pickup and drop-off times.
Since these are datetime objects will have to convert them to seconds.
We can use the DataFrame d-types method to see that indeed,
pickup and drop-off are both datetime methods.
Here, I'm going to take the difference between the drop-off and pick-up times,
and then I'm going to use
a Lambda function to convert them to the total number of seconds.
Then I'm going to use seaborne to create a histogram of travel time.
Now another thing we might like to do is see how this changes for different boroughs.
Customers can of course go from one borough to another,
so we really only want to look at those that start and stop in the same borough.
Here, I'm going to create a simple series of
true-false values to see if the pickup and drop-off borough are the same.
First, I create a series where I say,
is the drop-off borough the same as the pickup borough.
This will create a series of true and false values that
I then used to create a new feature.
Then I look at only the subset of data with true,
and then look at travel time.
Note, I only use the dataset where trip stayed in the same borough and
then I used hue to look at different ones by color.
Now, although I'm not using the specific feature cross to draw conclusions,
it did help me plot intro-borough travel times very quickly with only two lines of code.
Also, we see that we have a lot more trips in
Manhattan so we should probably look at relative frequencies between them.
We can do this by using the statistics parameter and setting it equal to percent,
and then setting the common norm parameter to false,
meaning that each borough will have its own normalization.
We see here that the distributions look fairly similar.
However, there are very few trips from the Bronx,
so the statistics just to have a lot of outliers.
Lastly, another example of a feature cross is to numerically manipulate features.
For instance, we might want to know if rides with
multiple passengers have different costs or simply,
what is the cost per passenger?
For instance, we can just take the total cost and
divide that by the number of passengers to get the cost per passenger.
Then we can plot this.
Or we might also create a new feature
specifying whether the ride was solo or multi passenger.
Once again, I can use a Lambda function to say if the number of passengers was one,
call it solo, otherwise call it multi passenger.
I can save this into its own series and then quickly use a box plot to show that indeed,
we see that if you travel with friends,
the total cost per person is advantageous on average.
Finally, I would like to introduce one-hot encoding,
which turns a categorical variable into a binary variable.
This means it turns it into a one or zero,
a true or a false.
This is often useful in machine learning contexts,
but you also might see it in data visualization.
To one-hot encode features,
you can use the pandas get dummies method.
If you don't specify a column,
it will operate on all categorical variables.
For instance, if we look at our DataFrame,
will notice that our starting DataFrame has 6,400 rows and 18 features.
But if we just apply get_dummies to the entire DataFrame,
it blows up to now 423 columns.
To get a better idea of what this looks like,
let's just specify the payment column.
Here we see when we pass and get_dummies with our DataFrame and specify that column,
it goes from 18 columns to 19 columns.
Basically, it goes from
payment and then converts it to payment cash or payment credit card,
where if that ride was paid with a credit card,
it will have a zero for cash and a one for credit card, and vice versa.