In this worksheet, I'm going to look at how to use shape
or size to encode a third variable in scatter plots.
We're going to start by importing the libraries for
both data analysis and visualization and also the fuel economy dataset.
We will also be extracting transmission type,
looking at automatic and manual vehicles.
Now, we have too much data to plot.
To reduce over plotting,
we're going to take a random subset of 200 cars.
Then we're going to combine that with a small amount of
horizontal jitter to ensure plotting markers don't overlap.
To do this, we're going to use Numpy's random library,
where we randomly select 200 rows without replacement.
Here you see our new DataFrame,
df_subset only has 200 rows.
Recall that both the reg plot and scatter functions do have a marker parameter.
However, this specifies the specific marker to use and it only takes a string.
If we were to look at, let's just say,
automatic transmission from our df_subset and
recreate a regression plot where our x-variable is engine displacement.
The y-variable is combined efficiency.
We're going to add a little bit of x jitter to make it easier to
read and we're also not going to plot our regression line.
We end up with something like this.
For marker, I selected an upward pointing carrot or triangle.
However, we want to plot both automatic and manual.
In order to do this, we set up a list of lists called T-type.
In this list of lists,
we have the category or the class category,
automatic or manual, and then also the marker we want to use.
We then loop over this list of lists.
Here we plot our reg plot for just that one list of data.
We plot here for our reg plot only one list at a time.
Note that because we sampled our DataFrame,
your plot might look slightly different than mine,
but should show similar trends.
It's worth noting that because we plotted reg plot multiple times,
Seaborn knew to plot each one with its own unique color.
This is fortunate since the two transmission types have quite a good deal of overlap.
For the legend, we use Matplotlib's legend function.
As an argument to this function,
we give a list of labels to place on the legend one for each reg plot call.
Now, instead of transmission type,
what happens if we wanted to add carbon dioxide emissions as a third variable?
Since CO_2 is numeric,
one encoding we could use is marker size.
The goal would be higher CO_2 emissions would result in larger markers.
Matplotlib's scatter function, we can set marker size with the S parameter,
setting it to the name of the column we want to map it to, CO_2.
Reg plot, we set the parameter as part of a dictionary on scatter keyword arguments.
Here, we're going to divide the values by two.
The trend seems pretty clear to me.
It seems that as engine size increases,
the circles tend to be a little bit larger,
meaning that CO_2 emissions increase.
But CO_2 is numeric data.
This doesn't really give us any sense of scale.
To understand how the markers grow with emissions,
we want to add a legend that tells us what a smaller circle really needs.
But we have a small problem here when it comes to adding a legend.
We only have one scatter plot, which is CO_2,
so the legend only gives us a single dot as you see up here.
As a workaround,
we can actually plot
multiple dummy scatter plot sequences so we can construct our own legend.
Here, I'm going to plot what we saw above.
But now, before I plot the legend,
I am going to plot only the sizes for CO_2 at 200,
350, and 500 units.
We're now going to loop over these.
For each of them,
we're going to have an empty scatter plot.
Then it will plot those empty scatter plots on top of the original one we plotted,
and then put the legend on top of that.
Now we have the same plot with a meaningful legend to give us a sense of scale.
The legend function,
note that up until now we've only seen it with one argument,
the labels for the plot.
However, in this case,
we see that the legend function takes
two or three arguments or can take two or three arguments.
One is the legend objects.
The second one is the list of names.
Finally, if we want to give it a unique title,
we can provide that as well.