In this lesson, we're going to talk about adding color as an encoding.
Now, color is a natural encoding regime for additional variables
and it's easily supported by both Matplotlib and Seaborn.
To get started, let's begin by doing our normal imports and also importing our data set.
There are many ways to add color to Seaborn plots and this lesson we're going to use
facet grid and we're going to specifically set for our facet grid a hue parameter.
In this case, we're going to set it to be transmission type.
We're going to plot specifically regression plot
looking at fuel efficiency versus engine size.
Note that the hue parameter sets the transmission type that we're interested in.
Also, hue order allows us to specify the order that would like to use.
Note also that because we only have a single plot,
I decided to set the aspect ratio to 1.5,
which gives us a larger plot,
50% longer than it is tall.
Now, let's look at vehicle class instead.
Vehicle class is an ordered variable so
the qualitative palette doesn't work quite as well instead,
we should specify a sequential palette.
This can be set through facet grids with the palette parameter.
Also note that we can use the same strings as in Matplotlib in this case,
I'll use verity reverse.
This palette not only goes from light to dark,
but it also has a good range of hues to further
discriminate between the various vehicle classes.
If instead we have a numeric variable,
such as CO_2 emissions,
we should not just set the variable and the hue parameter,
since facet grids only expect to facet across categorical variables.
If we do that, we're going to get a messy legend with
one color for every unique CO_2 value.
Instead, we should just use the basic Matplotlib scatter function to create our plot.
We lose the convenient jitter in this case,
but there's an interaction in
the color parameters that make coloring by value hard to do.
With scatter adding a third numeric variable is as simple as setting the C parameter,
which stands for color.
We can also set our own color palette using the CMAP parameter.
Finally, for the color bar,
we wanted to add a label to that also to make it clear what we are seeing on this axis.