Use of additional encodings is not
the only way to include a third variable in a multivariate plot.
One other way of adding an additional dimension to plots is through the use of faceting.
When we facet univariate plots by levels of a second variable,
we get a bivariate plot.
When we facet bivariate plots by levels of a third variable,
we get a multivariate plot.
Earlier in this lesson,
you saw the multivariate scatter plot of interest rates by loan amounts,
with different borrower classes indicated by different point shapes.
One alternative way that we could have displayed the data is by
faceting by the categorical variable like this.
Separating each borrower class into its own subplot.
We aren't limited to faceting by only one variable.
We could also choose to facet plots across two variables,
one on the rows, and one on the columns.
If we had known period as another variable,
then we could facet the data by rows in addition to the classes by columns.