In this lesson, we're going to talk about faceting in multiple directions.
In this way, faceting can be extended to
multivariate cases by having each facet be a bivariate plot instead.
We're going to start by doing our normal imports,
both of our libraries and visualization packages,
but also our fuel economy dataset.
We will also be creating a feature called transmission type,
where we just focus on automatic versus manual transmissions.
Here we're going to use a facet grid of
our DataFrame where the columns are vehicle class.
Now we use our facet grid mapping function to plot
a bivariate scatter plot looking at combined deficiency versus engine size.
Notice that now we get columns where each column is a different vehicle class.
We're not limited to only fascinating by one variable either.
We can also add a row term.
For example we can add now row equals transmission type with the same mapping function.
We now end up with this,
where each row is for a transmission class.
For example this top row is for automatic,
the bottom is for manual transmissions and each column is for different vehicle class.
This is very difficult to read the titles of.
One thing we can do is we can now set the perimeter margin titles equal to true.
This now moves the row titles to the rows for easier reading.
Now the row titles you can find over here on the right side of the plot, much cleaner.