In the previous lesson,
you saw how histograms and bar charts can be adapted into
bivariate plots by changing the count axis to indicate the mean of a second variable.
We can follow a similar approach for heat maps and clustered bar charts,
to change them from bivariate plots into multivariate plots.
For example, let's take this heat map
regarding shots made over a series of basketball games.
X and y positions are relative to the basket which is at the origin.
In this multivariate plot,
the color shows the third variable,
how accurate shots were in each region of the court.
Darker colors indicate a higher proportion of shots made.
You can see that very generally,
the shots that were closer to the basket had a higher chance of making it in.