Welcome to Lesson 7.
In this lesson, we're going to look at other adaptations of bivariate plots.
Let's start by importing the libraries we're going to need,
as well as our fuel economy dataset and extracting our transmission type.
To add color to most seaborne plots,
we can just provide this new parameter called hue.
For example, if we look at a point plot and plot
the combined vehicle highway city efficiency versus vehicle class,
we can then also segment by transmission type.
Using this point plot,
we can end up getting something like this.
This hue parameter is common for most seaborne plots.
We can create similar plots for a clustered bar chart.
This is an adapted cluster bar chart.
The only difference is now instead of a point plot,
we're passing in bar plot with the hue parameter.
Similarly, we can create a similar comparison using
the box plot function to create a clustered box chart.
Once again, our x-variable is vehicle class,
our y is combined fuel efficiency,
and our hue is transmission type.
I have also added rotation for the x-label,
15 degrees to make it easier to view.
We can also adapt heatmaps,
that is 2D histograms,
so that instead of color being based on count,
color is based on the average of a third variable.
Let's start by plotting a 2D histogram of combined efficiency versus engine displacement.
Color is going to be the total number of counts.
I'm going to set a minimum threshold for a cell to be colored to
be 0.5 and I'm going to choose my color palette.
Here we have our 2D histogram of
a fuel efficiency versus displacement where each bin shows the number of counts.
Let's now change this so that color shows the average CO2 output for each bin.
This uses the weight parameter of the hist 2D function.
By default, each points weight is worth one so that the colors reflect the total counts.
If we change it so that each points weight is equal to
its CO2 emissions divided by the number of cars in that bin,
then the total within each bin will be the average.
Let's break this into steps.
Our first step is to figure out in which bin each point falls.
We compute this using the pandas cut function.
We pass in the series or the array from the DataFrame,
the bin sizes and then we have to recast that to ensure it's an integer.
Next, we count up the points that fall in each bin.
We do this by using a group by statement over
both the engine size and efficiency bin sizes.
Then we use the pivot method to then group that into one, two-dimensional array.
Finally, we use the values attribute to get the number of points as an array.
Now, we can get our point weights using all of these values.
We take the CO2 series and divide each element
by the number of points in each bin just right here.
We can now pass this to the weights parameter of our 2D hist function.
What we see here is pretty clear that as engine size gets larger,
efficiency goes down, which also means the emissions go up drastically.