Welcome to Control Flow in Python.
In this lesson, we're going to be exploring several ways to carefully and
creatively manage our precise Python programs with crafty statements and logic.
Think about when you give someone directions or someone gave you directions.
While you're driving on this road,
look out for the street lamp.
Stop, then take a right.
Or continue on the current road until the end and then park. Something like that.
When we write our Python programs,
we will use various statements and keywords to signal our code to run,
only under certain conditions,
which we'll call conditional statements,
or to execute our code for only certain periods of time,
which will happen with a code format called loops.
Thanks to control flow and Python,
we don't have to write code again and again and again.
Remember, our time is valuable when we're working on important or time critical projects.
We need code that reflects this urgency when and where it is needed.
Let's see a very quick example of why we like and rely on control flow with Python.
Let's say we have a function and we want to greet someone x number of times.
In this case, let's say four times.
If we didn't have control flow,
we would need to do something like this,
where we would define a function with deaf grit,
and then we would say print.
Hello world. We would close out that print statement.
Then what we would need to do is that we would need to
call this greet function four times.
One, 2, 3, 4.
You might think this makes sense,
call the function four times.
But what if you have thousands or millions of
users and the greeting message could change?
This would be a huge file.
There has to be a better way.
When we run this, this would run four times.
But the more that we need to run these types of functions,
we're going to need a more scalable process.
Enter control flow in Python,
and we're going to be learning about
crafty and clever ways to manage this in the subsequent modules.
If you're ready to use Python to navigate repetitive tasks efficiently and effectively,
let's dive in together.