When we think about working with numbers and for loops,
let's run an example where we can see exactly how to use
a for loop to iterate over a sequence of numbers using the range function.
We'll be going through the range function in an upcoming section,
so don't worry about memorizing it right now.
But let's look at why a for loop is
the best choice when iterating through a range of numbers.
We'll declare our for loop like this,
and we'll say for i in range 5,
and then we'll print i.
This code outputs the numbers from 0-4,
the numbers between 0-5 denoted with this range function.
Using a for loop here is more optimal than
a while loop for iterating through a range of numbers,
because once we execute this code,
we're able to get all of those numbers very easily and
cleanly using this range function to count up to five.
Now, let's see how for loops work with strings.
In this example, we're going to be iterating over each character in the word Python.
This allows us to handle each character individually within
a loop through the for loop construction.
For loops can iterate over each character in a string,
allowing us to count our way through a list of characters. Let's see how to do that.
We'll first declare a variable called word and we'll set that equal to a string,
which we put the Python word in for.
Then we'll say for letter in word,
and then we'll print letter.
What we're doing is we're saying for
the incrementable item in word print, what its value is.
Can you guess what the output will be here?
This will output each letter in the word Python like this.
And if you guessed that, you're right.
Great job. Next,
let's see how for loops work with lists.
A list in Python is another way to say array,
which is a fancy word for saying a collection of things put inside of square brackets.
If we had a list of fruits in an array defined by brackets,
we could use a for loop to iterate over
each fruit to tell us which fruits are in that list.
Let's see an example of how to do this.
So first, we will create a list,
which would be a variable set equal to square brackets,
and then a list of items,
which we'll put as strings here.
So apple, banana, cherry, and grape fruit.
Next, we'll write a for loop to iterate over each of these items in the list.
We'll say for fruit in fruits,
and then we'll print each fruit item.
What we're doing is we're saying for each item,
and we could call this really anything.
We could call it i, we could call it item,
we could call it shopping cart item,
but we're going to call it fruit in fruits,
which is the array we set above here,
and then we're going to print each of those items in the list that it finds.
Can you guess what the output will be here?
We get apple, banana, cherry,
and grape fruit in the same order that is defined in the list.
If you said this, you're right. Great job.
Next up, let's see how for loops work with tuples.
A tuple is similar to a list like what we just saw earlier,
but data can easily be changeable.
We could have two fruits or 20 fruits,
depending on what you put in your shopping cart, for example.
But what if we had data that couldn't or shouldn't ever change?
We call that type of data immutable,
which is a fancy word for saying the data cannot be changed, edited,
or deleted after it's created,
and is organized in parentheses,
not brackets, like a list.
That being said, we can still iterate over a tuple in the same way as a list above.
Let's see how we can iterate over a tuple.
We'll set our coordinates variable equal to a tuple of coordinates.
We'll say 43, say 62,
and we'll say 89.
Then we'll write our for loop and we'll say for coordinate in
coordinates, we'll print coordinate.
What we're doing here is that we're setting an immutable set of data,
which we're calling a tuple here,
and then we're going to iterate over
each item in our coordinate tuple, and print that out here.
Can you guess what the output will be?
Here, we'll see an output of each coordinate in the tuple: 43,
right here, 62 right there,
and 89 right there.
Now, let's see how for loops work with sets.
A set is a collection of unique items organized with curly brackets,
and have some unique properties that make them very different
from the other data structures we've mentioned previously.
Sets are unordered, meaning the items do not have a defined order,
and their sequence may vary each time you use them.
They're also unindexed, so you cannot access items by their position in a set.
They are also mutable,
allowing you to add and remove items.
Although once an item is added to that set,
its value cannot be changed.
Finally, they only contain unique items,
meaning any duplicate values will be ignored.
Here's how we can iterate over a set.
What we'll do is that we will write a set like this and we'll say unique_fruits equal.
We'll put curly bracket here,
and then we'll put in a list of fruits like this.
Then in our for loop,
we'll say for fruit in unique_fruits right here,
put a colon and then we'll print fruit.
This will output each unique fruit in the set.
Can you guess what the output of this will be once we execute it?
We see cherry, banana, and apple.
If you said that, you're right.
This will output each unique fruit in the set,
but notice how apple is only printed once,
as it's right there and right there,
but it's only printed out once there,
because it is a duplicate,
and we will only see unique items in a set,
and that's why we only see these items here.
As we continue to work with for loops and sets,
let's see another example of how we could use a for loop to check
a membership allow list for multiple items against a set.
Let's see how to do that. First,
we'll create a set and declare that as the allowed users.
And in this set, we have Alice, Bob, and Charlie.
Next, we'll create a list of users_to_check,
and we'll define this as a list,
an array called users_to_check,
and that has David,
Alice, Eve, and Bob.
Then we'll write our for loop to check over each user.
We'll write for user in users_to_check with a colon,
and then we'll say if user in allowed_users will print an f statement,
An f string here,
and we'll say user is allowed.
We'll close out that print statement.
Then we'll say else,
and then we'll print the else statement,
and we'll do another f string,
and we'll say user is not allowed, then we'll close that up.
In this example, the for loop iterates over each user in the users_to_check list.
Then checks if that user is in the allowed_users variable,
which we've declared as a set,
which is happening right here.
The result is printed accordingly.
This approach leverages the efficiency of sets for
membership testing within a loop that processes multiple items.
Can you guess what the output is going to be here?
Let's run this code and find out.
After running the cell, we see David is not allowed,
Alice is allowed, Eve is not allowed,
and Bob is allowed.
We can see this because in the users_to_check,
David does not appear in the allowed list of users.
However, Alice is in that list.
Eve does not appear in the set of allowed users,
but Bob is. Bob is there.
We do see that Charlie is one of the allowed users,
but does not show up in the users_to_check list.
Did you notice that only two users are allowed in this user check as well?
Again, this is because Charlie did not come up in the users_to_check list,
so we wouldn't have iterated over Charlie
when we were checking our user and users_to_check.
As you can see, for loops are very versatile, powerful,
and can be used to iterate over many different types
of varied sequences and collections in Python.
For loops can also iterate over the keys and values of a dictionary.
Think of a dictionary as a real dictionary book that
stores a giant alphabetical list of words and their definitions.
Similarly, a Python dictionary stores data objects as key value pairs.
In this case, we are defining a data object called person
with three values: Name, age, and city.
The name has a string value, age,
an integer value, and city, a string value.
These key value pairs have a key,
the first part, and a value, the second part,
separated by a colon with the key representing an identifier,
and the value representing the corresponding data,
which can be of any data type,
such as a string or an integer.
Let's see how we can work with these key value pairs of a dictionary with a for loop.
To do this, we'll define our person object like this.
So we'll use squiggly brackets like this,
and you'll see name set to Alice,
age is 25,
and City as New York.
We can also write this a little bit more cleanly to see,
and this is something that I will usually do,
where I'll put each item on a new line so you can clearly see
which items are the key value pairs of a dictionary.
Then we'll write our for loop and we'll say for key value in person.items,
because there's multiple items in person.
Do a colon, and we'll say print,
and we'll do another f string,
and we'll say key, colon, value.
Then we'll close that out with the double quotes,
and then we'll close that out with our parenthese.
This should output each key value pair in the dictionary.
Can you guess what the output is going to look like when we execute the cell?
Let's find out what it'll print.
Here we see name is Alice,
age is 25, and City is New York,
exactly as we defined it in the dictionary.
As you can see, for loops allow you to easily
iterate over the keys and values in a dictionary,
making it a powerful tool for working with structured data like this.