When working with four loops,
it's important to be aware of the common pitfalls
that can cause unexpected behavior in your code.
Let's look at three key issues when it comes to writing our loops and Python.
The first one, one by one errors
occur when the loop iterates one too many times or too few.
This often happens due to a misconfigured loop condition.
Always ensure that your loops, range,
or condition matches the number of iterations you expect,
meaning the number of times you expect your code to run.
Next step is with editing loop variables.
Modifying the loop variable within the loop can lead to unexpected behavior.
This makes the code harder to understand and
may cause the loop to behave in unintended ways.
It's best to avoid altering the loop variable directly inside the loop,
but rather edit it outside of the loop,
and then just have your loop run the code as expected.
Finally, let's talk about mutable sequences.
When iterating over mutable sequences like lists,
be very cautious if you're modifying the sequence directly during the iteration.
Doing so can result in skipped items as
the loop might not account for changes made to the sequence.
A good practice is to iterate over a copy of the sequence instead.
This might seem like a lot to grasp at first, but don't worry.
We're going to go through some examples together.
In this demo, I'm going to show you an example of a four loop that runs one,
too many or one,
too few times due to a misconfigured loop condition.
This is going to show us how one by one errors occur,
and we can see how to set up our loops correctly.
Let's say that we want to execute our code exactly five times. How we do that?
Something that we might want to do is we could say four,
in range one, two, six.
And then we want to print I.
So if we were to run this, we'll see this.
1,2,3,4,5 as we wanted to execute our code five times.
So this is five iterations.
However, if we make a slight change to the max number and change
it from six to five like this,
We'll only see four items.
In the correct example,
the loop runs five times as intended,
but in the incorrect example,
the loop only runs four times.
It's really important to be aware of which changes in
your code could lead to errors or incomplete operations when writing four loops.
So be on the lookout for this.
In this next demo, we'll see when working with four loops,
modifying the loop variable inside the loop can lead to unexpected behavior.
Let's see an example to understand why this is problematic,
and how to correct it.
So we're going to use the range function in another four loop,
and we're going to say four i in range (5): and we're going to create an incrementor,
so we'll say, i+ = 1,
and then print i.
So this line right here does not affect the loop's iterations.
And in this incorrect example,
the loop variable is being incremented within the loop body.
Although this doesn't affect the number of iterations,
it can cause confusion and make the loop's behavior harder to predict.
Loop will still increment five times as defined by our range function here,
which we'll get to soon,
but the printed values are not what you might expect.
Let's see. Instead of printing zero to four,
it prints one to five,
for example, let's fix this.
What we'll do is that instead of using this incrementor,
we can simply just remove that.
And then we can say for i in range (5): print (i).
And this way, we get our iterations 0-2 up until five.
In this correct example, the loop variable I is
controlled entirely by the range five function,
which has no interference of using a counter on the
incremental i variable because that is what the range function is doing.
This ensures that the loop iterates naturally 0-4,
which we see here, which is the expected behavior.
By keeping the loop variable consistent,
the code remains clear,
predictable, and easy to understand.
In our final demo, let's see why we must be cautious when iterating
over mutable sequences like lists and modifying them within the loop.
Mutable sequences are data structures that can be changed after they are created,
meaning you can add, remove,
or change items within them.
This mutability can lead to unexpected results when modifying the sequence inside a loop.
Let's see an example that will not remove all items as we might expect it to. To start?
We'll create a list called items.
We'll use square brackets and we'll have one,
two, three, four, and five.
Then we'll write a four loop to iterate over these items and we'll say for item in items
: and we'll say items.remove(item).
And then we'll go ahead and print the items.
What do you expect the output of this to be?
Let's execute the code and find out.
Here, we see the output is [ 2,
4 ] in a list.
Was that what you expected?
When you remove an item from the list while iterating over it,
the loop skips the next item actually.
This unexpected behavior occurs because the list is being modified during its iteration,
causing the loop to skip items.
Let's give a step by step explanation of what is
going on in our code here so we can see what really is going on.
The loop starts out with the first item.
And removes it. The list now becomes 2,3,4,5.
The loop then moves to the next item three,
skipping two because it's now in the place of the removed item, and then removes it.
The list now becomes two, four and five.
The loop then moves to the fifth item skipping four and removes it.
The list now becomes two and four and stops.
Instead, it would be recommended to try a different approach
to avoid modifying the list while iterating over it,
such as iterating over a copy of the list.
Let's try another approach.
Here, we'll redeclare our items list like this,
and then we'll write another four loop.
So we'll say four item in items.
And we're going to use a special syntax,
which we'll talk about in a second,
where we'll put a square bracket and a colon and then close out the square bracket,
add another colon, and then we'll say items, remove item.
Then we'll print items at the end.
Notice this colon inside of square brackets.
This is Fancy shorthand for creating a copy of the entire list,
ensuring that the original list can be modified safely during iteration.
Once we create a copy,
we can then append all of the items in a remove action over each item in the items list.
Once our code is run,
we have removed all of the numbers in the items list,
1,2,3,4,5 and we do not see any numbers remaining like we did in the previous code.
Let's run the cell and see if that is actually the output that we would expect.
And we see exactly that.
So now there's no more items inside of the items list.
Hopefully, this is an insightful review of some pitfalls.
We can and will face win working with four loops in our Python code.
As we'll see, moving from this code to this code.
Great job getting through this and keep practicing by using
four loops and seeing what opportunities you have to work with in your Pythonic tool kit.
Four loops are yet another powerful type of loop we can now
add to our toolbox for iterating over sequences of items.
They are versatile, and they can be used with
various data structures such as lists, strings, and dictionaries.
By understanding how to use four loops effectively and avoiding common pitfalls,
you can handle a wide variety of programming scenarios.
Great job getting through this section on Four loops,
and I'm looking forward to seeing you in the next video.