Keeping in line with our new for loop skills,
we can upgrade our iterator to use
the range function to generate a sequence of numbers to iterate on?
The range function is a very powerful tool that Python provides
for us that simplifies the process of creating sequences of numbers,
and it can be used in various scenarios as well.
Let's start with a quick example of the range function in action to see how it works.
We'll write a for loop,
and we'll say for i in range (5): print (i).
In this example above, can you tell what it's doing?
This for loop will print the value of the incrementer for a range of five.
There'll be five numbers printed,
starting from index 0 to
Position 5, 0,1,2,3,4.
Overall, this loop will print numbers 0-4 due to the range of five.
The range function in Python is incredibly
versatile and is frequently used in a variety of scenarios,
as you'll see when we write our Python code in this course,
and in your own Python adventures to come.
Here, we'll explore for common ways to use range,
whether you're iterating over a sequence of numbers,
generating indexes for lists,
creating sequences with specific start and end points,
or utilizing the step argument to skip numbers.
Range is your go to tool for controlled iteration in Python.
Let's delve into some of these use cases with some demos.
In this demo, we'll explore how the range function
allows us to iterate over a specific sequence of numbers.
For instance, using a range of 10 generates numbers 0-9,
enabling us to run a loop exactly 10 times.
Let's see this in action.
We'll define our for loop as for i in range (10):,
and then we'll write print,
and we'll write an f string,
and we'll say iteration,
and put in squiggly brackets.
The letter i will close out that f string,
and then we'll close out the print statement.
Can you guess what this loop will be doing?
This loop is going to run 10 times and print the current iteration number each time.
Let's see how that works. We execute the cell.
We see 0,1,2,3,4,5,6,7,8,9.
The range 10 function ensures the loop iterates from 0-9,
making it perfect for situations where the number of iterations is known, like in this.
In this next demo, we'll see how the range function is useful
for generating indexes when working with lists.
When you need to iterate over the indexes of a list,
the range function comes in very handy.
Remember, a list is just a collection of items or things.
List can also be referred to as arrays,
which are simply lists of items and brackets grouped together.
Arrays are very important concepts in
programming and are used in many different contexts.
For example, an array of numbers,
such as in square brackets, 1,2,3,4,5.
Like this, an array of strings,
for example, hello world, like this,
or even an array of arrays, something like this,
which has square brackets around it,
and then groups of square brackets,
such as 1 and 2,
3 and 4, and 5 and 6.
Let's see this in action combining our knowledge of for loops indices and lists.
Going to define a list of fruits,
which will be a list of strings.
The list of fruits consists of apple, banana, and cherry.
Then we're going to write a for loop to iterate over all of these items.
We'll say for I in range because we can write anything we want for the incremental,
and we're just going to say i.
For each item in range,
and we're going to do a len fruits,
which we'll discuss in a second.
We'll do colon, and then we'll say print.
We'll do another f string,
and we'll say index,
do squiggly brackets over the i,
and we'll say contains,
and then in squiggly brackets fruits with an i,
and then in square brackets around that,
close out the squiggly bracket,
close out the double quotation,
and then close out the parenthesis.
Can you guess what this does?
This uses our fancy range function here to generate indexes for the list fruits,
allowing you to access each element by its index.
What's that len function you ask right here?
When we write len fruits,
we are asking Python to return the number of items in the list fruits, right here.
It's a useful mechanism when you need to determine the length of the list dynamically.
When you see len,
right here, think, tell me the length of the items in this group.
By using range len fruits.
We can access each element in list by its index,
making it easy to manipulate or retrieve specific items.
What does it mean when we can access each element by its index?
It means that you can retrieve each item in the list using its position number,
making it easy to refer to specific elements directly within the loop.
For example, fruits, zero,
which means fruits index 0 gets apple.
Fruits index 1 or fruits 1 gets banana.
Fruits 2 gets cherry.
When we are basically writing this,
we're saying fruits 0,
then fruit 1,
then fruit 2, 0,1,2,
and then there isn't a fruits 3 index.
This will go on for however many items are in the list of fruits,
and for us, there's only three items.
In many cases, it's often more readable and
simpler to iterate directly over the items in the list,
especially when you do not need the index.
But let's iterate over this and see what we're talking about.
When we run this, we'll see index of zero contains apple.
Index one contains banana,
Index 2 contains cherry.
That's how we count starting with index 0 up to Index 2 for all three of these items.
However, in many cases,
it's often more readable and simpler
to simply iterate directly over the items in the list,
especially when you don't need the index.
Instead of writing for i in range,
which we do here, you can write for fruit in fruits.
Personally, human readable code is more helpful,
especially when working with other engineers who might not
immediately understand why you wrote a for loop in a specific way.
Let's see an example. Instead of this code,
we could simply write for fruit in fruits,
and then colon print fruit.
This approach avoids the need to use the index and directly access
each item in the list with human readable code rather than using the variable i.
Just know that it's important to understand both implementations.
Since we've already declared fruits above,
we can write this for loop and also see.
We get all the same items as well,
so apple, banana, and cherry.
Now in this next demo, let's look at how we can use
the range function to create sequences with specific start and end points.
This is particularly useful when you need to
iterate over a range that doesn't start at zero.
You can specify a start and end point for
the range function so that there is
a specific point in which each function will execute and stop.
Let's see an example of this.
We'll write a for loop and we'll say for i
range (2,7): we'll say print(i).
In this example, we specify that we want the range to start at two and end at seven.
This means that our for loop will print numbers 2-6,
which is one less than the end point specified.
This allows you to control
both the starting and stopping points of your loop making the code more flexible.
Let's see what happens when we execute this code.
When we run this code, we'll see 2,3,4,5,6,
and then once it gets to seven, it will stop.
That's why it only prints these numbers here.
Finally, the range function allows us to introduce a step argument,
which specifies the increment between numbers.
This is useful when you need to skip numbers in your sequence.
Think of this like a skipper that allows you to
pass over numbers in the range with a pattern.
For example, we want to iterate over every second number or every other number.
How would we do that? Let's see how to do that.
First, we'll define a for loop and we'll say for i in range and we'll
put 0,10,2: then we'll print (i) to print out each item.
Can you guess what's happening here?
This is going to print every second number from zero,
the start to 10,
the stop with two being
this skipper element that we define for our range function like this.
When we execute the code, we'll see this.
See 0,2,4,6,8, and then once it gets to 10,
it stops and doesn't execute beyond that.
That's why we see these numbers here.
We're telling Python to count
every other number by setting the step argument here to two.
To break it down, 0 is our start number.
It's an optional parameter we can pass in and defaults to 0, if not specified.
The 10 is the end number, not optional,
and the loop runs up to,
but does not include this number,
which is why we always have to pass in a number into range.
Then 2 is the step number,
which is also optional and defaults to one, if not specified.
If the step argument was set to 3,
instead of 2, Python will count every third number.
Let's take a look at this example.
If we were to copy this code, paste it in here,
and then change 2 to 3,
this will now output something a little different from what we saw earlier.
By counting by three, we now see four numbers instead of five,
like we saw earlier here.