While the range function is powerful,
there are situations where it might not be the best tool for the job.
Let's explore three common scenarios where using range might not be ideal.
First, when working with large ranges,
range can consume significant memory and slow down your program.
Second, range only works with integers.
If you're dealing with floating point numbers or other types,
a different approach is needed.
Third, when your loop needs to run based on
a condition rather than a fixed number of iterations,
a loop might be more appropriate here.
Let's dive into each of these scenarios with Python demos,
so we can see this firsthand.
In this first demo, we'll see how using range with
a very large number can be resource intensive and why,
there are certain situations where we shouldn't use the range function.
The code generates a sequence of one million numbers,
which can consume a lot of memory and slow down your Python program
when you put in a range that's very high like this.
So we'll write for I in range.
And we'll put in a very big number.
That has, that's one, and then one,
two, three, four, five, six zeros.
We're then going to have this print and F string,
and we're going to say index squiggly brackets I.
This is resource intensive. We'll close that out.
When we run this, It's going to say that the data rate has been exceeded,
and that basically the Jupiter notebook will
temporarily stop sending output to the client to avoid crashing it.
We are trying to basically send a whole bunch of data outputs from this,
and this is going to be counting up to a very big number.
This would be very resource intensive,
and it won't allow us to execute this code,
or it will run, and then it would crash the Jupiter notebook.
This is a stop gap to prevent that from happening.
In such cases, consider using more efficient data structures or algorithms.
While range is convenient,
it's not always efficient for large sequences like we just saw.
In such cases, consider using more efficient data structures or
algorithms such as generators to manage memory and performance better.
Generators, which you'll learn more about a little later allow you to handle
large sequences more efficiently by
generating items on the fly rather than storing them all in memory.
Did you notice a new kind of print statement above as well?
It's not specific to print, actually,
but it's a way that we can format a string with data inside of it.
This is an example of what we can call an F string in Python right here.
F strings or formatted string literals are a way to insert expressions, data,
or other types of inputs inside of a regular string,
called a string literal,
using curly braces or curly brackets like you'll see here.
The letter F before the quotation marks indicates that the string is an F string.
Here, I in quickly brackets is
replaced with the current value of I in each iteration of the loop,
coming from here, resulting in a formatted string that includes the index.
F strings are a powerful feature in Python because they allow you to create
strings that include the values of variables and expressions easily.
This makes your code more readable and concise
compared to traditional string formatting methods.
For example, if you wanted to write an expression that greets somebody,
you'll probably need an F string to write F,
and then quotation marks,
Hello there, user name, like this.
Something like this. And we can do exactly this with F strings in our Python code.
In this next demo, let's explore why the range function
isn't suitable for non integer sequences like floating point numbers.
We'll attempt to use the range function to generate a sequence of floating point numbers.
If you need to iterate over a sequence of floating point numbers or other types,
you'll need a different approach.
Let's write some code and see why this is correct.
We'll write our four loop like this.
We'll say four, I in range.
And then we'll put in a start of 0.0,
and end of 1.0,
and a stepper of 0.1.
Then we'll say print,
and we'll write an F string,
and we'll say in correct use of range for floating point numbers.
We'll close that out. Let's try running this code and seeing what happens.
But before we run that,
what do you think the output will be?
When we run this, we'll get a type error that says,
float, object cannot be interpreted as an integer.
Did you get an error as well?
We see type error float object cannot be interpreted as an integer,
which is because the range function only works with integers.
If you try to use it with floating point numbers,
Python will raise a type error because range expects integer arguments.
But we're passing in floating point arguments.
Instead of doing this, we can use a i loop
instead or a different method to handle non integer sequences.
Let's see what this looks like in the correct approach
using L loop to iterate over floating point numbers.
Let's get rid of that type error so we can iterate over our floating point numbers.
Instead of a four loop,
we'll write a y loop.
We will do this by first creating a variable called start,
and we'll set that equal to 0.0.
We'll then create an end variable and we'll set that equal to 1.0,
and we'll create our steper,
defined as a step variable,
and we'll say 0.1.
We'll then say that current equals start.
We'll set this variable equal to our start variable, which is 0.0.
Next up, we'll write our while loop,
and we'll say while current is less than end,
and then we will print an f string, and we'll say,
correct use a while loop for floating point numbers."
Then we'll use curly braces and we'll say current like this,
and then we will close out our print statement.
Then, we'll say current, plus equals step.
When this runs, this works correctly,
because we have, first of all,
initialized the start, the end and the step values and used them in our while loop.
We've also used a while loop to iterate over
that start value to just before the end value like this,
incrementing by the step value each time, like this.
Ultimately, we correctly handle floating point numbers without causing an error.
Let's run this, and we'll see here,
that this counts up until the point where we need it to end,
which is right before one.
Now, remember the issues we had with floating point errors that we talked about before.
How would we fix our code to solve for this? That's right.
We'll bring back our trustee format specification tool
:.1f to format the floating point numbers with
one decimal and avoid the precision issues we just saw here.
First of all, we'll copy this code.
We paste it right down here in a new cell,
and then what we'll do is that we will keep our variables like this.
But, in our print statement,
we're going to change the current variable here.
What we'll do is, inside of the curly brackets,
we're going to say:.1f,
and this comes after current,
all within the curly brackets and we keep everything the same.
Can you guess what we're going to see when we run this different code now?
When we execute this code,
we see 0.0,
0.1, 0.2, 0.3, 0.4,
0.5, 0.6, 0.7 0.8,
0.9 all the way up to 1.0,
which is exactly what we'd expect.
Finally, in our last demo,
let's explore why the range function isn't always the best choice,
especially when dealing with loops that should run based
on a condition rather than a fixed number of iterations.
Let's see an example of using the range function incorrectly
for a loop that needs to run until a certain condition is met.
To illustrate this, we'll say for i in range five,
colon, and we'll say if i is less than three, print i.
In this incorrect example,
we're attempting to use the range function to control the loop,
but then we've added a conditional check inside of the loop right here.
This causes unnecessary iterations as the loop will run for all values from 0-4,
even though we only care about the first three iterations.
This is inefficient and can lead to unnecessary processing.
Can you guess what the output will be? Let's find out.
Even though we've declared this range,
we're then specifying for i to only be printed if it's less than four.
If we want to use the range function in an accounting mechanism,
we can do something like this.
We'll say for i in range three print i.
Can you guess what this will output when we run it?
We'll see 0,
1, 2, printed,
Meaning it went through the first three iterations as we would expect.
If you said this, great job.
Now, let's see another correct approach using a while loop.
The while loop is better suited for scenarios where the loop should run
based on a condition rather than a fixed number of iterations.
We'll declare a variable called count and we'll say count equals zero,
we'll then say while count is less than 5:
print (count) and then we're going to increment count by one.
In this correct example,
the while loop runs only as long as the condition of count being less than five is true.
This ensures that the loop stops as soon as the condition is no longer met,
making the code more efficient and easier to understand.
Let's run it and see exactly why this will work.
When we execute this,
we'll see 0, 1,
2, 3, 4,
exactly as we would expect.
The while loop gives us better control over
loops that are dependent on changing conditions.
As we wrap up our deep dive into this new range function.
let's look back on what we just learned.
We got to see that the range function is
a powerful tool for iterating over sequences of numbers,
whether you're counting iterations, generating indexes,
or creating custom sequences with specific start and stop points.
However, it's essential to consider efficiency when working with large ranges.
Generators might be a better choice in such cases.
Also, remember that range is limited to integers.
For non-integer sequences, a while loop will serve you better.
Finally, when dealing with condition-based loops,
while loops offer the flexibility you need.
Feel free to check out the resources below if you'd like to dive
deeper into these edge cases with the range function.
Understanding when and how to use range effectively,
will significantly enhance your coding efficiency
and adaptability in various programming scenarios.
Keep practicing, and you'll be a pro with using these functions in no time.