Before we explore different types of iterations in this section,
it's important to first think about and
understand the role of the pass function in Python.
Pass is a unique statement that essentially does nothing.
Think of it like a box of error that occupies space.
That being said, it's a powerful tool when you're writing Python code.
It serves as a placeholder allowing you to
define blocks of code that you plan to implement later on.
By using pass, you can avoid
syntax errors that occur when Python expects a block of code,
but you're not ready to write it just yet.
Frequently, pass is used in loops, functions, classes,
and conditional statements, when you want to outline the structure of
your code without filling in all of the details immediately.
This is especially useful in incremental development,
where you may want to keep certain parts of
your code empty while you work on other sections.
In summary, Pass is a simple,
yet effective way to maintain the flow of your code
and prevent errors as you build out your functions and scripts.