Let's take a look at how the pass instruction can
be used in a function alongside other logic.
In our process numbers function,
we'll be writing a for loop that iterates over a range of numbers from 0-4.
We'll first define our function.
We'll write def process_numbers.
Then what we'll do, is we'll put a colon and then we'll say for i in range(5): if
i = 3: we'll say pass else colon,
we'll say print, and we'll write an F string,
and we'll say processing number.
We'll do curly brackets,
end quotes and then end parentheses.
Then at the end, we'll run our function with process numbers.
As this loop runs, it will check if the value of i=3.
If it does, instead of performing any action,
we use the pass statement.
This is a placeholder where we can insert additional logic later,
but here it will do nothing when this condition is true.
For all other values of i before and after three,
the function will print out a message
indicating the number has been processed right here.
What do you think will happen here when we execute this cell?
We'll see processing number 0,
1, 2, and 4.
By running the function, we can see how the loop
behaves with and without the past instruction.
This approach is particularly useful when you're developing code incrementally,
allowing you to structure your functions and
loops while leaving space for future enhancements.
As we see here, where it will skip over number
three and proceed to the last number four given a range of five.