We can add other conditional logic to our loops for other intermediary statements.
Let's take a look at how to upgrade our four loops to include an else clause,
which will execute a condition once the loop completes.
Let's take our range function and add
an else statement to it so that once a range of five is reached,
we'll print the loop as it's finished.
We'll do that by writing a four loop with four I in range five.
We'll do colon, and we'll say print I.
Else. We'll say print, loop, just finished.
Do you see what's happening now?
Once the number four,
which is position five is reached,
the condition will be met and the value will no longer be true but false.
Thus the else clause will be invoked.
Can you guess what's going to happen when we execute this cell? Let's find out.
We'll see the numbers zero, one, two, three,
four, printed out,
and then the final statement,
Luke finished is printed at the end,
because we've iterated through all of the numbers in range five,
and then we invoke our else statement.
If you said this, great job.
When would we use else in loops?
The first is confirmation when the loop completed.
The else clause is useful when you need to confirm that
the loop has run through all iterations before being interrupted by a break statement.
This can be particularly helpful in search algorithms or when processing collections.
Second up is searching for an item in a list.
Imagine you're searching for an item in a list.
If the item is found, you break the loop.
If the item is not found after all iterations,
you can use the else clause to handle this scenario.
In this example here,
if the search item is found,
the loop breaks, and the else clause is not executed.
If the search item is not found,
the else clause is executed,
indicating the item was not found in the list.
As we see here, grape fruit is not found in this list.
The else clause is executed here.
Third, we can validate input data with else.
When validating input data or confirming if something is true or not,
you might loop through a set of conditions logic and use
the else clause to confirm that all conditions are met without any issues.
In this case here,
if a negative number is found,
the loop breaks, and the else clause is not executed.
If all numbers are positive,
the else clause confirms this,
as we see here with the else clause being
executed as all numbers are positive and greater than zero.
Last up, we can combine else with while loops.
The else clause is not limited to four loops.
It can also be used with while loops.
This can be useful for scenarios where you want to
ensure that a condition was met throughout the entire loop,
such as counting up to the limit and then
printing a message at the end as while completes.
While we add this powerful clause else to our Pythonic toolkit,
there are some things to note about how it works that are worth
going over so that you don't make these mistakes when you write your loops in logic.
Number one, else is not an alternative to I.
It's important to note that the else clause in
loops is not an alternative to using if statements.
It serves as a different purpose by providing a way to execute code after
the loop finishes provided it wasn't terminated prematurely by a break. Number two.
Else clause executes after normal loop termination.
The else clause only executes if the loop completes all iterations normally.
If the loop is terminated by a break statement,
the else clause will not be executed.
With these two helpful strategies in mind,
you'll be ready to tackle adding else to your loops.