Now that we understand loops,
let's take a look at something slightly more complex.
Python allows us to add loops within loops. Can you imagine that?
This is called nesting loops or nested loops,
and it works a bit like this.
Let's break down what's happening in our loop.
We have our array, we have our variable,
and we have our loop and I is starting with one and goes up to two.
Now that we understand what's happening in a loop in practice,
let's pop open our Jupiter notebook and see the interaction.
Let's talk about nested loops.
To see this more visually,
let's start with a simple loop that iterates over a range of
numbers to get us started thinking about how loops can be nested.
We'll say four i in range,
and we'll start with one, and go up to five.
Clon then we'll say print,
we'll do an F string, and we'll say iteration.
Put I in curly brackets,
we'll close out the F string, and then we'll close out the print statement.
When we run this, this will print the below when we run it.
And we know this because we start with a range of
one and go up to four because we specify the end being five.
So our loop will print four numbers and stop at five,
since there are four numbers or positions 1-5.
That's why we see one, two, three, and four.
Now, let's add a second loop inside of the first loop.
This inner loop will iterate over a list of fruits.
So we will create a list with square brackets,
and we'll have apple,
banana, cherry, and grape fruit.
Then we'll copy our four loop from earlier,
and we'll control V and paste that into here.
And what we'll say is, we'll say for in range
one to 54 fruit in fruit colon.
And then we'll edit this to say iteration I,
and then we'll say fruit, colon,
and then we'll put fruit in curly braces.
Can you guess what the output of this is going to be when we execute
this new four loop? Let's find out.
When we execute the cell,
we'll see this output below.
So we'll see iteration one,
fruit, this, fruit, this,
then iteration two, this fruit,
this fruit, d fruit, d fruit, iteration three,
fruit fruit fruit, fruit fruit,
and then same thing with iteration four with apple banana, cherry, and grape fruit.
Wait. Why are there so many more outputs when we add a loop inside of it?
Wouldn't it be more constrained? Not exactly.
Let's dive into why this is happening.
First, the outer loop here runs 1-4.
This has four cycles.
For each value of i,
the inner loop then runs through each fruit in the fruits list,
and this has four cycles.
This means that for each iteration of the outer loop,
the inner loop completes its inner cycle as well,
which is why it creates so many more iterations.
So when i is one,
the inner loop runs four times for each fruit in the list.
Then when I is two,
the inner loop runs again four more times and so on.
And this is the construction of nested loops.
To sum this up, in the above example,
we are using range to iterate over a sequence of numbers.
And for each number, we are iterating over a list of fruits.
This demonstrates how you can combine range with
nested loops to handle more complex iteration scenarios,
such as searching for combinations or pairing items.