In order to control our loops, start and stop,
we can implement break and continue clauses to curb how they operate.
This becomes incredibly important for preventing our functions from running forever,
eating up resources, budget, and our time.
Let's see these two clauses break and continue in action in the next sections.
Let's start by first taking a look at break.
If we want to end our looping logic early or under a certain condition,
we can use a brake statement to do this efficiently.
The break statement terminates our loop when a specified condition is met,
preventing the loop from continuing to execute.
Let's look at an example using the break statement.
We'll write a four loop and we'll say for in range, colon.
If I equals five,
we'll say break. Otherwise, we'll print.
So in this example, when I equals five,
the loop will break and stop execution.
Can you guess what the output will be when we run the cell?
The output will be zero, one, two, three,
and four and when I is five,
that means it will break and stop, like it just did.
If you guess this. Great work.
We want and need to close loops efficiently to prevent them from running indefinitely,
which could lead to endless loops.
Endless loops occur when the loops terminating condition is never met,
causing the program to run forever and potentially crash or become unresponsive.
Remember our example of the heating system for the house.
If there's no way for the house to know when to stop heating the house,
it will heat the house indefinitely,
melting everything and you inside of it.
Again, not ideal. Thanks to brakes,
we can tell a function to stop executing when a certain condition is met.
Let's look at an example of an endless loop using Python and how we can close our loops.
An endless loop will look something like this,
where the count will start at zero and just count upwards indefinitely.
So let's use an example of this.
We'll say count equals zero and then we'll say le, true, print.
This loop will run forever and ever and ever.
Then we'll say count plus equals one.
So, you don't need to run this.
This will actually crash your Jupiter notebook.
So what we won't want to do is run something like this,
but I'll run it just for example purposes.
And what this will end up happening is that it will just
start executing all of these outputs,
and it'll keep running indefinitely,
and then your data rate will be exceeded,
and then the Jupiter notebook will basically temporarily stop,
and what we'll need to do is we'll need to stop this.
But we'll see here that this ran an infinite number of times
and we'll just fill up your entire Jupiter notebook with all of these iterations.
We'll do is that we will clear outputs of all cells.
And to fix this, by adding a break statement,
the break clause will ensure that the loop will
terminate after 10 iterations like we'll define.
Without a break statement,
the loop will run endlessly, like we just saw,
because the condition while true will always be true.
So to fix this endless loop or infinite loop issue,
what we'll do is that we'll say while true will print,
this loop will run forever.
But it won't run forever because we're going to stop it.
Then what we're going to do is that we're going to say count plus equals one,
and then we're going to say if count is greater than ten, break.
Can you guess what will happen now when we execute this code?
This would actually run indefinitely,
but because we say count greater than ten, if this is true,
then we break and we stop this while loop from running,
which is why we get one, two,
three, four, five, six, seven,
eight, nine, 10, 11 breaks.
And then once this finishes,
because count is zero,
it's actually zero, one, two,
three, four, five, six,
seven, eight, nine, 10.
So again, we start at index zero,
and then we count upwards to 10.
But as soon as 10 is reached, then it stops.