If we want to skip a current iteration and go to the next case,
we can use the continuous statement.
The continuous statement skips the rest of the code inside
the loop for the current iteration and moves to the next iteration.
Let's look at an example of the continuous statement in Python.
We'll first start with writing a four loop,
and we'll say four in range ten.
Then we'll say I, I will use the percent sine,
and then we'll say the number two equals equals zero.
Colon continue.
Then we'll add a print statement below that if and that same indentation.
In this example, we implement skipping logic for the loop,
skipping even numbers with this.
If you remember our use of the percent sign from earlier,
this is using the Modulo operator,
which returns the remainder of the division operation.
I medulo operator two equals equals zero,
checks if the number is divisible by two,
meaning, is it an even number?
Yes or no. What do you expect the output to be when this cell runs? Let's check it out.
The output will be one, three,
five, seven, and nine.
Let's review what's happening here.
First, we set up the four loop to iterate over the range of zero to nine,
defined by range ten.
Next, we use the medulo sign,
the percent sign, which is the medulo operator,
and this returns the remainder of the division.
The expression percent sine two equals equals zero,
then we'll check if the number is divisible by two.
If the remainder is zero, the number is even.
With our continued statement,
if i is even,
the continuous statement is executed.
The continued statement skips the rest of the code inside of
the loop for the current iteration and moves to the next iteration.
Ultimately, if it's odd,
the print statement is executed,
printing the value of i.
When I is these even numbers 0246 or eight.
The continuous statement is executed,
and the print I statement is skipped,
so that number is not printed in the console.
And when I is these numbers, 1, 3, 5,
7 or 9, the print I statement is executed,
and the value of I is printed and we'll see the number.
This example should illustrate how to implement skipping logic in the loop,
using the continuous statement to skip even numbers.
The output is all the odd numbers 0-9,
demonstrating how the continuous statement can be used
to skip certain iterations based on a condition.
Are you surprised that we were able to add two words,
which we call strings together like this?
Remember, the add numbers together is just the name we put for this function,
but it doesn't lock it into a specific action.
This function takes in two arguments, inputs,
and then returns the first argument plus the second argument.
They do not need to be numbers necessarily as we saw. Pretty neat.