Even though Python is a computer programming language,
did you know that it can also make decisions?
It's not so different from how you or I make decisions in our day to day lives.
If it's rainy outside, wear a raincoat.
So long as it's Monday to Friday, work.
Or when it's Saturday or Sunday, rest and recharge.
We make tons of decisions every single day,
35,000 per day, in fact,
according to Harvard Business Review.
The way we make decisions is similar to Python in using conditions.
Python calls these conditional statements,
which you can think of as fact based observations of the world.
The if statement is the most basic form of a conditional statement.
Let's start with an example where we want to print the response to the input of age.
In this function, we want to check if the provided age
is greater than or equal to a certain integer.
In this example, if the age is 18 or older,
our Python program will print that you are eligible to vote.
Otherwise, it prints that you are not eligible to vote.
This way, we don't need to write
two separate functions and then run each of them at the same time.
We write this if statement,
and then use a conditional statement while
leveraging Python's built in logic and reasoning.
When we think about conditional statements,
let's see this in another example.
This time, with a scoring system for exams.
It would be so draining of our time if we needed to run
four different functions to check if a score is 0-69 as an F,
70-79 as a C,
80-89 as a B,
and 90-100 as an A.
Doing this per student would be exhausting.
Fortunately, for us, we can add more conditions using
elif and else to check other conditional cases.
It's much easier to see this as a visual. So check this out.
We'll first define a variable called score,
and this will be the score of a given student,
which will set as 85.
If this score is greater than or equal to 90,
we'll say print. Grade is A.
Then elif, score is greater than or equal to 80.
We'll say print, grade B.
We'll do another elif statement,
and we'll say elif score greater than or equal to 70,
and then say print,
Grade C. Then else,
so all other cases that aren't these.
Say print, Grade F. The first check is if the score is greater than or equal to 90.
Then the next band is if it's greater than or equal to 80 after 90 and so on,
to classify the grade as being between these scoring bands.
We don't need to write the same function for different times.
All we have to do is this,
if, elif, else statement.
Let's run this to see what happens.
So when the score is 85, the grade is B.
Then let's say if we change this to be 75.
We see that the grade is C. If we made this 99, grade A.
Of course, if we got score of 50, we get this.
If we even do 90,
we get grade A. Pretty neat.
In the next section, we'll learn how to expand
upon this conditional logic with some other cases.
Now that we've introduced the basic concepts of conditional statements,
let's break them down further into three main types of conditional statements.
If else, if elif and if elif else.
Understanding these will be essential as we progress into
more complex conditional logic that we can use in our Python code.
The if-else statement is the most straightforward conditional structure.
It checks a single condition, and if it's true,
it executes one block of code, the true case.
If the condition is false,
it jumps to the else block and executes that instead.
In this example, if the score is 70 or higher,
the message, you passed the exam is printed.
Otherwise, the exam prints,
sorry, you didn't pass.
This allows us to handle two mutually exclusive outcomes efficiently,
where one is either true or if it's not true, it's automatically false.
In this grading example,
the conditions are similar,
but now we've added a default response grade F,
where if the score doesn't meet any of the previous criteria,
then a grade F is presented.
This ensures that all possible cases are
handled before sending the final default response back.
Next up, we have the if-elif structure.
This is very useful when you need to check multiple conditions.
Python evaluates each condition in sequence and
executes the block of the first condition that is true.
Here, we're grading an exam.
If the score is 90 or higher, the student gets an A.
If it's 80-89, the student gets a B.
Notice how the code stops checking once a true condition is found.
This is the power of Python's conditional logic in using
our relational operators to create these assessment bands.
Finally, we have the if-elif-else structure.
This is a more comprehensive conditional statement where we check multiple conditions,
and if none of them are true,
a default action defined by the else block is executed.
In this grading example,
the conditions are similar,
but now we've added a default response, grade F,
where if the score didn't meet any of the previous criteria,
then a grade F is presented.
This ensures that all possible cases are handled
before setting the final default response back.