Before finishing out this lesson,
it's important to review a few key concepts
starting with the practical use of break in continuous statements.
First, we can search for an item.
The break statement can be used to exit a loop once a specific item is found.
In this example here, we have a collection of fruits in a list or in a right.
And the item we want to search for is cherry.
When we go through the list of fruits,
we want to stop when Python finds our desired fruit search item cherry in fruits.
This will output the below when cherry is found,
and then stop the function. Found cherry.
Second, we can use break and continue to filter items.
The continued statement can be used to skip over
certain items based on a condition set in your code.
Let's say that we're looking to go through a series of numbers in a range,
and we want to only output the odd numbers,
skipping the even ones. How would we even do that?
This will be our output. Next up,
nested loops with break and continue.
We can use break and continue clauses in our nested loops to control the flow of
execution and impact how Python processes our requested inputs.
In this example, for a range of three,
we have a nested loop inside of i called j,
and then we use continue and break to affect what ends up getting printed like so.
This will be our output. When adding these tools to your Python toolbox,
there are some areas to keep in mind.
Number 1, unintentional infinite loops.
Be careful with conditions and ensure that
brake statements are correctly placed to avoid infinite loops.
Number 2, skipping critical code with continue.
Ensure that us and continue does not skip
necessary operations or cause logical errors in your code.
By understanding and effectively using break and continue in your Python code,
you can control the flow of your loops more precisely.
This helps in optimizing your code and preventing potential issues,
such as infinite loops or logical errors.
Your team will also appreciate your diligence to detail,
especially during the pool review process when your code is
analyzed before making its way live to your end users.