For a breakdown on conditional statements,
let's first start with the 'if else' statement.
Here we're going to check if a student score is greater than or equal to 70.
You would do that like this.
We'll define a score as a variable,
and we'll say that it is 70 for example,
and we'll say if score is greater than or equal to 70.
I'll say print, you passed the exam.
Otherwise, with else, I will different print statement,
and this will say sorry, you did pass.
If this condition is true,
the program prints, you pass the exam.
Otherwise, it prints, sorry, you didn't pass.
This simple if else structure allows us to
handle two possible outcomes based on the condition.
If we run this, we'll see you passed the exam because it is 70,
and this indicates it needs to be 70 or higher.
If we were to put 60,
we get sorry, you didn't pass because that's the other part of the statement.
Next, we have the if LF statement,
which is used to check multiple conditions.
In this example, we'll check if a score is 90 or above and print the Grade A.
If the condition isn't met,
it moves to the next LF condition,
and we're going to check if there's a score of 80 or above.
If so, then we'll print the Grade B.
Let's see what that looks like here.
We'll copy our score value from before,
and then we'll say if score is greater than or equal to 90,
then we'll print Grade A. LF score,
greater than or equal to 80.
We'll print that. Then we'll do Score B.
Now, if we were to run this,
60 isn't a part of any of these bounds.
This is only checking if this is greater than or
equal to 80 or greater than or equal to 90.
Even if we do 70,
still won't pass up until we do 80,
and then we see Grade B,
85, 95 or higher, even 100.
We see that. The program stops checking conditions as soon as it finds one that's true,
making this structure efficient for scenarios with multiple conditions,
like here where we're checking the score to give a grade.
Finally, let's look at the if LF else structure,
which adds an else block to catch all remaining cases.
We'll take our code block here and we'll recopy that here,
and then we'll keep the if scores greater than 90 for grade A.
We do LF score greater than 80 for a Grade B.
Then what we'll do is we'll say else,
print Grade F. Here,
if the score is 90 or above the program, Grades A,
if the score is between 80 and 89,
you get a print out of Grade B.
But if neither of these two conditions are met,
the else block is executed printing a grade of F.
This if LF else structure ensures that every possible case is handled,
including cases where none of the specific conditions are met where
we return and otherwise do this with the else condition and you'll see that right here.
If we run score of 100,
that gives us a grade of A.
If we do 85, we get B.
But as soon as we get to 79, we get grade F,
and that's where if we do all the way down to 30,
we still get that Grade F. But once we get back to 90 or greater, we get Grade A.