As we delve deeper into Python's control flow mechanisms,
one powerful feature we can use is the ability to
evaluate multiple conditions simultaneously.
This allows us to combine several factors within
a single if statement using logical operators like and,
or, and not, which we learned about in the previous lesson.
Think about it like you're a detective,
and you want to check multiple things at once.
Instead of needing to ask, is this true?
Is this false? Isn't this true? Isn't this false?
You can ask multiple questions at once by asking,
is this true and is this true,
or is this true or is that false?
By combining conditions, we avoid redundancy and
we can handle more complex logic with ease.
Instead of writing repetitive code blocks for each condition,
we can create a streamlined decision making process
that checks all necessary criteria at once.
This is particularly useful in scenarios where the outcome depends on multiple variables,
such as determining permissions,
evaluating settings, or considering environmental factors like the weather.
I think visuals are helpful to illustrate the logic going
on behind the scenes of the control flow mechanism in Python.
Let's diagram it out.
This is a flow chart of how multiple condition statements can be used
to help us make a decision about what we should do today based on the weather.
The first step is to check the temperature.
If the temperature is above 77 degrees Fahrenheit on the left,
we proceed to check if it's sunny.
If it is, it's a great day to head to the beach.
If not, it might be better to stay inside.
If the temperature is between 50 degrees Fahrenheit and 77 degrees Fahrenheit,
on the right, we still check if it's sunny.
In this case, if it's sunny,
it's perfect weather for a walk.
Otherwise, staying inside remains the best option.
Remember, we only need to specify greater than 50 to check this bound between 50 and 77.
As soon as it becomes 77,
we're using the condition on the left until the temperature drops to 76,
we're checking the condition on the right.
Lastly, if the temperature is 50 degrees Fahrenheit or below,
in the middle, it's too cold to go outside,
so we'll stay indoors, and as soon as it gets to 50 or below,
we're checking the condition in the middle completely automatically with python.
This decision making flow allows us to evaluate multiple conditions in a structured way,
ensuring that all possible outcomes are considered.
Now, let's write some code for a weather example with
logical operators: and, or, not.
To tighten up our code.
There are a lot of if,
if, else, elif,
ifelse and we can tighten up our code and make it more human readable, and easier to use.
Let's refactor our code a bit to really show how
multiple conditions can apply to our conditional logic even more.
We'll begin by setting the temperature to 80 degrees.
We'll write temperature equals 80 and is sunny.
We'll set that equal to true,
just like we did in the previous example.
For the first condition, we'll check if the temperature is
greater than 77 degrees and if it's sunny.
We'll write if temperature is greater than 77 and is sunny.
Then we'll print, go to the Beach.
Both conditions must be true to print, go to the beach,
denoted with it and operator that we wrote right there.
For the second condition, we should check if the temperature is
greater than 50 degrees and it's not sunny.
Then we'd say print inside as a print statement.
We'll write elif temperature is
greater than 50 and not is sunny.
We'll then print, stay inside.
The and not operator flips the Boolean value,
so we enter this block only when it's
not sunny and when the temperature is greater than 50.
When is sunny is false.
In the third condition, we want to check if the temperature is greater than 50 degrees,
and it is sunny.
If so, then our code will print, go for a walk.
This is where we want to see the combination of temperature and weather working
together using logical operators to string these conditions together.
We'll write elif temperature is greater than 50 and is sunny.
Then we'll print, go for a walk.
Finally, if none of the above conditions are met,
we default to staying inside with our else block,
which is basically saying,
or this other condition.
The else block is checking for everything,
50 degrees or below.
We'll write else and then we'll say print, stay inside.
Now, let's run some tests.
When the temperature is 80 and it is sunny,
what do you think will be the output here?
When we run this, we see go to the beach because
the first statement is picking up both of these conditions evaluating to be true.
Now, when the temperature is 20 degrees,
and we run this, what do you think the output will be?
Now, we see stay inside because the else statement is
covering everything below 50 degrees and including 50 degrees,
regardless of the sunny part.
As soon as our temperature reaches 50 degrees,
what do you think the output will be then?
Here, we'll still see stay inside because the temperature isn't greater than 50.
It has to be greater than 50,
not greater than or equal to.
It gets picked up by the else clause again, right there.
Ultimately, when the temperature is 51 degrees,
this would now result in one of the elif statements being fired off.
If we write and execute this code,
we'll see go for a walk.
If we were to change this to be false,
and we execute this code we'll see stay
inside because now it's greater than 50 and is sunny is false.
By introducing logical operators,
we can fine tune our conditions to handle even more complex scenarios.
This approach allows us to layer multiple criteria creating
a more nuanced decision making process in our Python programs.