Nesting conditions is a powerful technique in Python
that allows us to add layers to our decision making process.
By placing one if statement inside another,
we create a hierarchy of checks,
where each subsequent decision is made only if the previous condition is met.
This approach is particularly useful when one condition is dependent on another.
For example, you might check if a user is logged in before verifying their permissions.
If they're not logged in, there's no need to proceed with the permission check.
Nesting also helps break down complex logic into manageable parts,
making it easier to handle intricate scenarios,
such as validating multiple user inputs in a specific order,
guiding users through multi set processes or navigating through decision trees.
Let's look at an example of how nested conditional statements work in practice.
To see how conditionals work with nesting,
we're going to refactor our previous python code with
the weather example that use conditional statements with logical operators
into new python code that uses a nested structure
with if else keywords to accomplish the same exact goal.
We'll start by checking if the temperature is greater than 77 degrees Fahrenheit.
If it is, we'll then evaluate whether it's sunny or not.
If both conditions are met,
we'll print, go to the beach.
If it's not sunny, we'll print, stay inside.
What we'll do is we'll remove
that end component and we'll keep if temperature is greater than 77.
We're then going to add if and else.
If is going to be if sunny.
We're going to take our print statement here and move that up here.
If it's sunny, print, go to the beach.
Else we'll print, stay inside.
Now, we'll write elif,
and we'll say if elif temperature is greater than 50,
we'll remove this and not is sunny component,
and we'll do the same exact thing.
We'll copy this code here.
We're going to remove this part.
We'll paste that in there. Then we're going to say, if is sunny.
So if it's greater than 50 and is sunny,
we're going to say, go for a walk.
Else we'll print, stay inside.
Else we'll then print, stay inside.
So if the temperature is not greater than 77 degrees,
we're going to go down to the elif statement right here,
and we move further down to the else block to check if it's greater than 50.
If it's less than 50,
that's where the else clause will be initiated.
Within this block, we'll nest another statement to check if it's sunny,
so that's why we're printing,
go for a walk here in this nested structure.
Otherwise, in the nested structure we'll print, stay inside.
Finally, if the temperature is 50 degrees or below,
that's this else clause here,
the program advises us to stay inside
directly as seen with this else statement at the end.
Now, let's run some tests as we did before.
When the temperature is 80 and it's sunny,
so we'll change that to true.
What do you think the output will be here?
If we run this, we'll see, go to the beach.
So if you said, go to the beach, you're right,
and that's because the first statement is picking up on both of
these conditions being true. Right there.
If the temperature is greater than 77 and is sunny.
Now, what if the temperature is 20?
What do you think the output will be here?
Let's run it and see and find out.
This says stand side,
and we see stand side because the else statement is covering everything
below 50 degrees and including 50 degrees regardless of the sunny part.
As soon as our temperature reaches 50,
will this fire off one of these statements here? Let's find out.
When it's 50 and is sunny,
we see stay inside,
and that's because it's not greater than 50. It's exactly 50.
That's what gets picked up by this else clause here,
and that's why we see this in the output.
Ultimately, when the temperature is 51 degrees,
what do you think will happen with the output now?
We'll see go for a walk,
and that's because the third conditional statement where the temperature is
greater than 50 and is sunny is happening right there.
By nesting these conditional statements,
we've added more structure and clarity to our decision making process.
Each layer of logic is clearly separated,
making it easier to manage and adapt to changes.