When you want to execute the same block of code multiple times
without needing to rewrite the function multiple times,
Python has a very handy method for handling this called loops.
You may remember from earlier,
we discussed a case where you want to greet somebody four times,
so you could write something like this.
Now you could totally write this.
This is reasonable code,
but it's not practical or scalable code.
Let's talk about what that means and why. Here's why.
As we scale this to thousands or millions of users,
our greater function would then need to be executed thousands or millions of times.
Meaning we need to write it that number of times.
Imagine how long a Python file like this would need to be.
Fortunately, for us, Python has our back and comes with a way for us to
handle and execute a block of code multiple times called loops with two flavors.
While loops which run when the specified condition is true,
and for loops, which run over a sequence.
Let's dive into what these nuances really mean.