A while loop repeats a block of code as long as a specified condition is true.
If you remember from our section on data types,
true comes from the Boolean data type,
which is the opposite of false.
As such, so long as a condition is true, for example,
so long as a number is below or equal to 100,
counting up to 100,
then the value is true.
Once the number is one value over 100,
then the condition is false.
Let's see while loops in action with an example.
We're going to create a counter function,
so we're going to declare a variable called count,
and we're going to initially set that equal to zero.
Then we're going to write our while loop.
To write our while loop, we'll write while,
and then we'll use the count variable, and then we'll say,
while that is less than five, we'll print,
count colon, and then comma,
write what our count variable is.
Then we'll increment count by plus one.
This above is an example of a counter function,
and the way it works is that you have a number value,
in this case, count,
and that is initially set to zero.
You then write a while loop here,
where the count is less than but not equal to five.
Then we will print the value of count with the print statement.
The fancy plus equal one code just means add plus one to the value of the count,
which is how it would go from zero to a value that could be up until five,
but not including five.
Once the value of count reaches five,
then the function will no longer return true,
and then the while loop would stop. Let's review.
In this while loop example,
the while loop states a condition that is true.
The code will loop continue to execute while the value of the condition is true,
in this case, the count being less than five.
Each time the loop runs,
count is incremented by plus one up until but not including five,
and then the condition becomes false once it hits five,
and then the while loop stops.
Let's see what this looks like as we execute it.
We'll see 0,
1, 2,
3, 4,
and once count reaches five,
then it stops, so that's why we don't see count five,
it counts up to four.
Pretty cool. Where do we use while loops?
While loops are perfect for situations where
we don't know how many iterations we need beforehand.
This makes them incredibly useful for tasks,
like continuously waiting for user inputs
or processing data until a specific condition is met.
Let's explore two practical examples that highlight the power of while loops.
When we think about handling user inputs, in this example,
we're going to write a while loop to continually prompt
the user for an input until they type exit.
How we'll do that is, we'll declare
a variable that will be an empty string called user input.
Then we'll write our while loop,
and we'll say while user_input.lower
function does not equal exit,
we'll set user input equal to
the input and we
will write a multi-line comment here,
and we'll say enter something type exit to quit the colon.
That's all closed out. Then we will say
print you entered followed by actually with that user,
we'll put in right here.
We'll close that off. The way that this loop will work is that this loop will
keep asking the user for an input until they type exit into the input field.
Also, notice how we're using this lower method to
convert the user's input to a lowercase before comparing it to exit.
This ensures that no matter how the user types exit,
whether in upper case or mixed case,
the loop will recognize it and stop.
It's like having a built-in spell checker that makes sure the input is always consistent.
This is very similar to what you will see when you
start running a Python program or within another programming language.
There might be a command to control plus C or to simply type exit,
enter into your terminal,
and the program will stop.
Let's see what happens when we run this.
When we run this, we'll see our comment that we'll say enter something,
and then it'll say type exit to quit.
If we said type something,
we type something, say something else,
we'll say something else, something else again.
It's going to continually prompt us to keep writing in something into the input.
But until we type exit,
press ''Enter'', then it stops.
If we were to do this again,
let's say we even did it in all caps, it'll still exit.
Let's say we even did some mixed upper and lower case,
say exit, it will still always turn it to a lower case to then exit.
That's how we combine and handle multiple user inputs in Python.
Now, let's talk about processing data until a condition is met.
We're going to move on to another while
loop example where we're processing data from a file.
In this example, the while loop is going to read and process
each line of the file until there are no more lines left.
We're going to first create a text file with a few lines of text in it.
The way that we'll do that is we're going to make a new file,
we're going to call it text.txt,
so I right-clicked, and then I created a new file.
We'll open this up, and then I'm going to copy and paste this into the text file.
Sometimes you might get a message that says shared a clipboard,
so I'll say allow,
and that's where we're able to add all of this text into our text file.
We'll give this a save and then we're going to write a script that
will open this file and then use the read line method to fetch one line at a time,
which are baked in functionalities of Python.
As each line is processed,
we'll update our live variable with the next line from each file.
The loop will continue until read line returns an empty string
indicating that the end of the file has been met. Let's do that right now.
What we'll do is that we will open up a new cell,
and we're going to say with open,
and we'll say text.txt,
and we'll put this in quotes because it is a string.
We're going to use r and put that in quotation marks,
and then we're going to say as input file.
We'll do a colon, and then we'll say line = input_file.readline,
and then while line is true.
We'll say print, and then in the parentheses,
we'll say line.strip and this will take each line out,
and then we will write line = input_file.readline.
In this example, this while loop reads and processes
each line in a file until there are no more lines left to read.
While loops are like your dedicated Pythonic assistants,
working tirelessly until a task is complete.
Whether they're waiting for the user to give the magic word like
exit or diligently reading through a file, one line at a time.
They're there to get the job done while there is a job to be done.
Let's run this and see what prints out.
This has 1, 2,
3, 4, 5, 6,
and there are 1, 2, 3, 4,
5, 6 lines in this text file.
This worked exactly the way that we would expect.
With these tools in your coding toolkit,
you'll be able to handle repetitive tasks like a pro.
Next time you need to repeat something in your code,
but don't know how many times it will need to be repeated,
think of the trusty while loop in your Pythonic toolkit.