When working with while loops,
it's important to be aware of some common pitfalls and considerations.
Understanding these can help you avoid bugs and write more efficient code.
We'll explore three key areas,
infinite loops, when the loop condition never becomes false.
Off-by-one errors, when the loop runs one
time too many or too few and ensuring termination,
so that the loops always progress towards an end and stop when we expect them to.
One of the most common issues with while loops is the risk of creating an infinite loop.
This occurs when the loop's condition never becomes false,
causing the loop to run indefinitely.
Imagine setting your home heating system to a desired temperature.
If there's no mechanism to stop the system once
the temperature is reached that is desired,
it would keep heating indefinitely,
potentially causing a disaster.
In coding terms, we need to ensure that our while loops have
a condition that will eventually become false.
Let's write out a function to do just that.
In our Jupyter notebook,
we will create two variables,
one that will be called desired_temperature.
We'll set that equal to 68,
and then we'll have another variable called current_temperature,
and we'll set that equal to 66.
We'll then write our while loop and we'll write while current_temperature,
right here is less than the desired_temperature.
We'll then print in F string,
and we'll say heating.
Then current temperature and
then we'll put in the actual current_temperature in curly braces.
We'll close that up, and then we'll end the print string,
the print statement with that F string in there.
Then we'll increment the current_temperature right here,
and we'll say +=1,
which will simulate heating by increasing the temperature by
one degree since this is just for example purposes.
Then we'll print desired temperature reached.
Heating system turned off,
once the temperature is achieved that we wanted to.
In this example, here,
the heating system will listen for an input,
and say you set the temperature to 68,
and it is currently 66.
Right there. The heating system will then ask,
is the temperature less than or equal to 68?
Which is there, so then it'll go up to 67.
If it is less than the heating system,
it will remain on and working,
since it'll be a true situation.
Once a heating system detects the temperature is up until the temperature becomes 68,
to which we would want the heating system to turn off false.
In this case, Boolean values will help us to shape
the while clause so that it would stop after a certain temperature is desired.
But what if we didn't have a desired temperature?
This is where our infinite loop comes into play,
and we could see this in real time.
If we did not have a desired temperature here, copy this down.
If we were to remove that, and we just say,
while current_temperature, and then current temperature is printed out,
and then we increment the current temperature plus one and then we
print desired temperature reached heating system turned off,
what do you think is going to happen to this function now that we don't
have a limit on what the current temperature can go up to?
We'll receive this error,
and it'll say the data rate is exceeded,
and it'll still keep trying to execute,
even though it has basically crashed.
Without a ceiling number to count to,
Python does not know where we want to stop at hence creating
an infinite loop because the number
always exists and continues to climb higher and higher.
The outputs just keep going and going as you don't see here,
but it is just running indefinitely,
and the data rate limit has been exceeded.
Another common pitfall is the off-by-one error,
where the loop runs one time too many or too few.
This usually happens when the loop condition doesn't
exactly match the intended number of iterations.
It's important to carefully check your conditions to avoid
this issue and make sure that it doesn't happen when you write your python code.
Let's write a counter function to increment up to and including five.
We'll declare a variable called count,
and we'll set that equal to zero.
Then we'll write our while loop.
We'll say while count is less than or equal to five print count,
and then we'll do, count,
print count with the actual value of count,
and then we'll increment count by plus one,
which is plus equals one.
If we were to run this, what do you think will be the output when we execute this cell?
But hold on a second. Why is it saying that there are six numbers between 0 and 5?
If we count 1, 2,
3, 4, 5, 6.
In this example, this will run one extra iteration than intended by using this less
than or equals to sign instead of a less than sign counting up until five.
This is something that we have to look out for.
We will need to make sure that we know exactly what to expect,
which means adjusting our count variable from 0-1 so
that the count starts at one and goes up to and including five like this.
We switch count equals zero to count equals one,
and then when we execute this,
we now see 1, 2, 3,
4, 5 like so.
Finally, it's crucial to ensure that your while loop is progressing towards termination.
We're going to talk about how to ensure progression towards
termination when we write our while loops in Python.
This means that a variable involved in the loop's condition should
be modified within the loop's body so that the loop will eventually stop.
If you forget to modify this variable,
you risk creating an infinite loop.
Let's take our counter example from earlier and see what
happens when there is no final terminated state.
If we were to write count equals one,
we'll say while count is less than or equal to five,
and then we'll say print, count count,
and we'll say equal to one.
With this count plus equals one part,
if we forget to increment the count with this crucial part,
this causes an infinite loop.
If we were to just do this,
this will just keep running indefinitely,
and it keeps running and this will error out the Jupyter notebook.
We're going to need to stop this by stopping the terminal.
We can restart, and then we can restart it again.
Wait for that to boot up. Now we have our Jupyter notebook back here.
The reason why we need to add this plus
equals one is that so we can count upwards until five,
and then the loop stops exactly when we expect it to on the five.
That's why this is a crucial part to prevent the infinite loop from occurring.
That's why when we execute this,
now we're counting correctly up to five because the loop is
set to terminate at that specific ending point.
This helps us ensure progression towards
termination and reaching a final state so that it doesn't continue to run indefinitely.
While loops are a powerful tool for performing
repetitive tasks until a specified condition is no longer met.
They are particularly useful when the number of iterations isn't known beforehand.
By understanding how to use while loops effectively and avoiding common pitfalls,
you can handle a wide variety of programming scenarios.
Here's some key points to remember.
While loops execute as long as a specified condition is true.
They are useful for tasks where the number of iterations is not known in advance.
Be cautious of infinite loops and off by one errors,
and you can use else with while loops for additional functionality.
You've just added a very powerful tool to your Python toolbox of skills. Great job.