For loops are a versatile and powerful tool in Python,
especially when you know the number of
iterations or times you need to run your code in advance.
A for loop is used for iterating over a sequence of items,
as in a list of things.
Such groups of things can be called the list,
tuple, dictionary, set, or string.
Don't worry if you don't recognize these words.
They are going to be explained later in the course.
All you have to know is that loops allow you to execute a block of code for each item in
the sequence and are particularly useful when
you need to perform repetitive tasks on a collection of items.
To see for loops in action,
let's start with a basic example of a for loop.
When we have a list of items such as items in a shopping cart,
we might want to run a specific function where there are items in that list.
Let's see an example. First, we'll create a variable called cart,
and we'll set that equal to a list or array of items.
Which I will put in here.
These will be a list of fruits.
Then for each item in cart,
so we'll say for item in cart,
we're going to print each item, like so.
In this example, the for loop iterates over each item in the cart,
which is a list right here and prints each item.
The word item is our loop variable,
a temporary variable placeholder that takes the value of each element in the sequence,
which for us in this example is cart.
In this code snippet,
the first item will be apple,
which is at index 0.
Then the second item will be banana, index 1.
Then the third will be cherry,
index 2, and finally,
the last item in the list is grapefruit at index 3 of this array.
Here's a breakdown of how this for loop works.
The loop variable item takes on the value of each element in the list cart one by one.
For each value of item,
the code block inside the loop executes,
which we have as printing the item.
The structure is for item in list,
and the item part can be anything we want.
We just need to make sure that it follows the format of for something in a group,
and that group needs to correspond to a list array of items to iterate over.
For this example, our list is cart.
Can you guess what the output is going to be when we execute the cell?
Let's find out. The output of this loop will be apple,
banana, cherry, and grape fruit.
If you said this, you're right.
So long as there is an item in the cart,
the for loop will print the item in the cart.
Once there are no more items,
there will be nothing left to print,
and then the for loop would know to stop.
One of the superpowers of the for loop is that it
automatically adjusts to the number of items in the list.
If the list changes should items be added or removed from the group,
the loop will still work correctly without any changes needed for our Python code.
This makes our for loops incredibly powerful and
flexible for handling collections of items when those items are changing.
Let's explore three common scenarios where for loops shine,
such as with numbers.
We often use for loops to iterate over a sequence of numbers.
This is especially useful when you want to perform an action a specific number of times.
In this case, using the range function helps
generate the sequence of numbers for the loop to iterate over.
Next is with strings.
For loops can also iterate over each character in a string.
This allows you to break down a word or sentence into
its individual characters and perform actions on them one by one.
Lastly, let's talk about using loops with collections.
For loops can iterate over various collections,
such as lists, tuples, and sets.
This is incredibly useful for processing each item in a collection,
like printing each fruit in a shopping cart list.
One important point to note here is,
remember to use for loops when you know the number of items or iterations ahead of time.
They are your go to tool for
repetitive tasks when the sequence or collection is well defined,
like items in a shopping cart or a specific set of numbers.