In this lesson, you've looked a lot at sampling distributions.
We might still not understand the use of this idea in practice.
In the next lessons,
you're going to learn more about inference.
Specifically, you'll be learning about Confidence Intervals and Hypothesis Testing.
When looking at these techniques online,
you might find a lot of formulas and
built-in calculators for computing the final results for these techniques.
However, these built-in calculators hide the assumptions and potential biases.
With your new understanding of sampling distributions and bootstrapping,
you're ready to tackle not only using the built-in techniques,
but to extend these techniques to a multitude of other situations.