You now have seen how a sampling distribution provides how a statistic varies.
As we saw, the proportions change with different samples of students.
However, we might also look at the distribution of other statistics,
like how the sample standard deviation, the variance,
difference in mean or any other statistic varies from one sample to the next.
Notice, we are not looking at the distribution parameters.
As you saw in the first example,
the parameter that is a numeric summary of a population is a fixed value,
so these values do not change.
However, statistics will change based on a sample you select from the population.
So what are the common traits of sampling distributions??