Let's compare our model to some models created by OpenAI.
The very first model released by OpenAI was called GPT-1.
It had 120 million parameters,
12 layers, and was trained on 4.5 gigabytes of data.
Their next model called GPT-2 was a scaled up version of GPT-1.
It has the same architecture,
but had around 10 times more parameters,
four times more layers,
and they also used 10 times more training data to train this model.
They then scaled up this architecture again and created the GPT-3 model,
which becomes the foundation for their ChatGPT product.
This model had even more layers,
more parameters, and was strained on even more data.
We don't know a lot about their most recent models,
but it is rumored that it is based on
a mixture of different models that have even more parameters.
One trend that you can see is that the bigger the model is,
the more capable it usually becomes,
and there are already some models with one trillion parameters.
Scaling models is not the only thing we need to do
to achieve capabilities of products like ChatGPT.
If we train a model that can simply predict next to word,
it will only be able to generate text,
but it won't be able to answer questions like ChatGPT.
This doesn't depend on the amount of training data that we use or the model size.
To give you an example of how this works,
I've sent the following prompt to one of the older versions of
GPT-3 that was trained to generate text instead of answering questions.
As you can see, instead of answering a question,
it started generating text related to the question.
After being trained on a larger text corpus,
it can only generate text that could be
surrounding a text that looks like the provided prompt.
In contrast, if you send this question to ChatGPT,
it would return and answer like Paris and possibly provide some additional information.
So how did OpenAI train the model that can answer questions?
Let's take a high level overview.
They first trained a GPT model which is similar to what we've built,
but bigger and using much more data.
Then they've used a data set of questions and answers.
Having this data set,
they updated weights of
the trained GPT model to create a model that can answer questions.
This new model that was produced as a result of this process was called GPT-3.5,
and it was used by the first version of ChatGPT.
This process of taking a model trained for one task and modifying
its weights to work for a different task is called fine-tuning,
and it is used not just for LOMs,
but for other deep learning models as well.
To fine-tune a model to perform question answering,
OpenAI went through the following steps.
First, they collected a dataset with different prompts and questions.
Then they had humans answering questions and
organized human provided answers into a data set.
This data set was then used to fine-tune GPT-3 model to be trained to answer questions.
After this, they went through a different process.
Using prompts, they sampled several outputs from
a model to generate multiple answers for the same question.
Then people were ranking these answers against each other.
Using these ranking results,
OpenAI created another data set.
This data set of ranked answers was used to train another model called
the reward model that can calculate how good an answer to a prompt is.
Finally, using the reward model,
they fine-tuned GPT-3 model to give
answers that are more closely aligned with the reward policy.
As you can see, training a model that can answer questions is a complicated process.
These datasets that were used for this are not
shared by OpenAI and are much harder to collect.