We have implemented a particular architecture for
large language models called decoder-only architecture.
It turns out that there are other architectures,
and now we'll briefly cover what they are and how they differ from each other.
Transformers were initially introduced in a paper called,
Attention is All You Need.
This paper described an architecture that is
more complex comparing to the architecture that we've implemented.
You see the image of this architecture on the screen right now.
It also was created for a different purpose.
Instead of having a goal to generate text,
the authors of the paper were working on a new way
of translating text from one language to the other.
But if you look closely at this diagram,
you will see that the right part should be somewhat familiar.
It has the embedding layer,
the positional encoding,
the masked multi-head attention,
and just to remind you,
masked is referred to a triangular mask we've used to change the attention scores.
It also has the feed-forward layer with the residual connection,
and the Nx means that this block is repeated multiple times,
similar to how we had it in our model.
What we did not have in our model was this section on the left,
called encoder, and we also didn't have the connection between these blocks.
The encoder block on the left was used to
encode information about an input text for translation.
The part on the right that we've implemented is called a decoder.
It receives a part of the translation it has generated so far,
and given the encoded inputs it generates the next token.
The encoder is very similar to a decoder with the main difference
that it uses a multi-head attention instead of a masked multi-head attention,
meaning that it computes attention scores based on
all tokens in the input without using the triangular mask.
When using this model we pass two different inputs.
Input to the encoder,
which is a text to translate,
and decoder's input that contains a partially translated output,
and the decoder's input that contains a part of the translation generated so far.
The encoder input goes through all the layers of the encoder,
and the output from its final layer is sent to every layer of the decoder.
Decoder layers then use this information from
the encoder to generate the next token in the translation.
Because the input to the encoder block does not change,
we can compute it once and pass it to
all decoder blocks while generating the output text.
Let's look at an example of how an encoder-decoder model
would translate text from English to French.
We would first tokenize the text we want to translate and convert it into token IDs.
Then we would pass these IDs to the encoder for
it to build a representation of a phrase we want to translate.
To start the translation process we would pass
a special character called Start of the sequence, to the decoder.
Decoder will read this input and the encoder's output,
and will produce the first token ID of the translated phrase,
which corresponds to the following French word.
We would then add the generated token ID to
the input as the decoder and send it to the decoder again.
Decoder will now receive a new input with
the same encoder output as on the previous step and generate the new token.
We then repeat this process again and generate
more and more output tokens until
the model generates the special end of the sequence token,
which means that the model has translated the whole phrase.
We can then convert token IDs into the human-readable sentence that looks like this.
Using encoders and decoders as building blocks,
we can have three different network architectures.
Decoder-only model that only has a decoder part and no encoder.
This is what we've implemented in this lesson.
This architecture is well suited for tax generation tasks,
and is used by models like GPT and Lama.
The other option is called encoder-decoder models.
In this case we have both encoder and decoder blocks.
These models are good from converting from one sequence to another.
For example, if we need to translate text into another language.
Some models implementing this architecture include BART and T5.
Finally, the last option is encoder-only models.
These models don't have a decoder,
and only pass inputs through an encoder.
This is useful if we want to build a representation for
text classification like sentiment analysis or spam detection.
BART is an example of a model using this architecture.