So far, we have been looking into how to create a large language model from scratch.
Now, let's look into how to use
existing large language models and how to
adapt them to various tasks in your applications.
While it is important to understand how large language models work under the hood,
it is unlikely you will need to create one from scratch for your applications.
Training an LLM from scratch is challenging,
and there are a few reasons for this.
Training these models require huge amounts of
training data and a lot of computational resources.
These models are also very expensive to train.
For example, the cost of training GPT-4 model cost more than $100 million.
Finally, developing new models require a specialized skill set,
especially if you aim to implement a state of the art model.
Fortunately, instead of creating a model from scratch,
we can use existing models created by
companies and researchers from all around the world.
To do this, we will use the Hugging Face library,
which is one of the most popular NLP libraries for Python.
At the moment of this recording,
it has a whopping 127,000 stars on GitHub.
It also has a huge community contributing to the project,
developing new large language models and improving its features.
Hugging Face simplifies building applications using LLMs,
but it's not limited to this.
It also provides tools for developing new LLMs, as well.
Hugging Face is a collection of multiple components that all work together.
It provides an API that allows us to build applications using LLMs.
We can access a large collection of
pre-trained models that we can use in our applications.
It also provides access to datasets for different purposes that
we can use to train our models or improve existing models.
Finally, it provides the spaces project that allows
to quickly create machine learning demos and applications.
Speaking of its API,
Hugging Face provides a set of
flexible and powerful APIs that we can use to build our AI applications.
Using their API, we can do things like access existing models for a variety of tasks,
such as text generation,
text summarization, and so on.
We can train new models,
or we can fine tune existing models from their library of models.
Fine tuning is a process that allows us to take an existing model and
update its weights to make it better for
a specific task for which the model wasn't trained for.
We can also process text for LLMs.
For example, we can tokenize a text using an existing tokenizer,
or we can even create our own tokenizer.
Finally, we can deploy our LLMs.
Hugging Face is also not limited to working with just text.
It also includes APIs to work with images and audio.
You might be wondering how Hugging Face is different from OpenAI.
Both provide models and allow us to build applications using them.
These however, are very different companies.
Hugging Face is an open source product.
We can run models from Hugging Face locally on our laptops or on servers that we control.
Finally, Hugging Face models are free to use.
On the other hand, OpenAI,
despite the name, provides closed source models.
They only allow us to access their models via the API,
and these models run on servers that OpenAI operates.
Finally, we also need to pay to access advanced OpenAI models.