Let's now take a look at how we can use existing LLMs with hugging face.
When it comes to using hugging face models,
we have two options.
First, we can use a high-level API accessible using the pipeline function.
Or we can use a more flexible but more low-level API,
which we would use if we want to have more control over how to use a particular model.
Since this is a beginner-friendly lesson,
we will focus just on using the high-level API.
But keep in mind that hugging face API has much more to offer.
Let's now look at how to use a large language model with a hugging face.
First, we need to import the pipeline function from the transformers package.
To use it, we need to call
the pipeline function and provide the name of the task we wanted to do.
Here we specify text generation to generate text,
but there are other tasks we can use such as text summarization and others.
The pipeline function returns
another function that we can use to perform the selected task.
We then need to specify a prompt for tax generation.
Since we've selected the tax generation task,
it will continue generating text that continues the selected phrase.
To generate x using this prompt,
we need to call the generator function returned by
the pipeline call and provide a few parameters,
such as a prompt, the maximum length of the output that it will generate,
and number of sequences we wanted to generate.
This will take the provided prompt,
pass it to the LLM,
and it will return a response.
Under the hood, it goes through the steps,
you should already be pretty familiar with.
When hugging face receives an input text,
it splits it into tokens using a tokenizer for the selected model.
Converts these tokens into IDs and then passes these token IDs to the model.
Then the model returns a set of logits that are then used to generate an output.
Hugging phase can do a myriad of different NLP-related tasks.
It supports tasks like text generation that we've just covered.
Questions answering, text summarization.
It allows to translate between different languages,
and it supports classification of text into one of selected categories.
We can use hugging face not only for NLP-related tasks.
It also supports audio-related tasks like audio classification,
and converting text to audio.
It also allows us to work with images and videos.
For example, we can use it to generate an image description,
classify videos, perform image segmentation, and much more.
Let's take a look at how to use hugging face for tasks other than generating text.
Here is an example of how to perform image classification with hugging face.
Again, we need to use the pipeline function,
but here we specify a different task called image classification.
Then we pass an image file or an image URL to classify.
The output of this score is a list where every element
contains a label and the probability associated with it.
In this case, it thinks that the image we've passed to it is likely an image of a cat.