In this demo, we will see how to use
the Hugging Face high level API to use some pre trained large language models.
Specifically, we will go through a few examples of how to use these models.
We'll see how to summarize text,
how to generate new text,
how to classify text samples, and so on.
First of all, to use the high level API from Hugging Face,
we need to import the pipeline function from the transformers.
Having this function, let's see how we can summarize some text.
To do this, first of all,
we'll need to create a pipeline and specify the summarization task when we create it.
This function will return a summarizer that we can then use to summarize our text.
To use the summarizer,
we need to provide the text to summarize and call the summarizer with
some optional parameters such as max_length and min_length,
which specifies the maximum and the minimum number of tokens in the result summary.
A single call to a summarizer might return multiple different summaries.
To get a text of a single summary,
we need to get the value of the summary text from the first summary.
Now let's see how we can generate some text.
The process here is very similar.
We create a pipeline and then we provide a prompt that will
be used as a starting point for the model to generate follow up text.
We can also provide additional parameters here,
like max_length, as we did before,
and the maximum number of sequences to return.
As before, the output that we get from the generator is similar to what we got before.
To get the generated text,
we need to get the first sequence and use the generated text field from it.
If you look at this text,
it says that the scientists from
this university created a new drug and so on and so forth.
It looks like a reasonably generated text about a potential news article.
The other thing that we will try to do is to classify
text using so called zero-shot classification.
A shot in this context means how many examples do we provide
in a prompt to our model for it to understand what it should do.
Zero means we don't provide any examples.
If we have one shot classification,
it means we provide a single example of how to classify text in a prompt itself,
and we can use more than one shot classification as well.
In this case, we again create a pipeline,
specify the name of the task that we will do,
and then we'll provide the text and the labels for a classifier to create the prompt.
We also provide the hypothesis template that will become the part of
the prompt and will help the model to figure out what are we asking it to do.
Classifier returned a list of scores for each of the labels we have provided.
If you look at the result,
it specifies that this text about transformers is most likely about technology.
Finally, Hugging Face is not limited to working just with text.
We can also use it with images.
For example, if we have an image like this that
I got from one of the Hugging Face datasets,
we can create a captioner model that will write a text caption for this image,
so it will describe what is there on this image.
To do this, I'll create a pipeline.
Here I use a different way of creating
a pipeline where it just provides the name of the model to use.
If we scroll down and print the result,
the text says two birds are sitting next to each other,
which is pretty much spat on.