Now we will talk about how we can affect tax generation results using
various generation parameters that are available in Hugging Face and other libraries.
To avoid some possible confusion,
there are two types of parameters.
Model parameters; these are parameters that were set during a model training,
and generation parameters;
these can affect the result of a tax generation when we use a model after it was trained.
We have already seen one parameter,
which is the maximum number of tokens,
tax generation process should return.
In Hugging Face, it is called max length parameter.
As you can imagine, the higher this parameter is,
the longer the output the tax generation process will produce.
One [inaudible], however,
is that it defines a maximum number of tokens and
tax generation can return an output that is shorter than this value.
During the tax generation process,
a model can emit a special end of sequence token that will
stop the generation process even before it reached the specified limit.
Now, let's talk about how we can generate text using an LLM.
One simple option is that every time we want to generate
a new token is to select a token with the highest probability.
Once our model produces the probabilities from the softmax layer,
it might be logical to just pick the word with the highest probability.
Once we select a token,
we can add it to the input and then generate the new token,
and then repeat this process again and again.
This approach, when we always pick a token with
the highest probability is also called greedy decoding,
because we are always greedily pick a token with the highest probability.
There is, however an issue with this approach.
If we pick a token with the highest probability,
it can lead to boring and repetitive results.
One surprising fix for this is to add a little bit of
randomness and pick less probable tokens when generating output.
We also have control over how much randomness we want to add.
We will look into this later and you will be able
to experiment with this in the upcoming exercise.
Picking a random token is called multinomial sampling.
If you recall, we can use the output as a softmax layer as a probability distribution.
We can pick a token randomly using this distribution,
and the higher the probability of a token,
the higher the chance that it will be selected.
In this case, if an LLM has returned to tokens with this distribution,
we'll pick powerful in roughly 10% of cases,
trained in roughly 9% of cases, and so on.
Once we've picked a token,
we can repeat the process as before and
add it to the input and then generate the next token.
This new input will give us a new distribution,
and then we can pick the next token randomly, and so on.
There is however an issue with only looking at one next token at a time.
It can lead to suboptimal results when selecting the follow up tokens.
It could be that if we selected a lower probability token.
First, it could lead to better result sequences.
A way to fix it is that instead of generating only a single sequence,
is to try to generate multiple sequences at the same time,
and then select the best result at the end.
We can't try all possible token combinations
on every step since it will quickly become unmanageable.
To evaluate multiple sequences,
we can use the algorithm called beam search.
Instead of generating a single output,
it tries to generate several sequences using a few different tokens.
At every step of the algorithm,
we keep and best sequences so far and we'll try to
generate new sequences starting from the sequences we have.
Then we just repeat this process multiple times.
Here is an example of how this works.
Instead of generating just one sequence from the initial prompt,
we try to generate two sequences using two most probable next tokens,
which are powerful and trained in this case.
This process produces two more sequences that we again
pass to our model to get two new probability distributions.
In this case, we have n = 2,
which means that we have two sequences we consider on each step.
Having two sequences, we can pick
two more tokens that will result in most likely outputs,
and we will have two more sequences that we can use for the next step.
When we are randomly selecting the next token given
the probability distribution returned by the softmax function.
We also have control over what tokens to pick when selecting the next word.
There are two related parameters that are called top-K,
which specifies the number of tokens with the highest probability,
the generation process should consider when selecting the next token.
The other parameter is top-P,
which can specify the total probability of most probable tokens,
a generation process should consider when selecting the next token.
Let's take a look at the top-K parameter.
If we set top-K to three,
it means that when generating text,
we will pick the next token from only top three tokens and model has returned.
In this example, it will randomly select either power, trained,
or vulnerable, but it won't pick A or few or any other tokens.
If we set it to six,
it means that we will pick from top six tokens.
Selecting the higher number of K means that the result text might get more creative,
or it might diverge into somewhat unrelated areas.
But if I set the value too high,
it can start generating nonsense.
The final parameter that we can use to control token generation is called T,
and this parameter affects the probability distribution returned by the softmax layer.
To use it, we divide the logit values by
this T parameter before we use these values in the soft max calculations.
If we set it to one, then the softmax function will just return the regular output.
However, if we make T parameter smaller,
then logits with higher values will get significantly higher probability,
increasing the chance that they will be selected.
It also decreases the chances that tokens with lower logit values will be selected.
On the other hand, if we set temperature to a higher value,
the probability distribution becomes more flat,
increasing the chance that the value with lower logit values will be selected.
Using Hugging Face,
we can provide values for all the parameters we've discussed so far.
When using the generator function,
we can provide do sample to enable multinomial sampling,
specify the number of beams in the beam search and provide top-K,
top-P or temperature to influence the degree of randomness in the output.