Welcome to lesson 4 on functions and exceptions.
The last lesson in our PCP course,
where we'll be diving into the methodologies and patterns for making
our Python code come to life almost as if by magic.
Imagine after a long day of coding in Python,
you become quite hungry and wander over to
the kitchen to cook yourself some food in order to refuel.
You pull up a recipe on your phone and start following each step one by one.
Perhaps, you'll need to add in some ingredients,
sprinkle in some spices,
mix in vegetables, or combine other mix ins.
Bring them all together in certain ways,
prepare the wet and dry ingredients separately,
and/or together, put certain foods on the grill or into the oven to bake,
and so on and so forth.
To give another example,
imagine you're assembling a car,
and you need to put a lot of various pieces together.
Instead in doing each step manually every single time.
You have a machine that knows how to do the assembly once you give it instructions.
The machine can follow the instructions with
near perfect precision and accuracy every time,
ensuring each car in the assembly line comes out the same.
In the world of Python programming,
we have something similar to recipes called functions.
Functions are like those detailed steps in a recipe,
allowing us to break down complex problems into manageable pieces.
They help us write clearer,
reusable and more organized code.
They can also help us follow a specific flow or layout of, if this,
then that or if this or that,
helping us stay logical, precise, and methodical.
Functions and Python act as these machines.
Once created, they allow you to reuse code,
break your programs into smaller,
manageable pieces, and even handle complex logic.
But what happens if your machine encounters an issue,
like a missing part for the car in the assembly line?
Or you're missing an ingredient for your delicious dinner.
If a recipe is missing an ingredient or a crucial baking step,
this can spell disaster for the meal.
Or if the car is not assembled correctly,
because the assembly line forgot to include different crucial steps,
the car might not come out correctly.
This is where exceptions come into play.
Python allows you to detect and manage unexpected situations ensuring that
your program continues running smoothly or handles errors gracefully?
In this lesson, we're going to take a deep dive into functions,
how they interact with the environment around them,
and how we handle those annoying little bugs that pop up, known as exceptions.
By the end of this lesson,
you will define and invoke your own user defined functions,
understand how arguments and parameters work,
and learn how Python handles exceptions and errors.
If you're ready to take your Python skills to the next level,
let's dive into the world of functions and exceptions.