Imagine you're working on a puzzle where each piece is interconnected and solving
one piece helps you get closer to solving the next part of the puzzle and so on.
Recursion in Python work similarly to this.
It's a technique where a function calls itself,
allowing you to break down complex problems into smaller,
more manageable steps automatically.
Let's say you have a mountain of books that need
sorting one by one into an ordered stack.
Instead of tackling the entire pile at once,
you pick up one book,
organize it, then hand the rest of the pile back to yourself to continue sorting.
This process repeats until there are no more books left to sort.
In Python, recursion can help you with tasks that involve repetitive patterns or steps,
especially when the problem can be broken down
into smaller sub problems of the same kind.
So when should we use recursion?
Recursion is particularly useful in compartmentalization,
where the problem can be divided into
smaller sub problems that mirror the larger problem.
In simplification, when you want to simplify code that
involves repeated tasks by letting each task built on the previous one,
and in mathematical operations,
where you are tackling problems like tree traversal,
sequence generation, or mathematical operations such as factorials,
that naturally lend themselves to recursive solutions.
When shouldn't we use recursion?
Recursion can be inefficient or problematic when there are
memory constraints because each recursive call adds a new layer to the call stack,
which can quickly exhaust memory and lead to stack overflow errors,
especially for deep or infinite recursions.
Performance concerns, as recursion can be slower than
iterative approaches due to the overhead of multiple function calls,
particularly for tasks that require a large number of iterations.
Or there is great complexity.
Such as if the problem doesn't inherently break down into smaller sub problems,
recursion might add unnecessary complexity to your code.
Let's see some examples where we see recursion in action to add more clarity.
In this demo, we're going to be talking about recursion.
Let's see an example of recursion in action by calculating the factorial of a number.
The factorial of a number n written as n with
an exclamation point is the product of all positive integers leading up to that number.
The factorial of a number will look like that.
For example, five factorial is really this.
It's 5*4*3*2*1 which equals 120,
and we can make sure that this is true because if we do this,
we'll change these xs to asterisks to indicate times.
What can say is five factorial equals this times this times this,
and then we can print the value of this.
We'll see that this is in fact,
120 or five factorial equals 120.
But imagine if we wanted to get the factorial of 100 or 1,000 or 10,000.
This would be way too much work to do by hand,
so we'll want to leverage recursion in Python to help
automate this process for us. How would we do this?
First, we'll define the function of factorial
n where n is the number we want to calculate the factorial of.
Next, we'll set up the base case to stop the recursion.
If n is one, we return a one because the factorial of one is itself.
This is how we will prevent infinite recursion,
which is a type of infinite loop like we learned about earlier in the course.
We need to escape the function from running forever.
This is how we'll do that. For n values greater than one,
we multiply n by the result of factorial n minus one.
This pattern repeats until n equals one.
When the base case is met,
which will stop the recursion loop from continuing.
When the base case is reached,
our function begins to return results back up the chain of calls,
multiplying each returned value by n,
and this is how the full factorial is calculated with Python.
Let's write a function to illustrate this.
We'll write def factorial and we'll put n for the placeholder of the input.
Then we'll say if n equals equals one,
then return one, and this is to prevent our infinite loop like we talked about before.
Otherwise, we'll continue with our recursive loop,
and we'll say, else, colon return.
N times factorial n minus one.
We'll save this function to our Jupiter notebook,
and will this actually work?
Well, let's test it out and find out.
If we were to print the factorial,
which we copy from here,
and we put in five into our input.
Can you guess what the output is going to be when we run our function?
It prints out 120,
which means that our factorial function worked.
Recursion is a powerful tool for solving
complex problems by breaking them into manageable steps just like this.
Remember to always define a base case to prevent infinite loops and be
mindful of memory usage when dealing with deep recursion. Great job.