In this next video,
we're going to talk about organizing the interaction between Python functions
and the Python environment where they run. That's a mouthful.
Let's unpack exactly what all of that means.
Imagine you're organizing a small dinner party.
You'll need to set up various parts of the event,
like inviting the guests,
choosing the menu, preparing the dishes,
making name tags, taking guest coats, and so on.
For each task, there are specific details or inputs that guide how you approach it.
Do you have dietary preferences to consider?
Are you expecting a formal or casual buy?
Just like organizing a dinner party,
interacting with functions involves passing in details
and setting the stage for how they operate within your code.
In the last module,
we dove into functions,
generators, and how they work in our code.
In this module, we'll explore the dynamics of
how functions receive and handle data from the rest of your code.
We'll cover the difference between parameters and arguments,
different ways to pass arguments into functions,
using default values to make functions more flexible,
and how Python manages names and sculpts within our functions that we write.