In this course so far, we've already touched briefly on parameters and arguments.
You've already been using these concepts in your Python code,
whether you realize it or not.
Let's dive a bit deeper into these concepts and
start by distinguishing parameters from arguments.
Although they're often used interchangeably,
they actually refer to different concepts in programming.
Parameters are like placeholders that you
define in the function signature when you set up the function.
They are the names you give to data that your function will use,
much like empty plates ready to be filled with food at the dinner table.
Think of these as the placeholder inputs that a function will consume.
Arguments, on the other hand,
are the actual values or data that you pass into the function when you call it.
They're like the food you serve on those plates at the dinner party.
These arguments are what the function uses to perform its task.
Think of these as the actual value inputs that a function will use and run with.
Understanding this distinction helps us when it comes to debugging
or reading our code or someone else's code that we didn't write.
When you see a function definition, look for parameters.
When you see a function call, look for arguments.
They represent the bridge between what
the function needs to know and the actual data it works with.