In Python, there are several ways to pass arguments into functions,
each with its own advantages and trade-offs.
Let's explore these one-by-one;
positional, keyword, and mixed argument passing.
Positional arguments are passed in a specific order,
matching the order of parameters in the function definition.
Here, the function uses the values based on their positions.
In mixed argument passing,
this is a mix of positional and keyword arguments in a single function call.
An important note about this one,
is that positional arguments must come before keyword arguments,
or there will be an error.
Finally, we have keyword arguments where we
specify the parameter name along with the value,
allowing you to pass arguments in any order.
This is my personal favorite method for defining arguments.
Let's see some examples of these different ways to pass in arguments into our functions.
Let's talk about positional,
keyword, and mixed argument passing.
First, positional arguments.
When it comes to positional arguments,
the order of the parameters to be used by the function are extremely important,
as we'll see in this function.
We'll write a function called describe_trip,
and we'll see why positional arguments are so important.
When we write def describe_trip,
we'll pass in city and days into the function as parameters,
and then we'll say return,
and we'll return an f string and say,
we'll spend in squiggly brackets days in city.
You'll spend days in blank, which would be the city.
By calling this function with describe_trip, we'll say Paris,
five, this will place Paris into
the city position and five into the days position, as we'll see here.
Our output will say, you'll spend five days in Paris.
However, what if we were to reverse the argument order like this?
Now our arguments are in reverse order like this.
Can you guess what the output of this is going to be?
When we run this, we'll see you'll spend Paris days in five.
Now the output is reversed.
As you can see, order matters a lot here,
because if you switch the arguments around,
you'll get a completely different result,
perhaps even one that's unintentional or full of errors,
like we just saw in the second example,
going from here to here.
Next up is keyword arguments.
Keyword arguments specify the parameter name along with the value,
allowing you to pass arguments in any order.
This is personally my favorite way to define parameters for my functions,
because while it is more verbose and requires more writing,
it helps to add a layer of structure and
accountability to how functions should be defined and how they should work.
You never have to worry about the order of the inputs because
you explicitly define what they are right from the get go.
For example, this is how we would assign
keyword arguments to our described trip function.
We'll write this function, and then what we'll do is,
we'll re-declare this function.
Now what we'll do is when we are defining our arguments,
we'll say days equal five and city equals Paris.
Now, even though these are reversed in the previous example,
when we print this, we'll now see,
you'll spend five days in Paris.
We can also assign default to our function as well to make sure that
our functions parameters always have a default value.
We'll learn more about this in the next section,
but here's a quick introduction to this concept.
What we can do is that we can take our function like this,
and we could say city equals Paris,
and days equals five.
Our two parameters now have default inputs, Paris, and five.
Even if we were to print just a simple describe_trip,
we'll execute this code.
We'll then not pass in any arguments into the described trip function but if we run this,
we'll now see you'll spend five days in Paris.
So we didn't need to input
those values because they are the defaults if we do not pass anything into them.
Now, we could still define whatever we want.
For example, let's say that we copy this from earlier,
and we say days is 10, and city is Norway.
Now we see you'll spend 10 days in Norway.
But, we still have those default values attached to the parameters as backups,
just in case we were to not include a keyword argument.
If we were to write describe_trip days equals 10,
the output will be,
you'll spend 10 days in Paris,
because Paris is still the default value for city,
but we've updated the days from what the default is of five to now 10.
Now let's talk about mixed argument passing.
You can also mix positional and keyword arguments in a single function call.
However, positional arguments must come before keyword arguments.
Let's re-initialize this function again with no default argument values.
We'll just take our code from before,
and we will re-run the cell,
and then now if we were to say describe trip,
and we pass in again,
our original input, which was Paris,
and days equal five,
now we'll see, you'll spend five days in Paris.
But this will not work if we were to do this in reverse.
If we were to take days and put this before Paris,
since they are mixed arguments,
we'll get a syntax error,
and it'll say positional argument follows keyword argument.
This will not work. Always be careful to define
the positional arguments with no argument equals something first,
and then include the keyword arguments.
Argument equals a value after.
Using mixed arguments offers flexibility
while ensuring that required positional arguments are provided first.
Personally, I find this one a bit more confusing,
but it's important to know how to work with this method.
If you end up seeing this in code,
you get from your team or are working on
functions where this method works for you. Great work.