Now let's talk more about default parameter values,
which are a backup plan for your functions.
When you define a parameter with a default value,
you don't have to pass an argument for it,
as Python will use a default if nothing is provided for it.
Think of default parameter values as a default setting,
such as the default color for a car during checkout.
If you specify that you want your car to have metallic red or night blue,
that is a selection that will be an argument put into your function.
But if you don't specify a color,
the default value could be set as shiny silver,
which will mean the car will be made with
this default color value instead of a specific color.
This feature of having a default makes functions more flexible and reduces the need for
repetitive arguments because it will always be
a fallback option that will be dynamically used automatically.
Just remember that parameters with default values should be placed
after those with defaults in the function signature.
Let's see this more clearly in an example next.
Let's look at default parameter values.
Imagine you're building a car generator function,
and one of the parts allows a user to customize the color of the car before checkout.
We could define something like this where we define a choose_car_color function,
and it takes a parameter of selected_color.
If we return an F string telling us what
color the car will be based on what the user selected,
we might write something like this.
We could say def choose_car_color,
and then as a parameter,
we'll say selected_color as an input,
and then we'll return an F string, and we'll say,
the car color will be, colon,
and we'll pass in selected color and squiggly brackets, and we'll close that out.
Now, if we press "Shift" and "Enter",
we'll save this function to our Jupyter Notebook.
However, this doesn't have a backup plan.
If the user didn't select the color and the function is run like this,
where we say, choose_car_color,
and we try to execute this code,
can you guess what will happen when we run this?
Let's find out. When we run this,
we'll get an error that's a type error, and it will say,
choose_car_color missing one required positional argument, selected_color.
This is because we are referencing an input parameter,
but no argument was passed in,
hence the error of the missing positional argument.
We can avoid this error by adding a default parameter value
for selected_color so that even if a user doesn't select a color,
the car will still have a pre-loaded default,
such as metallic red.
What we can do is that we can pass in this default value
here so that choose_car_color given this parameter,
if we pass it in as an argument or not,
it will have a default metallic red setting.
Now if we save this cell to our Jupyter Notebook as a function,
now if we run choose_car_color,
the output will now say, the car color will be metallic red.
If the user chooses a color like this,
such as night blue,
we'll now see the car color will be night blue.
It's a good practice to get into the habit
of adding in default parameter values if there is
a system or program default or returning
an error via an exception if no input is provided,
and that is important to consider. Great work.