Now it's time to explore name scopes,
name hiding, and the global keyword.
These topics relate to how Python manages
names and variables within different parts of your program.
Let's start with a look at name scopes.
A scope defines where a variable can be accessed.
Different variables have different levels of access
based on where they are located in our Python code.
It has a few different types of scope.
For example, local scope,
which is where variables defined inside
a function are only accessible within that function.
That's very different from global scope,
which are the variables defined outside of
any function are accessible from anywhere in your code.
When we're writing our variables and functions,
scope is incredibly important to think about in Python.
Let's consider this example.
In this example, we declare a global variable called global_var,
and inside our print function,
we are making a local_var equal to the global_var.
If we run this function,
this will print our global_var because the local_var is equal to that.
We can reference global_var anywhere else in our code,
but we cannot reference local_var anywhere else,
only inside of that function.
Let's see some examples of scope in action.