Let's talk about name scopes.
To see an example of this in action,
we're going to write a function that's called print function.
We'll say def print_function and then we'll
say local_var_in_function = I am a local variable.
That will be set as a string.
Then we'll print that variable right here.
Then we'll execute our function below.
When we run this function,
we'll see a print out,
I am a local variable.
But if we were to try and print the variable inside of the function, which is this one,
and we try to do this, we say print_local_var_in_function,
can you guess what's going to happen when we do this?
When we run this, we'll see a NameError,
and it will say name,
local_var_in_function is not defined.
This is because local var and function only exists within the print function.
Trying to access it outside of the function
will result in an error because it's out of scope.
What does a global scope for a variable look like instead?
Let's use another example.
We'll say global_var = I am global.
That'll be set as a string,
and then we'll define a print_global function
where we'll print that variable that we've defined up at the top called global_var,
then we'll execute our print_global_function below.
When we run this, can you guess what the output of this is going to be?
When we execute this cell,
we'll see I am global.
Also, if we try and print global_var like this,
can you guess what we'll be able to see when we just do this?
If you said, I am global, you're right.
We'll also see the same variable string printed out.
This works because we've defined this global variable outside of the function,
and then it's able to pull from this global environment.
But here, because this is locked within the function,
we cannot access it outside of the scope of the function.
But here, because the global variable exists outside of the function scope,
it's now in a global scope,
so we're able to call that from within the function and outside of the function.
Now, let's talk about name hiding and shadowing.
Sometimes local variables can have the same name as global variables.
This is called name hiding or shadowing,
and the local variable takes precedence within its scope.
Basically, what's happening here is that we're
declaring a globally accessible variable at the top,
which we're going to see in a second called name,
and that has a global scope.
Inside, the print name function,
which you'll also see next,
will declare a variable, also called name,
but this has a local scope. Let's do that right now.
We're going to say name = I am a global name.
Name is set as a string and then we're going to define
a print name_function with def print_name and then we're
going to say name = I am a local (name).
Then we're going to print(name),
and then we're going to run
our print name_function and then we're also going to print the variable of name.
Can you guess what these two outputs are going to be?
They're going to print two different things or maybe two of the same things.
But can you guess what the output of print_name will
be and print variable of name will be?
When we execute this code,
we'll see the first statement,
which is print_name,
which is printing the name says I am a local name,
and then print variable name right here,
says I am a global name.
Although there is a global variable name at the top,
the function defines a local variable
here within the same name shadowing the global variable.
Outside of the function,
the global variable remains unchanged.
When we redeclare a variable called name,
even though it has a global scope,
the function will take this to be what we want name to be,
and then it will assume that we are writing name as a variable within that function,
and we only want to call that not the global scope,
if they have the same name.
But when we call this outside of the function scope with print(name),
that's why it prints I am a global name,
as opposed to I am a local name,
which is function specific.
Finally, let's talk about the global keyword.
Expanding upon our local and global scope knowledge from the previous sections,
let's say we want to modify a global variable from within a function.
You might be wondering, how do we do that since global and local are separate scopes?
We can use something called the global keyword to accomplish this.
But just a word of caution.
Be very cautious and careful with this approach as it can make
debugging harder mixing global and local scopes like you're going to see in a second.
First, let's see an example where we're going to be
declaring a globally scoped variable that will be a counter variable,
and then we're going to be writing an increment function that will overwrite
the counter variable by using
the global keyword on the counter variable and incrementing it by plus one.
Let's see what that looks like in action.
We'll declare a variable called counter,
and we'll set that equal initially to zero.
Then we'll define a function called increment and then
we're going to declare a global variable called counter.
Then we're going to say counter += 1.
Then we will call this function and execute it.
We'll run this function by calling the increment and run this whole operation.
Once we execute this, if we were to then print(counter),
can you guess what the output of counter will be?
Counter is now one.
If you said one, you're right.
Notice how it now is no longer zero.
By declaring counter as a global variable
here within the global keyword inside of the increment function,
which is within this, any changes made inside
of increment affect the global counter variable above,
even though counter would otherwise be a locally scoped variable.
If you remember from earlier,
if we were working with variables inside the function,
that would be function specific.
But because we use this global keyword that then tells
Python to look outward to the global scope,
and then to increment
the actual globally scoped counter variable and
not a locally scoped variable within the function.