Imagine you're a chef in one of the busiest restaurant kitchens in the city.
You have an order for your signature dish and you could make
each component from scratch every time an order comes in from a hungry customer.
But that would be exhausting,
tedious, and time consuming.
You think to yourself, there has to be a better way to do this.
Instead, you've carefully prepped ingredients and created
steps that you could repeat for each dish ensuring consistency and speed.
In fact, your steps are so well defined and repeatable that you started to allow
other staff members to cook the special dish
following the recipe because everything is all accounted for.
It works like clockwork.
In Python, functions are like these prepped steps.
They allow us to break down our code into
smaller repeatable recipes that we can call on anytime we need them.
Instead of writing the same code over and over again,
we can create a function once and use it whenever and wherever we want.
This not only makes our programming more efficient,
but also keeps our code organized and easy to manage.
Anyone could run the prepared steps and get the same output each time.
In this section, we'll explore the basics of functions,
seeing how they can transform our coding process just as
a chef's prep work transforms the process of cooking in a busy kitchen.