A function Python is like a mini program inside your program.
You define a function using the def keyword
followed by the function name and parentheses.
Think of defining a function like writing down a recipe in your restaurant.
You list out the ingredients, inputs,
and steps, making it easy to follow and repeat.
When you're ready to use this recipe,
you simply use Python to invoke or call the function,
just like you would when cooking a meal,
following those steps to your recipe.
Earlier in the course, we learned about various methods that Python comes
prepared with or pre-baked with that are called built-in functions.
Python is very powerful because right out of the box,
it can do many incredible processes that we've looked at,
such as print, outputs text to the console.
Len returns the length of an object like a string or a list.
Sum adds all items in an iterable together,
such as a list and type returns the data type of an object.
These functions are part of
Python's standard library and don't require you to define them yourself.
They're highly optimized and designed to handle a variety of
common tasks that you will use regularly in your day-to-day Python programming.
User-defined functions, on the other hand,
are those that you create to preform
specific tasks that are not covered by Python's built-in functions.
These are functions you,
as the programmer, create to perform specific tasks.
They allow you to define steps tailored to your specific needs,
so you aren't limited to the built-in functions Python provides alone.
This way, you can reuse your own code whenever needed,
saving time and keeping things organized.
You define these functions using the def keyword like this.
In this user-defined function,
we write our own custom function called say_hi.
That will do exactly that.
Print the phrase we define.
"Hi there", with a return statement.
Defining a function like this allows us to reuse the code anytime we need a greeting,
without having to retype the print statement over and over again.
We can just do this,
and it will remember the print statement and any logic we add to our functions.
User-defined functions work really well for
executing a block of code all at once after being called.
But what if we need to handle a large amount of data or sequences one step at a time?
You might think that we could write a normal function,
but there is another more efficient way to
handle big datasets and sequences called generators.
Generators are a special type of function in Python,
similarly to regular functions,
but using the yield keyword instead of return.
They produce items one at a time and only when asked,
making the memory efficient for handling large amounts of data.
Imagine that your restaurant, you're baking cookies.
Over the course of the day,
you might bake hundreds or even thousands of cookies.
If you bake 1,000 cookies at once,
you might have cookies getting cold or still if they're left out all day long.
You don't need to bake all of the cookies at once.
Instead, you can produce a batch of cookies,
serve them, then bake the next batch when it's needed, and so on.
Generator functions operate in a very similar way to this cooking baking example.
They yield one item at a time,
pausing until the next item is requested.
This makes them incredibly useful when dealing with
large sequences of data or when you don't need everything at once.
They can be difficult to grasp at first.
But do not worry once you see an example in action,
it will make a whole lot more sense.
Let's take a look at functions,
and we'll look at a simple example of generators for context.
We can define a function with a few elements.
We'll start with a def keyword,
def, a function name, which in this case,
is count_up_to, and we can pass in
arguments such as Max to set an upper limit to count_up_to.
We can then use the yield keyword instead of return to produce values one at a time,
pausing the function while keeping its state or
memory of where it lasts was in the generation process after each yield.
Often generators will include a loop like while or
for to repeatedly yield values until a condition is met,
like reaching our upper limit.
We'll then create a generator object like this counter equals count_up_to 3.
Which doesn't run the function right away,
but returns a special generator object that
we can iterate over to get values one at a time.
To use our generator, we'll use next,
which retrieves the next value each time next is called on the generator object,
continuing until the generator is exhausted.
We'll execute the cell block,
and then each run will print outputs like this.
Once we run print next counter,
we then get one.
We'll run this again, and we'll get two.
We'll run this one more time. We'll get three.
We'll run this once more,
and then we'll get a stop iteration error.
Once the limit is reached,
which is defined as three in our function here,
our generator is told to go up to and include the max, which is three.
Then we cannot run the generator, again.
What makes a function a function in a generator generator?
Let's dive into the differences of each.
Then what makes them similar.