Functions use return to output a single result,
execute all at once when called.
Store all data and memory at once,
can be memory intensive with large datasets.
Typically use for one time calculations for single actions
and do not retain state between calls as each call is independent.
Generators, on the other hand,
use yield to produce a sequence of results one at a time.
Execute in a pause state, resuming,
where it left off are memory efficient,
especially for handling large datasets,
are ideal for processing data in chunks or streams and retain state between yields,
picking up where it left off with each next call.
The things they both have in common are they both are defined using the dev keyword.
They're reusable for repeated tasks.
They can take parameters.
They can be looped over specifically generators with next and functions with loops
inside and are used to break down complex tasks into manageable steps.
If this still feels a bit complicated,
do not worry at all.
We'll dive into some demo examples,
so you can see exactly what we're working with here.