User defined functions are well defined by you.
This means that we can write almost anything that we can imagine to accomplish our goals.
Let's say that we want to print a greeting to a user and say,
Hello World, every time a certain function runs.
Python does not come pre installed with a function to do this,
but it does come with pre installed abilities for us to write a function to do this.
We will do this by writing a function called
greet that will then print the message Hello World.
This combines the use of the built in
function print inside of our user defined function called greet.
Let's test this out by writing it.
We'll write def greet,
and then we'll say print Hello World.
We'll end quote there and then we'll end the print C. When we run this function,
we should see our message that looks like this.
We'll define this function and we'll call it.
Just like that, we see our message Hello World.
But this is impersonal and generic.
If we wanted to make this more customized and dynamic to the user,
how can we update our user defined
greet function to greet an actual user with their name?
If you remember from earlier,
functions allow us to pass in an optional input,
which could be one or more values that we can use to customize how our functions run.
We can pass in a name value into our function in order to make a customized greeting.
Let's see how to do that here.
We'll take our base of our greet function.
We'll pop open a new cell,
and we'll say def greet input.
Then we'll pass in name as an input,
we'll say return, and then we'll return in F string,
and we'll say hello,
and then in curly brackets,
name exclamation point, and then closed quotation marks.
Then we'll call our function, greet input.
Then we'll pass in Python coder.
Now, because we are using an F string to
define a string with a dynamic input of the name value,
can you guess what the output of this will be?
Let's run this and find out.
You should see hello Python coder,
and that's because we pass this in as an input into our input function,
which passes that into this output. Pretty cool, right?