Now let's talk about generators.
If you remember our cookie baking example from earlier,
in our busy bakery,
we will receive multiple orders for cookies,
but we don't want to bake thousands of cookies all at once.
That would not be efficient,
and lots of cookies would be left out waiting around and not ready to be eaten by anyone.
Generators are ideal for this type of task as they let you yield one batch at a time,
pausing and resuming as needed.
This helps you save memory and
ensures that you're only producing cookies as you need them.
Let's see how to use generators to yield a limited number of batches,
such as if you know the exact number of orders to make in a given day,
and how to yield batches indefinitely if you want to just make
cookies in a batch each time you need
to while tracking how many cookies you've generated.
Let's define a generator function for baking cookies.
We'll use yield instead of return,
allowing the function to pause and
continue baking whenever we're ready for the next batch.
Our bake cookies function will take in a batch size and
also have an optional limit of max batches to make,
but the default if it's not defined is none.
Then we'll set the batch count and total cookies each to zero as we start the generator.
If the max batches is provided as a parameter input when it's not set as none,
the generator will stop when it reaches the limit,
which we define with our while loop logic.
We'll then increment by counting upwards where the batch count increments by one.
This allows the function to pause and
continue baking whenever you're ready for the next batch.
First, we'll define our function bake cookies with def bake_cookies,
and then we'll pass in a batch_size,
and max_batches equals None as the default.
We'll set colon, and then we'll say batch_count = 0 and total_cookies = 0.
Then while max_batches is None or batch_count is less
than max_batches will increment total cookies, with += batch_size.
Then we'll yield total_cookies,
and then we'll increment batch_count by += 1.
If we know in advance how many batches we need,
we can set a limit to curb how many cookies get made.
Imagine if you had a limited number of resources in
the kitchen and you knew you could make 300 cookies in a day,
but not a cookie more.
Or perhaps your budget only allows for
a certain number of cookies to be made before you start losing money.
You could set a limit to prevent an overage with an upper bound.
For example, let's bake cookies and batches of 100,
stopping after three batches,
so we can only make 300 cookies.
If this was a regular function and we wanted to run this all at once,
we could do something like this where we set our batch size as
the first parameter of 100 and the max batches with a none,
none value of three.
Then we write a for loop that will run our generator object three times and then stop.
What we'll do is that we will say limited_cookie_batches = bake_cookies.
We'll use our function from up here,
and then we'll say 100,
to set the batch size and then max_batches = 3.
Then four cookies in limited_cookie_batches. We'll say print.
We'll do our f string and we'll say
baked , cookies in total.
We'll close out the f string,
close up the print statement, and then first,
we will execute this function to make sure that it's saved in the kernel,
and then we will execute this.
What do you think the output will be when we run this?
Let's find out and run this.
We'll see that the output will be baked 100 cookies in total,
baked 200 cookies in total,
and then baked 300 cookies in total, and then stopped.
However, this is making all of our cookies at once.
How do we make this into a generator and unlock the magic of incremental baking?
What we will need to do instead is re-initialize our function or
rerun the function in our Jupyter Notebook and then re-initialize our generator object.
What we're going to do is that we're going to write
limited_cookie_batches = bake_cookies 100.
Then we're going to say max_batches is three.
We will rerun this function.
We will then rerun this new cell.
Can you guess what the output will be when we run this?
When we use our built-in function next to increment over
time up until our 100*3 upper bound of 300 cookies,
the first run we're going to do is we're going to say next(limited_cookie_batches).
We'll run this code,
and we'll see that it ran 100.
Then we'll do this again,
and the output is 200.
We'll run this once more,
and then the output is 300.
Then we'll try to run this again,
and we get a stop iteration error.
Here, as we defined above,
the max_batches = 3 ensures that the generator stops after 300 cookies, which it does.
The three batches is defined through that because each batch is 100 cookies,
and we are only doing this three times,
so 100*3 is 300.