Which makes sense up there.
This is like fulfilling a small order where you know exactly how many cookies you need.
Sometimes however, you may not know how many batches of cookies you'll need to bake.
Maybe orders keep coming in throughout the day,
and you just need to keep baking,
but keep track of how many cookies you're baking.
In this case, you can skip specifying a limit,
allowing the generator to run indefinitely.
This time, we'll initialize a new generator object that has a batch size of 100,
but no Max batches parameter as the input like this,
which you'll see right here, unlimited_cookie_batches = bake_cookies(100).
This will allow us to run this generator function as many times
as we'd like to. We'll initialize this.
Then every time we run the generator on this new generator object,
we get outputs that count upwards beyond 300.
For example, taking the unlimited_cookie_batches with next,
we'll run the cell, and we see 100.
Next, we see 200, next, we see 300,
and now we see past 300,
400, 500, and so on.
With no limit. You control when to stop by simply deciding when to
stop calling the next function on our unlimited_cookie_batches generator object.
This is useful if you want to keep the bakery
running until you decide to close shop for the day.
Let's quickly review what we learned about functions and generators.
Functions are versatile tools that allow us
to execute a block of code with a specific purpose.
They can take in parameters,
perform actions, and return a result.
Functions are great for performing one off tasks or calculations all at once.
However, they return a single result and
don't retain any state after they finish executing.
Some examples can be built-in functions that Python all ready comes preloaded with,
or we can write our own self defined functions to handle our own custom logic.
Generators, on the other hand,
are a special type of function that lets you control
the flow of production in a more gradual way.
By using yield instead of return,
generators produce values one at a time,
pausing between each until they're needed again.
This is like baking cookies in batches.
You only bake what you need when you need it, which saves resources.
Generators are ideal for handling
large sequences or ongoing tasks without overloading memory.
Instead of holding all the data at once,
they create each piece as requested.
This is incredibly useful for scenarios where you might not know
the total size of the data or want to process it in chunks.
In summary, functions are great for one off or repeatable execution of the same code,
while generators give you flexibility and efficiency,
yielding items on demand.
This makes them perfect for tasks where you want to manage resources carefully and work
with large or continuous data streams one manageable batch at a time.