We just learned about the return keyword in the last lesson on functions.
But let's dive into
a bit more detail about what it does and what it's used for in Python.
The return keyword allows a function to send
back a result after processing some Python code.
Think of it as getting a finished product from an assembly line.
Once the steps are complete,
it's sent back ready for further use or consumption.
Let's see some examples of how the return statement works and how we can write
code that ensures we know what will be returned each time our code runs.
Let's talk about the return keyword.
For example, let's say we have a function that adds two numbers together.
By using return, we can send back the result of that addition,
which then can be used elsewhere in our code.
Here, we're going to write an add function that
completes its task and sends back the sum of a and b,
which we then store in the result variable for further use.
We'll do this by declaring def add(a,
b): return a + b.
Now, result is set to add (3, 5).
When we print result,
can you guess what the output is going to be?
If you said eight, you're right,
because 5, 6, 7, 8,
so 5 + 3 is 8,
which makes sense and that means that we wrote our add function correctly.
But be careful though,
because the return value will literally
return what you tell it to. What do I mean by this?
Well, let's say that you have this add function and you mistakenly put in add(3,
'Python') in which case you added a number and a string together.
This would look something like this.
If you were to do this, you might think that this would create (3,
'Python'), but can you guess what this will create instead? Let's find out.
This will create a type error,
and it'll say unsupported operand types for integer and string when we add them together.
When you're working on a team,
a great convention to practice is defining the types of the inputs so that it's very
clear what goes in the parameters and what comes out via the return statement,
or yield if you're writing a generator function.
We would define our parameters with the colon and then the data type,
which in this case, we want whole number integers. Let's do that right now.
We'll take our function from earlier,
and we will say (a: int, b: int).
We can also enter our inputs like this so
that we can see our parameters a little bit more
clearly in case this is a little bit easier for you to see.
This will work and this will also work together.
What if we wanted to combine strings together
rather than integers like in a greeting to someone?
How do we do this? We do this in a very similar way to the last function,
but instead of int, we're using string.
We're going to write a function to greet someone and we can
customize the greeting by passing in two parameters.
The first as a greeting,
and the second as the name.
We'll use an f string to combine these together
into a single string. Let's do that right now.
We'll say, def say_greeting(greeting
: str,
name: str): and we'll say return,
and we'll write an f string,
and we'll do squiggly brackets for greeting and then we'll do squiggly brackets for name.
We'll then use an exclamation point and we'll close out our f statement.
Next, we'll set a variable called greeting_result,
and we'll set that equal to say_greeting and we'll pass in
"Howdy" as the first argument and "Python Coder", as the second argument.
Now we'll print greeting result.
Can you guess what this output will be?
Let's run this code and find out.
If you said, Howdy, Python Coder, you're right,
because that's what we see when we run this code and this is the output.
The colon data type, such as this,
or this or this or this
helps us identify what the inputs to the function are so that we can
get a sense of how they will be used for the output. Great work.