In Python, if a function doesn't explicitly return a value,
it automatically returns none.
This is Python's way of saying,
I have no output for you and is especially useful
when a function is meant to perform an action without needing to give anything back.
If you remember from our generator example was baking cookies,
we actually used none to create a default value of nothing for a parameter.
If we use this function and don't pass in a second parameter for baked cookies,
like baked cookies 100,
it will make batches of 100 cookies every time it runs,
but could be invoked forever.
That's because the function expects to have two inputs,
but we can use the none keyword to stand in place as a value of nothing.
Let's see some examples of the none keyword in action.
Now let's talk about the none keyword.
If you create a function that performs a simple task like printing a message,
but doesn't need to return a result,
it will implicitly return none.
To see an example of this, we're going to write a function called no return value,
and what's interesting is that we're going to have the function print a statement,
but we will not include a return keyword.
Let's see how to do this. We'll say def no_return_value,
and then we'll say print("This function does not return anything at all").
We'll end the quote, and then close out the print statement.
Now, result is going to equal no_return_value(),
and then we're going to print the result.
Can you guess what the output is going to be?
Let's run it and find out.
When we run this, when the function runs,
it will print to the console the phrase,
this function does not return anything at all!.
But if we make set a variable of
result equal to the value of what the function returns when it runs,
the value of the result itself is none.
Let's see a more practical example of the none value being used in an everyday scenario,
like finding items in your refrigerator.
If you have a smart refrigerator,
you might want to be able to look up if an item is in there or not.
If there is an item found,
we want to have our Python code let us know.
Otherwise, we would not want to return anything.
First, we'll define a list of items that are in our smart refrigerator,
and then we'll make our own function called find item that takes in
a target that we want to find if it's in there.
Our for loop of item in items will iterate over the list of fruits,
and if our target is found in the list,
it will return a statement that says found XYZ.
Otherwise, if the target isn't found in the list of items,
then we return nothing with return none. Let's do that right now.
First, we'll define our list of items, which is an apple,
banana, and a cherry as a few fruits,
then we're going to write a function.
We'll say def find_item, and we'll say target.
That will be the value that we check inside of this function,
and then we're going to say for item in items for our for loop construction,
we'll say if item == target:, return,
and then we'll print an F string and we'll say Found
:  and target will be in squiggly braces,
and then we'll put an exclamation point, and then we'll close that out.
Now, on the same level of the for loop,
we'll return none,
and that will be if the loop completes without finding the item,
then none will be returned.
Otherwise, we'll return found with that item.
We'll execute this code to save this function to our notebook.
Then if we do find item,
and let's say that we look for banana,
and we execute this, what do you think the output will be here?
Let's run it and find out.
We'll see 'Found: banana!'
and that makes sense because banana is in our list of items.
However, if we were to run this same exact code except to switch out banana for orange,
what do you think the output is going to be now?
There is actually no response at all
since orange is nowhere to be found in our list of items,
since there's only apple, banana, and cherry.
To confirm this, we can set a variable of result to the orange look up.
What we'll do is we'll say result = find_item,
and then we'll put in orange,
and then we'll print result.
Can you guess what the output of this will be?
We'll see none, and if you said none, you're right,
and this is because orange is not in our smart refrigerator.
The for loop checks over all the items,
does not find it, and then returns none,
and that's exactly what happens here, because again,
banana is in our list of items,
but orange is not. Great work.