Before we get started,
let's take a step back and look at the big picture of
what machine learning is and how aggression fits into it.
You might have heard of machine learning as it's currently a really hot topic,
but the truth is that it isn't really new.
It's just a new way to package things that have actually existed for a really long time.
Two primary branches of machine learning are called
supervised learning and unsupervised learning.
Supervised learning is where we use input data to predict a label for that data.
Examples of this type of machine learning are using
credit card transaction data to predict fraudulent transactions,
or using customer financial data to predict the chance of a default on a loan,
or using neighborhood characteristics to predict home prices.
Another large branch of machine learning is known as unsupervised machine learning.
In this type of machine learning,
you're clustering together data based on common characteristics.
These data don't have labels like in supervised machine learning techniques.
Common unsupervised problems include trying to group similar customer segments,
or group documents that cover similar topics.
There are other machine learning approaches but these are the two main branches.
And as it turns out,
linear and logistic regression fall into the supervised machine learning branch.