In this lesson, you'll be learning about confidence intervals.
When we try to estimate a population parameter based on a sample statistic,
this is like fishing with a fishing pole.
And there's nothing wrong with fishing this way.
It's a perfectly good way to fish.
However, you'd be much more likely to catch a fish if you cast an entire net.
How much more likely are you that you'll catch a fish?
Well, that depends on the size of the net.
The larger the net, the more confident you can be that you'll actually capture a fish.
This net is much more likely to catch a fish than the smaller net.
Though this example isn't exactly the same as building a confidence interval,
because we consider a parameter to be
a non-moving number and not a moving fish amongst water.
This idea that providing an interval and not just a single estimate will help us
gain confidence in our ability to capture
a population parameter is at the core of confidence intervals.
And the wider our interval,
the more confident we can be that we capture our parameter of interest.
Let's take a closer look.