Pandas is a powerful tool for data analysis and manipulation.
One of the most popular formats used to store data is CSV or comma-separated values.
We can load CSV files into data frames using the read.csv() function.
Let's load Google stock data into a data frame.
This file was taken from Yahoo Finances and contains Google stock data from August 19th,
2004 to October 13th, 2017.
The data frame consists of 3,313 rows and seven columns.
Let's look at the stock data.
We can see it's a pretty large dataset and that
pandas automatically assign numerical row indices to the data frame.
Pandas also used the names that appeared in the CSV file to assign the column labels.
When dealing with large datasets like this one,
it's often useful to just take a look at
the first few rows of data instead of the whole dataset.
We can take a look at the first five rows using the HEAD method.
We can also take a look at the last five rows of data using the TAIL method.
Both of these accept an integer as an argument
if you want to specify a different number of rows to return.
For example, I can get the last eight rows like this or the first two rows like this.
Let's do a quick check to see whether we have any non-values in this data set.
To do so, we will use the ISNULL() method followed by
the any() method to check whether any of the columns contain non-values.
This shows us that we have no missing data.
When dealing with large datasets,
it's often useful to get statistical information from them.
Pandas provides a described method which returns
descriptive statistics on each column of the data frame.
We can access elements in a data frame in different ways.
In general, we can access rows, columns,
or individual elements by using the row and column labels.
Let's see some examples.
We can access the bikes column using the column label like
this and use a list of the column labels to access multiple columns.
We can access a row using
the row index label and the value at a specific row and column like this.
It's important to know that when accessing individual elements in a data frame,
like in this last example,
the column label always comes first and then the row label.
If you provide the row label first, you'll get an error.
We can also modify our data frames by adding rows or columns.
Suppose we decided to add a shirts column to our data frame.
To do this, we can define a shirts column containing
the quantity for each of the two store rows like this.
This added a new column to the end of our data frame.
We can also add new columns using
arithmetic operations on other columns of our data frame.
For example, we can create a new column called
suits by computing the sum of the shirts and pants column.