The way we've been building confidence intervals thus far is
based on bootstrapping and our knowledge of sampling distributions.
This is an extremely effective method for building
confidence intervals for essentially any parameters we might be interested in.
However, if you've taken a statistics course elsewhere,
you might be confused as to why
this notation is different than what you've done in those other courses.
You might have seen equations like these for capturing a population mean or proportion.
Similarly, you might have seen equations like these for
capturing the difference in means or the difference in proportions.
All of these formulas have underlying assumptions that may or may not be true.
If you truly believe that your data are representative of your population of interest,
the bootstrapping method should provide
a better representation for where the parameter is likely to be.
However, with large enough sample sizes,
these formulas should provide
very similar results to those that we've seen in bootstrapping methods.
In the next concept, we'll take a look at a few examples.