Here we'll work together through the solution for
this simulating from the null hypothesis notebook.
This first part, we're just reading in our data and importing some of our libraries,
and then the very first question,
we're supposed to set up the correct null and alternative hypothesis.
Let's look at the wording associated with this question
and see what indicates why the null and alternative would look like this.
In general, it says, what if you're interested in studying whether the average height for
coffee drinkers is the same as for non-coffee drinkers?
In this case, there's no indication that you
care about which direction the heights might go.
You don't say anything about,
we think that coffee drinkers will be
taller or we think that coffee drinkers will be shorter.
We just say, are they the same?
Because of this, the test that we want to do is a not equal to test.
This says that the average for the coffee drinkers
versus the average for the non-coffee drinkers is not equal to zero,
is our alternative, and our null is basically the opposite of that, so it's equal to.
In general, the null always has this equal to portion and
the alternative has either the not equal to or greater than or less than portion.
In this case, because there's no indication of direction,
we would just use a not equal to alternative.
In the second case, it's worded a little bit different,
so if you're interested in studying whether the average height
for coffee drinkers is less than for non-coffee drinkers.
Remember, the thing that you want to test or the indication of
the direction you want to test should show up in the alternative hypothesis.
This says that the average height for coffee drinkers
minus the average height for non-coffee drinkers is less than zero.
We believe that this number should be less than the non-coffee drinkers.
That indicates that the less than should be pointed this direction,
and basically then again,
the null is the opposite side with the equal sign associated with it.
Sometimes you'll just see equal to here and then less than,
and that would also be okay.
The main thing is that the alternative is set up in this direction.
If you set up these subtracted
the opposite direction and then you put a greater than on this side,
that would also be okay.
Those alternative hypotheses are equivalent.
With that, the rest of this is like,
how would we use data to test these sets of hypotheses?
The first thing that we do here is basically very similar to
a lot of the examples we've seen with the sampling method.
You can imagine what we do is we have some large number of iterations.
What we're doing is we're keeping track of
the average height for the non-coffee drinkers,
the average height for the coffee drinkers,
and then basically the difference between these two heights.
The first part here is just basically saying we're going to replace equals true,
we're going to sample 200 times from the original data set that we have.
If we actually look at this ahead of time,
we have this dataset.
Basically, what we're going to do is we're going to randomly choose
200 rows from this dataset with replacement,
and that's going to go into this Bootstrap sample placeholder,
and then basically with that Bootstrap sample,
we're going to look at the average height for those who drink coffee.
We have this drink_coffee column.
This is someone's height for someone who drinks coffee,
and so you could say, if they drink coffee, what's their average height?
If they don't drink coffee in this sample, what's their average height?
Then basically we can append each of these things.
We can append the average height of the coffee drinkers into this list,
the non-coffee drinkers into this list,
and then the difference between
the coffee drinkers and the non-coffee drinkers into this final list.
Basically, I would also recommend setting up this part to be
consistent with however you set up your null and alternative hypothesis.
In our case, we had coffee minus non-coffee,
and so that suggests this way.
If you set it up the other way,
you'd probably want to just make sure that
you calculate the differences in the opposite direction.
There isn't a right or wrong,
it just should be consistent with your null and alternative.
This might take a little while to run.
We are running 10,000 iterations.
But once it completes,
we're going to look at a bunch of statistics
associated with each of these different groups.
The standard deviation for the non-coffee drinkers is here.
The standard deviation for the coffee drinkers is here.
The standard deviation associated with the difference between the two is here.
What we're doing here is actually looking at the sampling distributions
associated with the average for the non-coffee drinkers versus the coffee drinkers.
Again, this Alpha just makes it a little bit more see-through.
If we wanted to, we could add labels to this.
We could do label equals non-coffee,
and then we could add another label down here to this one,
and so we could do label equals coffee.
Then we could add a legend to this.
You can see the non-coffee drinkers' average heights are here.
The coffee drinkers' average heights are here.
Let's make sure that we got that set up.
That all looks good. Basically,
from here, whether it's stat sig or not is hard to tell,
but you can definitely see there's some separation between these groups,
and it definitely looks like the coffee drinkers are a little bit taller on average.
Then this last part is just looking at the differences.
You can see there's a little bit of
a tail over zero which might suggest there isn't a difference.
It just depends on how many samples are in this tail.
Then overall, the distribution is fairly normal.
The central limit theorem probably gave us that,
especially with a sample size as large as 200.
We have a pretty good idea of what
this sampling distribution for the difference looks like.
The next thing that we might want to do in this last part is basically say,
well, what would this look like under the null?
Well, under the null, we basically are saying there is no difference.
Basically, it should be this distribution,
but instead of centered here on some non-zero difference,
it should be centered on zero.
What we can do is we can say draw from a normal distribution,
because that's what we know should be true under the null hypothesis,
again, following the central limit theorem.
Use the standard deviation of your sampling distribution for the differences,
and we can do that 10,000 times too.
We look at this distribution,
you can see basically, here's what we think is true under the null hypothesis,
and we might even plot this difference on top of it.
We could do Alpha equals 0.05 here.
0.5 here.
Again, this could be null_true as my label.
This one it's label
equals actual_data or something like that.
Then again, we could add a legend to look at this.
The differences from my actual data are here,
and the differences from my null hypothesis are this blue version.
Then the question is basically,
do we think this is statistically significant?
One of the things that we could do is we could ask what proportion of
our values under the truth fall below this zero or not.
Let's just pull this second part.
Again, here's the distribution of the truth and we could say,
imagine we want vertical V line at zero.
Something like that. We could change the color so that it stands out a little better.
But the idea is this line represents where
the null hypothesis thinks this should be. Put this part at the top.
This red line thinks this is where the null hypothesis should be,
and here's where our distribution is at.
Then to get some value for how unlikely these things are,
we could just ask what proportion of diffs, so diffs.
Diffs are all of
our simulated differences between the coffee drinkers and the non-coffee drinkers.
We'd say of the diffs,
how many of them are less than zero.
I'm going to make this NumPy array in order to do this.
It doesn't let you do it with list,
so we'll change this to an array.
Otherwise, everything else should stay the same.
NumPy actually supports this pretty well.
Here's all the ones that are basically down here in this tail,
and we could look at how many of them there
are and divide that by the length of all of our diffs.
I would say only 0.3% of my values are down here in the tail.
All the rest of them actually are above zero,
suggesting maybe the coffee drinkers are taller.
Hopefully this gives you a good idea of what we are looking for in the solution,
and we will definitely be exploring these concepts more in the pages ahead.