In the last video,
we saw that a p-value is the probability of obtaining
our data or more extreme values from the null hypothesis.
So how does this connect to making decisions and the types of errors that we can make?
If the p-value is really small,
this suggests it's less likely to observe our statistic from the null.
And it's more likely that it came from the alternative.
But how small does the p-value need to be
before we no longer stay with the null hypothesis?
Well, I guess that depends on how willing you are to make certain types of errors.
If you are willing to commit five percent of errors,
where you choose the alternative incorrectly,
then your p-value needs to be smaller than
this threshold in order to choose the alternative.
However, if your probability of getting the data from the null is, say,
an eight percent chance,
this is enough of a chance that you would stay with
the null under a five percent type one error threshold.
The fast rule is that if our p-value is less than a type one error rate,
then professionals say we reject the null.
That is, we choose the alternative hypothesis.
If the p-value is greater than our type one error rate,
then we fail to reject the null.
That is, we stay with the null hypothesis as our decision.
What's actually true?
We can't really be sure in practice,
but we now have a database way to make our decisions.