Here we are going to go through the solution for this calculating errors notebook.
The first thing that we're going to do is just read in our Q data sets here,
and we can take a look at each of those.
You can see the judicial data set has a bunch of defendants,
and then whether they're truly innocent
or guilty and then our prediction of whether they're innocent or guilty.
Then this parachute one is very similar.
Each row as a parachute and then whether it actually opens,
and then whether we predict it opens.
This first part is just to look at different proportions of our types of errors.
First, we are looking at the proportion of errors in the judicial data set.
An error happens anytime that the actual column,
this actual column in either of these,
but here we're looking at the judicial data set,
anytime this actual column,
the value doesn't match the predicted column,
we are going to count that.
Basically what this says is,
go through and look at the actual column,
compare that to the predicted,
and then this exclamation point equals as a not equal to.
It says, look at when the actual doesn't equal the predicted,
and then this shape zero just says, count the rows.
Shape gives back the rows and the columns,
and then this zero is just grabbing back the row part.
Similarly, this is just saying,
grab all the rows in the judicial data set to get the proportion.
We could break this out a little bit if we want to see each of the parts,
but the idea is that this first part is just finding all of the errors,
so this is anytime the actual doesn't match the predicted.
Here we see a bunch of guilty matched with innocent,
but it also could be innocent matched with guilty,
and those would show up here too.
Then the shape gives back the number
of rows where that happens and the number of columns, which we can see as three.
There's the defendant, the actual and the predicted columns.
The zero is just grabbing back the number of rows.
This is the total number of rows where these two things don't match,
and then similarly with this jud_data.shape,
this is the total number of rows in the data set,
and this is the total number of columns,
and so the zero is just grabbing back the number of rows.
This is saying the total number of rows where these don't
match over the total number of rows in the data set is the total number of errors.
We can see that that happens about 4% of the time.
Similarly, if we want to look at each different type of error,
one set is where the innocent is the truth and we predict they're guilty,
and the other is when they're truly guilty and we predict they're innocent.
The first one is a Type 1 error,
and the second one is a Type 2 error.
Here, this count is basically doing the same thing as shape.
It's a little different in that,
if there were null values,
the count would not count those.
Whereas, if there were null values,
the shape would count them.
Sometimes it can be useful to use count instead of shape,
but in general, they're doing the same thing.
We could go back to shape here,
and these would give the same answer.
Here you can see that,
or if we use count,
this is just another way to do this,
they give the exact same answer.
But it just depends on if there's null values in your data set. We could check.
If we wanted to, we could look at jud_data and then do isnull and sum.
You can see there's no null values in this data set at all,
so whether you shape or count, it doesn't really matter.
Then this is the total number of Type 1 errors we make, and then similarly,
if we're just matching the actual as guilty and the predicted as innocent,
then that's our Type 2 error rate.
You can see that's quite a bit higher here.
In general, this query method is really useful for any and,
or or logic that you might want to do.
You could say, is guilty versus
predicted guilty or you can use or statements, you type in or.
But this query method is really useful.
You just wrap your logic in a string and pass it into it.
I really like this query method.
Hopefully you can make use of it in lots of situations you might find yourself in.
Then a question is, if everyone was predicted to be guilty,
then every actual innocent person would be a Type 1 error.
Basically, this situation where we want to
know the total possible Type 1 error rate, which is basically like,
we predict everyone to be guilty is basically just like,
well, all the innocent people would be calculated wrong.
This is looking at that proportion.
Basically, this is the highest possible Type 1 error rate we could commit.
The fact that we're only committing a 0.0015 rate,
when the total possible Type 1 errors that we could commit is about 45%,
this the total number of innocent people that we could get wrong,
seems like we're doing pretty good.
Then the next part is,
if everyone was predicted to be guilty,
then what's the total Type 2 errors?
Basically, if everyone is predicted to be guilty,
we'll never commit a Type 2 error.
Because if everyone is predicted to be guilty,
then all of the guilty people are marked correctly.
Never will there be an error in that case.
Great. This next part is just doing the same thing,
but with the parachute data,
you can see it's very similar logic.
We're matching whether these are equal.
Also note, this could also be done with the query method if we wanted to.
It would look very similar to this down here.
You would put the actual in a string and you'd say,
actual doesn't equal predicted.
In any case, we can use
the same logic as up here and calculate the Type 1 and Type 2 error rates.
Here it's just noting that the Type 1 error is,
if we say it opens,
and it actually doesn't,
and a Type 2 error is saying that it doesn't open,
but it actually does.
Similarly, if every parachute is predicted to fail,
what's the total number of Type 1 errors? There wouldn't be any.
But if all of them are predicted to fail,
basically everyone that truly opens would be a Type 2 error,
and so we can calculate that here.
Basically anytime that the actual isn't open,
that would be a Type 2 error if we just said, hey, none of them work.
It probably wouldn't be a good way to run your business,
because you would never hand out a parachute then,
in which case, if you were a sky diving company,
it would basically just mean that no one would
ever jump because you would just say they're all failures.
Don't give anybody any of them.
Hopefully, this is a really good example of these Type 1 and Type 2 errors,
and it shows you a little bit of the code that you can use to
determine these different errors and how you can calculate them directly in Python.