Let&#39;s say you&#39;ve just finished running an experiment,
where you send out a promotional coupon to
a mailing list in order to see if it drives up sales in your online store.
Going through the statistical analysis,
you find that there is a statistically significant effect.
People who received the coupon were five percent more
likely to make purchases than those that did not.
Does this mean that we should send out the coupon on a broader scale?
Not necessarily.
If the cost of sending out the coupon and reduced revenue
from the coupon outweigh the revenue that was gained without it,
then it doesn&#39;t make sense to use the coupon on a broad scale.
This is an example of the importance of considering practical significance.
Practical significance refers to the level of effect that you want to see in
your experiment in order for it to make sense
for your manipulations to actually be implemented.
As suggested by the example,
simply because your experiment is statistically significant,
does not necessarily mean that it&#39;s also
practically significant and worth following through.