So you saw earlier that hypothesis tests and confidence intervals are pretty similar.
But you might be surprised just how similar these two techniques are.
It turns out that if you are to do
a hypothesis test that contains a not equal in alternative hypothesis,
your conclusions are identical to a confidence interval,
as long as 100 minus your confidence interval level
is the same as the type one error rate in your hypothesis test.
That is, if you build a 95 percent confidence interval,
this is the same as doing
a two-sided hypothesis test with a five percent type one error rate,
and building a 99 percent confidence interval will provide
the same results as a hypothesis test with a one percent type one error rate.
With this in mind, many academic journals are moving away
from hypothesis tests as they find the results are often misinterpreted.
Instead, more and more confidence intervals and
other statistics like effect size or machine learning techniques are being used.
There is more information on effect sizes as well as
a link to a free course in the Udacity Nanodegree,
link in instructor notes below.