Hopefully, you're starting to feel more comfortable
identifying hypotheses and the types of errors that you can make.
In this video, we'll go through one more example to iterate on these ideas.
This example is one that really helped me connect
all the dots of hypotheses testing and type I and type II errors.
I hope it does the same for you.
Imagine you own a skydiving shop.
And as a part of your job,
you must check parachutes to assure they worked correctly.
There are two potential outcomes,
either a parachute works or it doesn't.
You can create these as our two potential hypotheses.
You know that there are four potential outcomes for each skydiver-parachute combination.
First, you check each parachute to make a decision.
Either the parachute works or it doesn't.
If you determine that it works,
you put it on the shelf for skydivers to use.
If it doesn't, you throw it out.
Now, there are two possible truths,
either the parachute actually works or it doesn't.
For the parachute that we threw out, if it doesn't work,
that's great, but if it did,
then we probably lost like 30 bucks.
Now, for the parachute we put on the shelf,
if it works, then the skydiver uses it
to jump out of a plane and land safely on the ground.
However, if it doesn't,
we clearly just committed the worst type of error possible.
This should clearly be the type I error in this example.
So, the other type of error is the type II error.
This helps us align our null and alternative hypotheses to look like this.
As we know that type I error rate should be
choosing the alternative when the null is true.
And it helps us align an appropriate type I error rate as
one or five percent as entirely too high.
Committing five or even one of these errors out
of every 100 individuals would just be unacceptable.