Once we set up our null and alternative hypotheses,
we need used data to figure out
which hypothesis we actually think is more likely to be true.
And there are two ways we might approach choosing one of these hypotheses.
One is the approach that we saw using confidence intervals,
where we simulate the sampling distribution of our statistic,
and then we could see if our hypothesis is
consistent with what we observe in the sampling distribution.
The second way we could approach choosing
a hypothesis is simulating what we believe to be
possible under the null and then seeing if our data is actually consistent with that.
This is what professionals tend to do in a hypothesis testing.