When solving data problems,
you likely do many complex things.
But at the end of the day,
you want to give your audience what they need to make your results actionable.
Here are a couple of tips for showing off your results.
First, know your audience.
If you're too technical with your presentation when your audience is non-technical,
you'll lose that audience.
This won't lead to a great experience for them or you.
Second, use pictures where possible.
Often a graphic can display an idea better than words or numbers.
When I'm presenting my work to my colleagues who
work with data all day and who are very technical,
I might present code, formulas,
and rough sketches of ideas in a document or Jupyter Notebook.
Alternatively, if I'm meeting with product managers
and designers or presenting to the company executives,
this same topic will likely live in slides with concise, clear ideas.
Plots that clearly show the point of my ideas.
Finally, I would share conclusions and recommendations of how to use the results.
Many times, these conversations are less exploratory and more persuasive in nature.
We should implement this product change
and this is why should come from this conversation.
In the first situation with my data peers,
we might discuss the difficulties and different methods we could use to analyze the data.
We discuss the pros and cons of each method,
but these details aren't necessary for your final stakeholders in most cases.