Sometimes we'll need to know whether an item is in a list or not.
You can use in and not in to check if an item exists in that list.
This is like asking, is apple in my cart or is Sam in the list of students?
These operators allow us the ability to search within
the data collection and let us know if our item of interest is there or not.
Sometimes you just need to do a quick check.
Let's check out an example where in and not in
operators can come in handy for searching through a list to find an item.
For example, let's create an array of fruits again,
where we'll say fruit is our variable name,
and we'll set that equal to a list of apple,
banana, and cherry, which are three different strings.
If we want to check if apple is in our list of fruits,
we could do this fairly easily if there were only three items in the list,
because we can just see that it's there.
And we can also simply count through the items as well.
But what if there were tens or hundreds of items or even thousands?
This could take a huge amount of time to manually check through the list.
This is where we can use our in operator to check
if apple exists within the fruits array.
We'll write an if statement and ask if apple
exists in the fruits list and then print a message.
We'll do this by writing an if statement,
and we'll say if apple in fruits,
then print a string,
and we'll say apple is in the list with an exclamation point,
then we'll close out the quotes,
and then we'll close out the print statement.
What do you think will happen if we run this code?
Let's find out. We do see that it's print out apple is in the list.
Since apple does exist in our fruits list above,
when our code runs, we in fact see the success message printed out,
apple is in the list.
We can also check if something is not in the list with the not in operator.
Let's check if grape is in the fruits array.
We'll define another if statement and ask if grape is not in the fruits list.
Since we've already declared the fruits list above,
we can then write our if statement here.
We can say, if grape,
not in fruits, then print grape is not in the list.
Then we'll close out that print statement.
Can you guess what the output of this cell is going to be?
By running this code, since grape is not in the list,
we see the message of print,
grape is not in the list,
and that's because we only have three items in our fruit list,
which is apple, banana,
and cherry, so grape is not in that.
Now we know a couple of very handy and versatile ways to search
whether certain items are in our lists or not. Great work.