List comprehensions provide a compact way to create lists.
It's a more concise alternative to using a loop to generate a list.
Think of these as automatic list generators where we can
generate values for a list based on a bit of math and computation.
Let's see an example of using list comprehensions to generate
code outputs to be then put into an array.
If we want to make a list of squares similar to what we saw earlier,
this is a math function where we want to put each number to the power of 2,
meaning times the number by itself,
and do that over a series of numbers.
To do this with a list comprehensions inside of the square brackets,
we'll use the exponential operator 2 for x, like this.
We would say, x asterisk asterisk 2.
Then for a series of five times.
We want this exponential process to run.
We'll do this by using our exponential operator component for x
and then use a for loop so that x will only run up to a range of five,
meaning it will only run a total of five times.
We'll do this by writing a variable called squares,
and we'll set that inside of square brackets,
and we'll say x, we'll use our exponential operator,
and then we'll say 2 for x in range five.
Then we'll print the value of squares
to output what this list comprehensions will look like.
What do you think the output of this will be when we execute our code?
When we execute this, we'll see in a list 0,
1, 4,
9, and 16.
What's happening here is creating a list of these operations.
We're taking 0^2,
which is 0, 1^2,
which is 1, 2^2,
which is 4, 3^2, which is 9,
and 4^2, which is 16,
which is how we get those elements inside of our list.
That is what is happening here when we're creating a list of these operations.
But since we are doing this inside of a list of comprehensions,
we have all of these numbers put into our square brackets
automatically as the items are generated and put into the list completely automatically,
thanks to the power of Python.