As we start to build out lists,
there will come times where we need to duplicate the result,
while also preserving the original list as well.
Sometimes when we're working with data and we modify the items inside,
we will want to keep that updated list the way that it is,
but then run an experiment or run some computation on it.
In order to do that in a safe manner,
we will want to copy that list Number 1 into a list Number 2,
and then we can use that list Number 2 for a whole bunch of computations.
Let's say that we update list Number 2,
and then it turns out we made a mistake.
Fortunately, for us, we have a whole backup with list Number 1
that we could copy into a list Number 3 and work with that list now,
all things to the copy function.
Let's say some examples of copying and cloning of lists in action.
In order to see copying and cloning in action,
when we think about list comprehensions,
it's helpful to think first about what happens when you assign one list to another.
When this happens, both lists then refer to the same list in memory.
Here's an example to see what this means.
Let's create two lists first,
one for fruits and one for veggies.
Our fruits list will look like this.
Our veggies list will look like this.
In fruits, we have apple, banana, and cherry,
and then for veggies, we have spinach,
lettuce, and bok choy.
Those are three items that are strings in each list fruits and veggies.
We'll execute this code so that it creates these two lists.
If we were to print veggies,
we'll see the output of spinach,
lettuce, and bok choy.
Now, let's at veggies as fruits and print the value of veggies.
We'll say veggies equal fruits.
Then we'll print veggies.
What do you think the output of veggies will now be when we
execute this code? Let's find out.
If we execute this code, we'll see,
veggies is now apple, banana, and cherry,
and the veggies list has been replaced with what the value of the fruits list is.
Veggies now refers to the list of fruits,
which were those three items we had when we initially created the fruits list,
which is apple, banana, and cherry.
If this was a mistake, we can't undo or go backwards,
The list has now been overwritten and changed forever.
To prevent this from happening,
we can leverage the copy function.
Let's recreate these arrays or lists and
try out our new copy function to see how this can help us.
We will copy the lists of fruits and veggies,
and we will execute this code so that we have these lists.
Now, recreate it,
and to make a copy of our veggies list, we'll do something like this.
We'll say veggies, underscore clone equals veggies dot copy,
and we'll assign the copy function to veggies.
We'll then print veggies clone,
and when we run this,
we can see that it's the same items that are in veggies,
which is spinach, lettuce,
and bok choy, as we see up here.
To give this a bit more context about what cloning is,
cloning doesn't mean it's a link to the reference of the list. What does that mean?
Let's see an example where we add a new item to
the veggies list with our newly learned append utility.
If we do veggies.append,
and let's say we add carrot.
When we print veggies,
we'll now see a new vegetable in the output added at the end.
Now it says spinach,
lettuce, bok choy, and carrot.
However, does this mean that the veggies clone updates to? What do you think?
If we were to print veggies clone,
what do you think the output would be?
Let's find out. We see here that veggies clone is spinach,
lettuce, and bok choy.
If you notice, it's missing the new vegetable
that was added to veggies, which was carrot.
This is because when you take a copy,
the new list is a replicate at that point in time.
If we had said, for example,
veggies clone equals veggies.
Instead of what we had before,
which was veggies under scare clone equals veggies copy,
then veggies clone would have been a reference
to the list and then Carrot would have been included.
But we cloned the veggies list before we added carrot.
That's why the veggies clone didn't include that item.
Another way we can clone a list is with the slice method,
which we just learned about in the previous section.
Let's see how this works.
If we want to make a new list called veggies clone
2 and set that equal to veggies, we would do something like this.
We could say veggies_clone2=veggies.
We'll do a square bracket,
colon, and then end square bracket.
When we print veggies_clone2,
what do you think the output will be?
If we execute this code,
we'll see spinach, lettuce,
bok choy, and carrot.
Notice how this new clone now includes the carrot item in the list at the end.
This is because the new cloned list was
made after this last item was added to the veggies array.
Instead of putting numbers around the semi-colon,
which we have here with
square bracket colon square bracket to limit the start and end of the slice method.
If we leave it like this, it will include everything in the list.
This is a crafty shortcut for making a copy in Python.
Just like that, you've learned two very powerful ways to copy lists in Python. Great job.