As we get more comfortable with lists,
let's expand our idea of what a list can be.
A list can, in fact,
even contain other lists within it.
What will we need to do this for, though?
This allows us to create more complex data structures like matrices,
which are 2D lists,
or cubes, 3D lists.
This is useful for representing grids,
tables, or multi dimensional data.
Now, the goal is not to teach you how to work with matrices,
but it's important to get exposure to this now
so that when you go into further Python work and data engineering work,
you'll be prepared for more advanced types of Python programming.
For example, vector embeddings and
tokenization are very topical to work with machine learning,
while matrices and 3D data structures are quite
relevant to video games and multimedia animations.
In order to see how matrices and cubes work,
let's check this out with an example next.
To see lists within lists a bit more clearly,
let's first code out a 2D matrix,
known as a list of lists.
We'll do this by typing something like this.
We'll say matrix equals and we'll have outside square brackets,
and then inside, we'll have three specific lists.
The first one has 1,2,
and 3 in it.
The second one has 4,5,
and 6 in it, and the third one has 7,8, and 9 in it.
Here we've created our first matrix with three rows and three columns.
When we go to print this, it will look something like this,
which is exactly what we just printed into our matrix.
The output, again, looks exactly like the matrix object definition,
which we've defined at the top.
For a more readable output of the matrix,
we can use a four loop to iterate over each row in
the matrix or each iterable it over the big collection,
and then print each row or iterable it like so.
We'll write four row in matrix, colon print row.
The output now looks like this with three rows and three columns like that.
Now we have our matrix defined,
Let's see what operations we can perform on our matrix.
First, we can try accessing a specific element.
If we want to access the element in the third row second column,
for example, we would use our index locator,
like we have done in the past with brackets over our matrix object.
We can do something like this. We'll say print matrix,
and we'll say 2,1
because it is the third row or the second index,
and then the second column or the first index.
That's how we get eight. Again, that makes sense because it's 1,2,3 row,
and then 1,2 second column.
This is the output of eight exactly as we'd expect.
Second, something we can do is we can access an entire row of a matrix.
To do this, we can use our index locator over
the matrix object and get all of the values for a specific row in the matrix,
like the first row, for example,
which remember is index zero right here.
When we print matrix index zero, we get the first row,
1,2,3, and this prints out exactly what we would
expect the first elements of the first row of the matrix, 1,2,3.
Third, if we want to access multiple rows instead
of printing them all like we just did earlier,
we could use a for loop to make this more
compact and only define the rows we want to include.
For example, let's say we only want to see
the second and third rows. How would we do that?
Well, something that we can do so we can write a for loop and we'll say for row in [1,2].
Then we can say print matrix, and then [row].
Then when we execute this code,
this makes sense because we see 4,5,6,
and 7,8,9 which is exactly what we just define where we want the second and third rows,
which is index 1 and index 2. That makes sense.