Next, if we want to add matrices together that are of the same size,
we can do that as well. Let's see how to do that.
First, let's define our first matrix,
which we'll call matrix A,
and that will have three lists inside of this big list,
which is 1,2,3,4,5,6, and 7,8,9.
Next, we'll define our matrix B,
which is three list items as well,
but we'll have in the first 9,8,7,
second one is 6,5,4,
and the third one is 3,2,1,
so it's the opposite of matrix A.
Then we'll add them together with a for loop adding in
the addition result to an empty result object to hold our new matrix as it's generated.
To do this, first,
we'll define a result matrix,
which we'll declare as an empty array and we'll create a new cell.
We already executed these two matrix lists,
then we'll say result equals empty bracket.
Then we're going to create a four-loop to iterate over each row index.
We'll say four row in range,
and then we'll say len for length,
and we'll say matrix A.
Then the new row array will store the new row after addition happens,
and we'll do this by declaring an empty new row list.
Then we're going to loop over each column index
in the current row as this loop is iterating.
We'll say four, col which will be short for column in range,
and we'll again do the length function.
We'll say len matrix A index zero closeout length function
and then close out range function.
We'll do a colon, and then we're going to add the row and column elements together.
We're going to do that inside of this for loop with column,
and we'll say sum_value = matrix_a.
This will have row,
this will have column,
we're doing the matrix of index row of index column,
and then we're going to say plus,
we're going to copy the same thing except this is going
to be for matrix B of index row of index column.
Then we'll append the result to the new row.
I'll do that by saying new row.append,
and we'll say some value.
Then we'll jump back to the same level as the for loop and we'll append the new row to
the result matrix with result.append(new row).
We'll then print our result and that pretty much rounds out what we'll do.
Can you guess what the output of this operation will be?
Let's run this code and find out.
In the output, we'll see three lists inside of this bigger list,
and we'll have 10, 10, 10,
10, 10, 10, and 10, 10, 10.
This makes sense because we're doing all of these different operations,
so 1+9, 2+8,
3+7, 4+6, and so on,
which you see here, where when we add up these items via the columns,
we have 1+9, 2+8, 3+7, 4+6,
5+5, and so on, all the way down to 6+4,
7+3, 8+2, and 9+1.
That's pretty cool. But this so far has been 2D matrices.
You might be thinking, can we expand this a bit to build
a 3D list or a cube? It turns out we can.
Think of this as stacking many matrices on top of each other.
Let's define a cube which has a length,
the first layer, and a width,
the second layer and a height, the third layer,
which collectively makes it 3D,
like what I'm going to share here.
In this queue, we have three different lists inside of a big list.
This has also a list of list.
This has 1, 2, 3, 4, 5,
6, 7, 8, 9, then in the next one,
10,11,12, 13,14,15,
16,17,18, and then in this third list of list,
we have 19,20,21, 22,23,24,
and 25,26,27, and this is all within one big list that we define as cube.
If we were to print our cube,
we will see something that resembles a cube,
but this time it has an extra pair of square brackets around the elements.
We'll execute this code, and if we print cube, we'll see that.
We'll see here that it has all of
these different items and that additional square bracket all the
way around it compared to the 2D matrices that we saw before.
Just like a 2D matrix,
we can access an element inside of our 3D matrix or cube by specifying the layer,
row, and column.
To get the element at the third layer,
second row, and first column,
we can do something like this after declaring our cube in the previous step.
Now what we can do is we can say print, we'll say cube,
and then we want the second item,
which is the third layer,
we want the second row or Index 1,
and we want the first column,
which is Index 0.
We'll then close out our print statement.
Can you guess what the output of this will be?
We see 22.
Again, we don't need to know how to work with
matrices and cubes in depth for the PCP exam.
But it's important to know how to do
this computation if you continue down the path of a data engineer or a software engineer,
especially in working with different types of data formats.
Great job going through this demo.