As we continue to expand our understanding of data types and data structures in Python,
we've now arrived in the world of tuples.
Imagine you've decided to go on a cross country road trip and want to
keep track of the fixed geographic coordinates of each place you visit,
knowing that these coordinates will never change.
You wouldn't want these numbers to be altered along the way.
Those coordinates would never change.
This is where tuples come in very handy as a data type,
and we wouldn't want to leave for our trip without them.
Tuples are a data collection type in Python that are immutable,
which is just a fancy word that means once they're created,
they can't be modified or edited.
Tuples are perfect for storing data that should remain constant,
permanent, fixed, and stand the test of time.