When we think about using tuples,
we're going to be placing items inside of parentheses separated by commas, like this.
Think of tuples like an itinerary of your trip.
Once you set the cities,
you're going to visit on your grand road trip of adventure, it's all locked in.
No changes allowed or permitted throughout the entire trip, no matter what.
Let's see some examples of what we can do with tuples, specifically,
indexing, slicing, building, in immutability.
Let's talk about tuples and specifically indexing,
slicing, building, and immutability.
If we want to create a simple tuple, for example,
we'll declare a variable and set a list of items to it all within parentheses,
and each item is in quotation marks, just like this.
We'll say cities equals,
and then in parentheses,
three strings, New York,
Los Angeles, and Chicago.
If we were to print cities,
we'll see the cities then printed out like this,
New York, Los Angeles, and Chicago.
Again, all within parentheses because we are defining cities as a tuple.
If we want to find the index of a specific element in the tuple,
we can do that just like a list.
We can write print and
then cities and then the index
of zero, which is the first item.
Then this will output our first item in the Tuple. Can you guess what that will be?
If you said New York, you'd be right,
and that's our first item that we see here in the Tuple.
We can also retrieve parts of a tuple using a slicing method and
get a cross-section of the tuple as well. Let's see how to do that.
We could say print, say cities,
and then if we wanted to get one, two,
three, can you guess what the output of this statement will be?
We'll see the second and third items printed like so.
If you guess this, Los Angeles and Chicago, you're right.
Notice how they still preserve the parentheses,
which we see on the outside here.
Remember when we talked about immutability before, well,
what will happen when we try and set one of the items in the to be a different city?
Let's see what happens.
If we take the first item of cities,
and we try to set that equal to San Francisco,
and we try to execute this code.
What do you think will happen? When we try to run this, we'll get a type error.
This type error will scream at us and say type error,
tuple object does not support item assignment.
Remember, this is because once a tuple is created or initialized,
the elements cannot be edited or amended,
and that's what we just tried to do,
and Python will tell us that,
hey, we can't do that because this is a tuple.