Just like lists, tuples are ordered collections that can be indexed,
meaning we can find an element at a specific position,
like the first element, and sliced,
meaning we can retrieve a portion of the collection,
such as the second through the fourth element.
But unlike lists, they cannot be modified once created,
meaning we can't edit what is inside the data structure.
Tuples are immutable, meaning they can't be changed,
but lists can be freely changed.
If you need to change items,
like a shopping cart, use a list.
If you need to keep items the same,
like road trip coordinates that need to stay the same, use a tuple instead.
As we start to work with these data types, you might think to yourself,
would there ever be a need to combine data types together,
such as tuples and lists?
You'd be right to start thinking about such cases,
as they could be more frequent than you might expect.
The short answer is, yes,
you can have lists inside of tuples or tuples inside of lists.
This allows for a mix of mutable, editable,
and immutable, non-editable data,
depending on what you might need.
Let's see some examples of this.
Let's talk about lists inside tuples and tuples inside lists.
To see an example of a list inside of a tuple,
imagine you have two legs of your trip,
and for each leg, you want to list the cities you'll visit.
We'll define a tuple with lists inside of it.
We'll have a trip variable,
and that's a tuple,
which includes two lists.
The first list has New York and Chicago,
and the second list has Los Angeles and San Francisco.
Here, the tuple contains two lists of cities
and we can access individual cities using double indexing.
Let's show an example of that.
Let's say that we wanted to take the second list and then pull out the first item,
which would be the first city there.
We'll say print trip,
and we'll say Index 1 for the second list,
and then the first item, which is Index 0.
Can you guess what the output will be when we run this?
If you said Los Angeles, you're right.
You can also modify the list inside the tuple since the list themselves are mutable,
even though the tuple as a whole is immutable.
This means that you could edit the cities inside of the lists,
but not their positions or add new elements.
To see an example of a tuple in a list,
imagine you have a list of city pairs where each pair represents a stop on your trip.
For stops, we'll set that equal to a list of two tuples.
First tuple is NYC,
which is New York City, and Chicago,
and then the second one is LA or Los Angeles,
and SF, San Francisco.
Now, let's say that we wanted to go into the first tuple and then print the second item.
Can you guess what that would be or how we would write that?
We'll say print stops,
zero for the first tuple,
and then we'll say one for the second item, and then print.
Can you guess what the output will be here?
If you said Chicago, you're right.
The output here is Chicago as we can do
the double indexing in the same way that we did in the previous example.
The one important thing to note about this is that the list can be modified.
For example, you can add or remove city pairs in the stops variable,
but the tuples themselves remain immutable and cannot be changed.
In the previous example,
we could edit the cities if we wanted to because they are lists.
But here, since the items in the list are tuples,
they are locked and cannot be edited.