Dictionaries are yet another data type in
Python that you'll come to know and use regularly.
Imagine you're running a library and need to track
which books belong to which genre or topic,
or which authors have written specific books in your collection of books.
The library is huge after all,
and you don't have time to count through every single book. You'd be there forever.
How would you organize all of this data efficiently?
This is where dictionaries come in,
and fortunately, for us,
Python has a very unique way of storing data that we call key-value pairs.
Dictionaries allow you to associate data,
like matching up book titles with their genres or authors with their own books.
Let's look at an example of a dictionary like this.
Here, the keys are the book titles,
and the values are the genres associated with the books.
Thanks to this handy data structure,
we can use the book title key to look up or unlock
the genre value that the book is associated with.