List in Python are like dynamic arrays,
collections of items that you can change,
expand, or shrink as needed.
Think of these like a shopping cart of items.
You can add items to the cart,
review what's in the cart,
remove items from the cart,
and there is a specific order in which you add items to them or remove them.
Lists are ordered and mutable,
meaning they keep the order in which elements are added,
and you can change them after creation.
Constructing lists or vectors involves putting items inside of square brackets.
Lists are versatile because they allow you to store multiple related items in one place.
You can create a list by placing your data in side square brackets separated by commas.
In this example, we've created a list of fruits.
Lists are great for storing collections of related data,
like a shopping cart full of items.
You can think of a list as a structured and flexible way to group similar data together.