Dictionaries are built using curly braces with each key value pair in sight.
For example, a dictionary for books and their genres might look something like this.
Earlier, we had them all on multiple lines,
but here we can have them all on one line.
Both can work, but the first example is much more human readable,
at least in my opinion.
Let's see some examples of what this looks like.
Let's talk about dictionaries and specifically,
building, indexing, adding, and removing keys with them.
First, let's build and initialize our dictionary of books, titles, and genres.
We'll create a variable called library,
and we'll have a few items in there.
We'll have pred and prejudice set as romance,
1984, as dystopia, and Moby Dick as adventure.
It might be easier to see this if we have these as different lines.
This is the library dictionary,
and then we have three items with their own keys and values.
That's what we talk about when we say key value pairs.
Now if we were to print this, We'll see this,
and these will be the items that we have already created in our library dictionary.
When we think about indexing,
in order to access data within the dictionary,
we can do a handy lookup with the key or book title.
For example, let's say that we want to print the value of
1984 and we want to see if this item exists in our dictionary.
If we want to find the value of this book,
we'll see that it will output dystopia.
Now, notice that we cannot do the usual indexing method like we usually do like this.
If we do library, and we do this,
this will return a key error.
This tells us that we can't use that as the key to look up an item in our dictionary.
Now let's talk about adding and modifying key value pairs.
Thanks to Python, we can add or modify key value pairs
in our dictionary very easily. We can say library.
We can say the great gas B and square bracket
equals classic.
We are telling the dictionary,
here's the first item, which is going to be great GASB,
and that's the key in brackets,
and then it equals its value,
which is after the equal sign.
If we enter this, and now if we print our library,
We now see that there was a new item added,
which was the Great Gatsby and classic,
which is its genre and of course,
this was added at the very end of our dictionary.
But what if that genre was incorrectly assigned or needs to be updated? What would we do?
Fortunately, dictionaries let us modify the value for an existing key,
which we can do like this.
We'll say library, and then we'll say
the great Gatsby, and equal adventure.
Now if we print library again,
We'll now say that Great Gatsby is no longer classic.
It's now adventure.
Now let's talk about removing key value pairs.
We can also remove an item from our dictionary very easily as well with a Del statement.
All we have to do is this, Delbrary,
and use the key, the Gab.
Once we execute that cell.
Then when we print our library,
we now have the same three items that we started with,
Pride and Prejudice, which is romance,
1984, which is dystopia,
and Moby Dick, which is adventure.
Of course, the Great Gatsby is nowhere to be found in this dictionary.