If we have a library of books,
we could be dealing with thousands or
even tens of thousands or even hundreds of thousands of books,
articles, and media items.
There is no way that we have time to individually
go through each item by hand, would take forever.
That's where we'll want to iterate through dictionaries like this,
so that we can go through our key value pairs without spending excessive time and worry.
If we wanted to loop through all of the key value pairs in a dictionary for our library,
we can rely on our trusty for loop to help us out.
We can loop through a dictionary to access its keys, values or both.
Let's see an example of this.
Let's talk about iterating through dictionaries and their keys and values.
First, we'll build out a dictionary which we will set as library,
and this library will consist of three items.
There will be pride and prejudice,
which is set as the romance genre,
1984, which is the dystopia genre,
and then Moby Dick, which is the adventure genre.
It's a list of titles and genres.
When we print our library,
we'll see those three items printed here as well on one line.
If we wanted to loop through all the keys,
we can do this by looking for book,
our arbitrary counter element in library,
the dictionary we just declared and then tell our for loop to print the counter element,
and we'll do that by saying for book in library.
Remember this is our increment for item in library,
which is our dictionary.
We'll then say print book.
When we execute this, we'll see all three titles,
Pride and Prejudice, 1984, and Moby Dick.
Now, what if we wanted to print out the genres of the library?
We would do the same thing but for this,
we can change the arbitrary counter to genre,
and then we need to use the dot values method off of the library dictionary.
We'll learn about this in a second,
but notice how we can now increment with the second value rather than the titles,
which is the first item and we'll do that by taking
our for loop from the previous step and modifying it so slightly.
We can just change this to any name,
but we'll say genre and then we'll say in
library dot values because we're looking at the second element.
This is the key and this is the value.
Now we're looking at just the values here.
Then when we print book but genre,
this will now print out, romance,
dystopia, and adventure, which are the three genres in our library right now.
To wrap up incrementing,
if we wanted to cycle through both the key and the value,
we can use another method called items which we'll
also learn about momentarily to go through multiple items.
For our for loop, we can just string these multiple items together as book genre,
meaning, for book and genre in our library of items, print the values.
What we'll do is we'll say, for book,
genre in library items.
Colon, we'll say print,
and we'll use another f string,
pass in squiggly bracket and say book,
and then another set of squiggly brackets, and we'll say genre.
We'll close out that f string,
close out the parenthesis.
Now, can you guess what this will output when we run this?
It will now print out each has a string.
Pride and prejudice for romance,
1984 for dystopia, and Moby Dick for adventure.
We're iterating over the keys and the values of our library. Pretty neat, right?