We've already started to use some handy strategies for working with Python.
Let's review what methods we will come
to use when working with the dictionary data structure.
First up, keys. This returns a list of all the items in the dictionary.
Next, values returns a list of all of the values in the dictionary.
Finally, items, this returns a list of
the key value pairs as two pools for that dictionary.
Understanding key value pairs is an essential concept when it comes to data engineering,
building out databases, working with large data sets, and so on.
Many databases and storage systems rely on
key value pairs to organize data in tidy compact formats.
In data modeling, key value pairs can help you and your team
coordinate how that information is organized, stored, and accessed.
If we're defining a user's profile with key value pairs,
this might look something like this when Alice signs up as a new user on our platform.
As her profile is built,
her Alice underscore profile object might consist of her unique ID in our app,
such as a long number,
her name, which is Alice Coder, her birthday,
which is January 1st, 1991,
her favorite color, which is orange,
and her favorite food, which is pizza.
We need to pull out her name to display that in our app,
we go into the key of name and then out pops Alice Coder.
This is how key value pairs become very useful in how we work with our data.
Let's talk about the methods,
keys, items, and values.
In order to see this in action,
let's review what the outputs look like when we
use these methods on our library dictionary.
To get the first values,
we'll use the keys method.
We'll first declare our dictionary,
which we have as pride and prejudice with the Romance,
1984 with the dystopia and Moby Dick with the adventure.
If we want to get the first values of the dictionary,
we'll say print library keys,
and then we'll execute this code.
Now we'll see dictionary of keys is Pride and Prejudice,
1984, and Moby Dick.
Now to get the second values,
we'll use the dot values method,
so we'll copy this last print statement.
But instead of saying keys, we'll say values.
When we execute this code.
We'll now see dictionary values is romance, dystopia, and adventure.
Now to get the key value pairs of all of the items as an immutable triple,
we'll use the dot items method.
We'll copy this last print statement,
and instead of values, we'll say items.
Now instead of getting the first or just the second items,
when we execute this, we'll get the whole library,
which is our entire dictionary inside
of a tuple and that will have pride and prejudice as romance,
1984, as dyspa and Moby Dick as adventure.
And notice how each of these items is a tuple inside of our list.
Dictionaries give us the ability to manage and
organize our data very efficiently using keys and values.
Now your digital library is well organized and easy to manage,
as well as any large data set you need to organize with Python.