We've already been working with strings a great deal in this course.
Let's review them in a bit more detail.
Let's imagine you're a storyteller crafting a very exciting story.
In your exciting story,
every word sentence and paragraph is represented as a sequence of characters.
In Python, these sequences are known as strings.
Whether you're working with text in a story,
a list of commands,
or even just a user name,
strings are essential for storing and manipulating text data of characters.
You'll notice something is a string because it will have quotes around it,
like you see here, much different than a number,
which has no quotations.
You can create a string using either single or double quotes,
both will do in the world of strings in Python.
Think of this like writing a note.
Whether you use single or double quotations,
doesn't matter very much,
as long as you're consistent.
When you're working on a tech team,
your team will probably adopt a specific style.
Make sure to subscribe to those types of standards for consistency.