Just like the lists rays in tuples we have been learning about.
Strings can also be indexed and sliced.
You're probably thinking, how?
Isn't a string just a single item?
You'd mostly be right.
But something that we can think about as we expand our concept of indices and
slicing is that strings are made up of individual characters,
and they can be indexed and sliced.
Let's see an example of this in action.
Let's talk about indexing, slicing, and immutability.
When we first construct a string,
we'll probably do something like this.
We'll say greeting or any name is equal to list of characters like hello world.
We'll execute this cell,
and now greeting is set to our string, hello world.
To see an example of indexing with strings,
we can then get the first character Index 0 of this greeting variable,
which we set as a string in the same way that we can for lists and tuples, like this.
We'll say print greeting.
We'll take the first index,
which is Index 0.
Then when we execute this,
can you guess what the output will be?
If you said H, you're right.
This will print the letter H. This is the first item in this string,
which is the Index 0.
If we try to print the index of one,
can you guess what the output will be here?
If you said e, then you're right there because
this is the second item or Index 1 of our string.
Now, if we want to slice out a few characters of the string,
we can do that in a similar way to how we've learned how to do that before.
Let's say we want to print the characters from Index 0 to Index 7.
We'll do something like this.
We can copy this just for speed.
Then what we can do is we'll say in those square brackets,
0:7 to do a slice.
Can you guess what the output of this will be when we execute this cell?
This will print hello w. Now,
what if we slice well beyond the number of characters in the string?
This is not a problem at all for Python.
It will return up to the number of characters of the string and nothing more.
Let's say that we wanted to do this again,
but we're going to do it up to 20.
There's of course, no 20th character here or 20th index for our characters.
There's 0, 1, 2, 3,
4, 5, 6,
7, 8, 9, 10.
There's Index 10 items for 11 characters,
and there's 1,
2, 3, 4, 5,
6, 7, 8, 9,
10, 11. So that checks out.
But if we were to do this over 20,
this will still print our exact string as hello world, and nothing more.
Something else to keep in mind with strings is that they are immutable.
We cannot change a character in the string as each character within the string is set,
and trying to change one will raise a type error.
Let's see this in action.
When we try to change the first character of our greeting string,
which is hello world with an A character,
meaning we want to change the H to an A like this.
We'll say greeting and we'll take the first index,
and then we try to set that equal to A.
We're trying to change this character to an A character and we try to execute this code.
Can you guess what the output is going to be?
We'll get a type error, and we'll say,
string object does not support item assignment.
That means because strings are immutable,
we cannot assign new items to what has been declared there already.