If you ever need to include special characters like quotation marks or adding a new line,
such as an Enter, into the string,
you can use the backslash character as an escape character.
You might not have ever needed to use this special backslash character before,
but it is a very handy one to have in your back pocket.
For example, let's say that you want to break up text into two lines,
but it is the same string.
You can use the handy backslash character to put
the part after the backslash onto a second line.
Otherwise, it would all be on one line without that special symbol.
Let's see what this looks like in practice.
Let's talk about escaping using the backslash character.
To see how the escape character works or backslash character,
let's say that we want to print a sentence,
and it includes a quote from someone, like this.
Our quote is, "After completing the course,
you exclaimed: 'I love coding in Python!'"
Now, you might think we could code this by declaring a variable and making it
set to the quotes and including the quote inside, like this.
We'll say quote equals,
we'll add outside quotes,
and then we're setting this long string to our quote variable like this.
But this will cause a syntax error when trying to initialize
this variable because of the quotes that are inside of the outside quotes.
When we execute this code,
we'll see this, and it'll say "SyntaxError: invalid syntax".
This is because the quotes are missing backslashes.
To escape the quotes inside of the quotes,
we'll put the backslash character to the left of the inside quotes, like this.
Now when we execute this cell, we'll see this printed.
We'll execute that cell, we'll say print,
and then we'll execute this code so we can print out what quote is.
Now we see the full sentence with the quotes.
After completing the course,
you exclaimed: "I love coding in Python!" Great job.