To use a quotes inside a string,
you can either escape them with a backslash,
like we just learned how to do in the previous lesson,
or use different types of quotes.
In this example, the single quotes wrap the entire string,
and you can put double quotes inside of the string as needed,
or something like this.
In this example, we use double quotes to wrap
the entire string in a single apostrophe shows up inside of the string.
Both of these are acceptable strings according to Python.
With regards to apostrophes inside of strings,
so long as it's a single apostrophe,
then that will not cause an issue or need to be escaped.
If you were to have quotation marks inside of quotation marks,
that is where we would need to have them be escaped,
like we walked through in the last lesson.
May remember our use of multi line strings from the previous lessons.
But let's recap what makes the multi-line string different from a regular string.
As you'll see here, multi-line strings have triple quotes at the beginning,
and at the end, and can span across multiple-lines of text.
Regular strings have the same quotes at the beginning and at the end of the string.