Now that we know how strings work,
let's check out some of the methods for working with strings in our functions.
This will involve turning our strings to all lowercase,
all uppercase replacements, and splits. Let's dive in.
The first method is lower,
and this converts the string to all lowercase.
Imagine you're building a login system where users email addresses are case insensitive,
meaning JohnCoder, with those capitals @email.com,
should be treated the same as johncoder@email.com.
Using the lower method ensures that
all email inputs are standardized before comparison like this.
Use lower when you are standardizing text inputs for case insensitive operations,
such as login systems and searches.
The second method is upper,
which does the opposite of the first method we just learned about.
This converts the string to all uppercase.
Suppose you're working with an inventory system for a retail store,
and the product codes need to all be uppercase.
Using the upper method ensures that codes entered in
lowercase or mix case are converted to uppercase before being processed, like so.
Use upper when you're ensuring consistency in product codes,
reference numbers, or identifiers that must be in uppercase.
The third method is replace,
which allows us to replace a chunk of characters or
sub-string with another chunk of characters or another sub-string.
Let's say you have an e-commerce website,
and you're running a promotion.
You want to dynamically change the displayed currency from dollars to euros.
Using the replace method,
you can easily swap one currency symbol for another.
Use replace when you are replacing dynamic content such
as formatting prices or handling localization,
where certain terms need to change.
The fourth method is split,
which does exactly what it says.
It splits the string into a list based on a delimiter,
otherwise known as a character that we'll use to separate items in two.
Imagine you're processing customer feedback on a website where users submit comments.
You need to split sentences into individual words to
analyze which words are most frequently used.
The split method helps you break down these sentences into lists of words.
This turns the comment into this product is amazing.
I love it. Use the split method when you're tokenizing text for data analysis.
For example, customer feedback,
social media posts, and so on.
Processing CSV data or parsing logs.
Let's see these in action.
Let's talk about basic string functions and methods.
To see these methods for working with strings,
let's take this starter string here,
where we'll type text = Hello, World.
Now, to make all of the characters in this string lower case,
we can use the lower method. Like this.
We'll say print(text.lower()),
and then we'll add parentheses,
and then when we execute this code,
this will turn Hello,
World into all lower case, hello, world.
Next, we turn all the characters uppercase.
We'll use the upper method, like this.
We can copy the previous print statement,
and instead of lower, we'll say upper.
If we execute this code,
this will turn our capitalized Hello,
World into all uppercase,
and it'll say HELLO, WORLD in all caps.
Now, let's say that we wanted to switch out one of
the characters or one of the words in our string.
You might remember that I said strings are
immutable and that we can't replace individual characters.
Well, there is a way to do this with the replace method.
If we wanted to change out the word world for Python,
we could use the replace method like so.
We'll say print, and then we'll do text.replace,
then we'll say "world",
in quotes, and then we'll say "Python".
That's also in quotes,
and then we'll close out our parentheses for a replace function,
and then we will close out print.
Can you guess what this output is going to be once we execute this code? Let's find out.
We now see Hello,
Python, and now our world has been replaced with Python.
This first input is then replaced by what we put
in as that second input once it finds this in text.
There might come a time where we want to split up the text of our string by
a delimiter or a splitting character into a list or array of parts.
How could we do this? What we can do is we can say (print(text.split(",")),
and then we'll close it out of parentheses.
By running this, our split method will split the string at the coma,
and it'll create a list.
Now this will create a list with some strings in there,
so we'll have 'Hello', ' World! '
And then in quotes space World, and exclamation point.
Again, this is all within a list.
In the example from earlier with an even longer amount of text,
you will see even more tokenized or broken
up components from the string into its individual components.
Let's take a comment and we'll write comment equals,
so we're setting a variable here.
We'll set this equal to. This product is amazing. I love it.
Now, we'll take words and we'll equal comment.split.
We'll put this in parentheses.
We'll do a (" ") end parentheses,
and then we'll print the words.
Can you guess what this is going to output?
When we run this, this will turn the comment string into this product is amazing.
I love it, and this is all in the list.
We break up the words based on the delimiter of a space,
which we defined here.
That is where the space comes in with the split method.
These methods are simple,
but extremely powerful tools for
manipulating and formatting text in real world Python applications,
all with the power of strings.
Great job going through all of these methods,
and hopefully you can see how these methods could be powering the technology,
apps and websites you use and depend on every single day. Great job.