Lists allow you to access elements using an index, starting from zero.
Think of an index as the relative position of an item around other things.
Before your favorite band performs at the Big Stadium,
attendees file into the stadium in an orderly fashion.
There's somebody who entered first, second, third,
fourth, all the way to being the 1,000th or even 10,000th person.
The order is incredibly important for lists,
which you will see in a bit.
Something that can be quite confusing that you should remember is
that the first index of a position is actually zero.
While the order might be person 1, 2,
3, and so on,
person one's index is zero.
Person 2 's index is one,
person 3 's index is two, and so on.
Make sure to keep that in mind as you go about using indexes.
Once we have a list of items,
we might want to select only a subsection of
that list or pull certain items out of that big list.
Think of this like a crane going into a basket of prizes.
When you are slicing a list,
you can pull out a single item or a collection of items that are next to each other.
Slicing uses the format, start, colon, end,
where start is the index to begin at,
and end is the index up to,
but not including that number.
Let's see an example of lists in action with
our fruit list example from before using indexing, and then slicing.
Lists allow you to access elements using an index starting with zero.
We'll define a list with a variable name,
which we'll call fruits, and then we'll use
square brackets and then put items inside of it.
Here we have three strings, apple,
banana, and cherry, indicating our three fruits.
If we want to print the first item, how do you think we would do that?
What do you think the first index would be as an index zero?
To write this, we'd write fruits.
We'll use a square bracket.
We'll put zero for the first item,
and the square bracket, and then we'll close out our print statement.
What do you think the index of zero will be?
If you guess apple, you're right.
It's the first item in the array,
and thus index position zero.
You can also retrieve a slice of a list using the slicing syntax.
Again, we'll take our list from before,
and we'll paste that into a new cell.
If we want to slice out part of our list,
such as the first index to the third index,
what do you think the output of this will be?
If we do fruits, do a square bracket.
We'll do one colon 3,
and then we'll close out that statement.
What do you think the output will be here?
Let's run it and find out.
This is going to retrieve the elements from index one up to but not including index 3.
It will skip apple at index zero, our first element,
and then we'll print the first index,
which is banana up to the third index,
which is cherry, because it will include that,
and then once it reaches the third index element, then it would stop.
But we only have 0,
1, 2 index items.
But since we said third,
that's why it includes cherry.