Python provides several built-in methods to make it easier to manage lists.
Some of the most useful include append, insert, and index.
Append is where we add an item to the end of the list.
This is useful when we want to add items into our shopping cart.
Insert adds an item at a specific index.
This is useful if we want to add an item to our cart in a specific place,
such as organizing fruits together or perishable items
together so that they can go in the same bag for easier organization.
Index, which finds the index of a specific item in the list.
Think of this as using a powerful magnifying glass to identify
the specific placement of an item in the list
and tells us the index of that item in the collection.
Just keep these things in mind for now.
We're going to go through examples of these in some demos,
so you can see these powerful methods of Python in action.
Let's see some examples of the append, insert,
and index functions in action using our fruit array.
First, let's start off with the append function.
Let's say we want to add another fruit to our list of fruits.
How would we do that? Well, we can use the append function like this.
We'll first create our list of fruits.
We'll say fruits is equal to and in square brackets,
apple, banana, and cherry as a list of strings.
Then what we'll do is we will say fruits.append,
and then inside of the append function,
we'll add another fruit,
which we'll say is grape.
Then we'll print our updated list of fruits.
Can you guess what the list of fruits will now look like?
Now we see apple, banana, cherry, and grape.
Now we've added grape to our last item in the list,
and that's why it's at the end of it.
If we want to add items to a specific location,
how would we accomplish this?
This is where our insert function comes into play.
Now, we already have our fruits list already created.
If we wanted to insert an item, we'll create a new cell,
and we will say fruits in
the position that we want that new item to go into at that index,
and then we'll add in our new item,
which we'll say is orange.
Then we'll print the updated list of fruits.
Can you guess what this will output?
Let's run this and find out.
Now, you'll notice we have grape at the end of our list that we
added in the previous step and a new item orange as well.
And this is at Index 1.
This makes sense because it would be index zero,
Index 1, and now we have 2, 3,
4 because now we have one, two, three, four,
five fruits in our fruits list now.
Now, if we want to find the specific index of an item in our list,
we can rely on our trusty index function.
Let's see this working in an example here.
If we wanted to check the index of banana,
we would write something like this.
We would say print fruits index banana.
We pass in the item that we want to check,
and we use the index function over our list,
and that's the same list that we declared earlier.
When we run this, we'll see two is the output.
Here the index of this item is two,
but originally, it was one.
This is because we have a lot more items in the array than when we started,
and we added orange.
Originally, it was zero,
one, Index 1,
but now it's Index 2 as in index zero,
Index 1, and Index 2.
Same with grape.
If we wanted to find the index of grape,
we would write print index grape.
Then we would execute that, and we'll see that that's Index 4,
which makes sense because it's zero,
one, two, three, four.
Let's validate this is true.
We'll write print fruits,
and then we'll press Enter.
Can you guess what the output will be for all of the fruits?
We'll see five items.
If you guess this, you're right.
We'll see apple, orange,
banana, cherry, and grape.
We can verify that this is Index zero,
one, two, three, and four. Great job.