The len function is used to get the length of a list,
such as the number of elements inside that list.
Think of len as a quick way to count how many items are currently in your shopping cart,
regardless of if they are veggies,
fruits, bread, dessert, etc.
We might only care about the overall number of items.
For example, in the express checkout line,
you might need to have 10 or 15 items or less.
That is where our trusty len function comes in very handy for us here.
In this example, let's count how many items are in our list.
In this case, there are three items in the list,
so len(fruits) returns the number 3 since there are three items in the list,
apple, banana, and cherry.