Along with the list methods we saw in the previous lesson,
Python offers powerful functions to work with lists.
In this video, we'll take a closer look at len and sorted.
Len, as we just saw the length function,
returns the number of elements in a list.
This is a counter for finding the number of pieces in the collection.
Sorted, on the other hand, returns a new list with the elements
sorted in ascending order or descending if specified.
This helps us sort our organization of items,
kind of like cleaning our room or putting everything in
a logical orderly manner for better analysis or review.
Let's see a demo of how these functions help us with managing our lists.
Let's look at the len and sorted functions.
First, let's take another example list,
this time with a list of numbers.
If we want to count how many numbers are in the list,
we'll use the len function like so.
We'll define our numbers list like this.
In square brackets, we have 5,
2, 9, and 1.
Then we'll write a print statement where we'll take the len or the length of numbers.
We'll do len in parentheses put in our list,
close out len and then close out the print statement.
Now, when we run this,
we're going to see that the output has some numbers in it.
What do you think the output will look like?
When we run this, we see the output is four because there
are four numbers in the numbers list,
1, 2, 3, and 4.
Now, if we want to sort these in numerical order,
it would take a huge amount of time to do this
manually if we have a huge amount of numbers.
As Python developers, we have to move fast.
So let's leverage the powerful sorted function for this.
What we'll do is that we will say sorted numbers,
as a variable name, equals sorted,
and we'll put our numbers list inside of that.
Now, when we print our sorted numbers,
what do you think we'll see as the output?
When we run this, we now see 1,
2, 5, and 9.
And now we see the output of sorted numbers is
now in complete numerical order, almost by magic.
And if you thought that it starts and stops with numbers, think again.
Let's try this by alphabetizing our fruits array.
Our fruits array looked something like this.
We had apple, orange, banana, cherry,
and grape, and that's set to the fruits variable here.
So we can execute the cell on this that will save our fruits.
Now if we were to print the value of our fruits array,
we'll see apple, orange,
banana, cherry, and grape, right here.
Now, let's use the sorted function to alphabetize all of these items in our fruits list.
We'll say print(sorted(fruits)) we'll put in fruits,
and then we'll close out the print statement.
So what do you think the output will now be for our fruits list?
Again, almost by magic,
we have our fruits array sorted in complete alphabetical order, which is A,
B, C, and then G and O, so apple,
banana, cherry, grape, and orange. How cool is that?