You can also loop through all the elements of a list using a for loop.
You'll remember for loops from the previous lessons,
and now we get to see this powerful skill we learned in a more data-centric manner.
Using a for loop over a list is like scanning each item in your shopping cart.
Here, we'll see it print out each item in the loop.
Remember our format of for loops.
For tells Python, we want to iterate through a specific item,
which we can name anything.
But here we declare a single item called
fruit in a list of items in a predefined array called fruits.
The output is apple, banana, and cherry.
The for loop automatically goes through each element,
in our case, each fruit,
and prints each item one at a time,
iterating through the fruits array.