When using a for loop with lists,
you can initialize a list beforehand and then build it inside the loop.
For example, let's say that we want to add items to our cart,
but we don't know what they will be until the for loop runs.
When using a for loop with lists,
you can initialize a list beforehand and then build it inside the loop.
For example, let's say that we want to add items to our cart,
but we don't know what they will be until the for loop runs.
The concept becomes a little bit clearer with a math example.
Let's say we want to iterate over
a series of numbers and calculate the square of each one.
A square is simply a number multiplied by itself.
For example, the square of 2 is 2*2,
which we'll see is 4.
The square of 3 is 3 times itself, 3.
If we execute this code, we'll see nine.
When we talk about a list of squares,
we're referring to a collection of numbers where
each number is the square of a particular value like 1,
2, 3, and so on.
Imagine you're a city planner and you need to
calculate the area of square shaped plots of land.
Each plot of land is defined by its side length.
For example, 1 meter,
2 meters, or 3 meters.
The area of a square is found by squaring the side length.
For example, side length times side length.
Here's how we could use a list of squares to represent
the areas of plots with different side lengths.
For example, a plot with side length of 1 meter has an area of 1*1,
resulting in 1 square meter.
A plot with side length of 2 meters has an area of 2*2,
equaling 4 square meters.
A plot with side length of 3 meters has an area of 3*3 or 9 square meters, and so on.
In this case, you might use a loop to calculate
the area of each plot and store those areas in the list.
Let's write some code as an example to calculate
the areas of plots with side lengths from 1-5 meters.
We'll first create a empty list variable called areas
and we'll set that equal to an empty list with nothing in it.
We'll then write our for loop and we'll say side_length
in range 1-6 because we want it to go from 1-5 meters.
Then we'll say areas and then we'll use our append function that we just learned about.
Inside of that, we'll say side length and we'll say ** 2.
Then we'll print the areas list.
Can you guess what the output of this will be when we execute this code?
Here, we'll see an output of 1, 4,
9, 16, and 25 inside of our areas list.
Notice how originally areas was an empty list
here and now it has been populated with lots of numbers here.
This list of squares represents the areas of plots with side lengths from 1-5.
Why are these types of calculations useful?
Well, in geometry and space calculations as shown before,
squares are useful when calculating areas of square spaces.
In physics and engineering,
in certain physical equations like calculating energy or force,
squaring values is often required.
In machine learning and statistics,
squaring numbers is common when calculating errors,
such as in regression analysis,
making this concept important in data science.
Great job learning some new math concepts.
Hopefully this helps show the power of
lists and also how we can combine them together with
real world applications and use cases like
space calculations as a city planner like we saw here.