Pandas and NumPy are powerful tools that can help you explore all aspects of your data.
So far, we've only scratched the surface.
In this lesson, we're fully immersing ourselves into payments.
In this lesson, we'll begin understanding
some of the simple procedures that come with cleaning data.
These include dealing with incorrect data types,
duplicates, missing and mismatched data.
If we need to remove data,
we'll cover how to drop data from our DataFrame.
Will go over how to rename columns for better readability.
Selecting data from our DataFrame takes many shapes.
One approach is to use the query method,
which is a powerful operation that can be used with either strings or numerical data.
From there, we will experiment with how to join
Pandas DataFrames together through concatenation and merging.
We'll go over how each method works and the difference between them.
When it comes to merging data with SQL functionality.
We'll go over the different types of joins, mainly inner, outer,
left and right joins,
will also cover ways to distinguish data after it has been combined.
Lastly, data is not always formatted in a way that has individual values to a column.
By using the explode method,
you'll learn how to expand a list from a single column vertically
into rows or horizontally into columns.
As you can tell, this lesson is jam-packed with new tools for
you to use in your data analysts journey. Let's get started.