Let's learn about NumPy and how we can use it to do this.
NumPy is short for numerical Python and is designed for efficient scientific computation.
It's built on top of the programming language C,
which works at a lower-level on our computer.
To understand what this means for the speed of our code,
see the link in the instructor notes.
Pandas is built on top of NumPy,
which is why it's so fast with all its computations for functions like describe.
If you try doing these computations in plain Python, it's much slower.
Here's an example, calculating the mean for an array of 100 million values.
This generates an array of 100 million random floats zero and one.
We could also type in 1e8 to make this clearer.
Looks like that provides a float when it requires an int.
Let's see how long it takes standard Python to compute the mean of this array.
A little more than nine seconds.
Now, let's see how long it takes NumPy.
That was almost instant. Isn't that cool?
Imagine how much it speeds up the process when there's much more computation happening.
For example, let's say we're engineering a whole new feature or column,
which you compute by multiplying the values and two columns
together and divide by the values in another for each row.
Unlike NumPy, plain Python would require
a massively long loop through all the rows to compute the new value for each row.
The main object we work with in NumPy is
a multi-dimensional array of values of all the same datatype.
These arrays, along with many useful functions in NumPy,
optimize and simplify operations on data.