Pandas supports a wide array of data types,
but the difficult types you will encounter include objects.
These are typically strings,
integers, whole numbers like zero, one,
and two, floats,
which are floating point numbers with high precision.
Booleans, you'll see these as true or false.
Datetimes, these include the date and the time into a single value.
Sometimes you'll see these as timestamps.
Finally, categorical.
We'll use these later in the lesson,
but these data types help organize string representations in your DataFrame.
There are many more, and I suggest you look
at the pandas documentation to review them all.
To change a column's datatype,
you can use the astype method.
This works with either a dictionary mapping on
the entire DataFrame or converting the column by accessing the series.
You will still need to assign it back to the DataFrame for the conversion to persist.