When combining two or more data sets together,
pandas provides an incredible tool called concat.
Concat takes a list of one or more DataFrames and joins them vertically or horizontally.
Here you can see them vertically.
Think of this as stacking one DataFrame on top of another.
Pandas tries to align all of the columns
together by joining and matching on the column names.
The return value of concat is a new DataFrame from the joint results.
By default, concat joins vertically.
Or you can explicitly state it by using the axis equal to zero.
To join horizontally, one must set axis equal to one.
Concat includes additional parameters allowing
you to combine your DataFrames in different ways.
Let's go through the Jupyter Notebook,
and practice using this amazing tool.