One of the many problems faced when manipulating data using pandas is
converting nested lists so they each have a value represented in a row or column.
To solve this, we use the explode method provided by pandas.
The explode method will convert a list of values into a row representing each value.
For every row that has a list,
the result will be a singular column.
We stacked row values representing all of the list values from every row it transform.
Expanding a list into columns does not use the method we just mentioned,
but can be achieved by creating a list of values while defining a new DataFrame,
effectively transforming the list into columns.
It is important to mention
these two transformations as they solve the same problem differently.
Let's go through the notebook to practice
the two techniques and visually understand their distinctions.