In this lesson, we learned how to use pandas and
NumPy to manipulate data into formatted forms.
This includes performing data cleaning such as
dropping and renaming columns and fixing data types.
Filtering data with SQL like syntax by using
the query method to sub-select specific parts of the data.
Joining and merging data using concatenation in SQL like operations,
and expanding nested list data to separate rows and columns using explode processing.
While these are the high-level key points,
you learned a tremendous amount of
pandas functionality to utilize in your data analysts to belts.
Take a second to congratulate yourself.