In the last lesson, you learned about how you can predict
the response variable using a single explanatory variable in simple linear regression.
In this lesson, you'll extend that knowledge further.
You will learn about how you can predict a response variable by using multiple inputs,
including both quantitative and categorical variables.
With your understanding of simple linear regression,
you're in a great position to master the ideas in this lesson.
At the end of this lesson,
you will learn not only how to build multiple linear regression models in Python,
but you will also learn the pros and cons of this modeling technique,
and how to interpret your results.
For those who like additional resources,
I've linked a full text of introduction to statistical learning.
This is a great book.
Chapter three specifically, is a great resource for this lesson.
With that, let's get started.