Each time you add these higher order or interaction terms to the model,
you should be sure to add each of the lower order terms as well.
We saw how you might be able to identify a quadratic like relationship,
and even higher order terms might be useful when we see
many curves in the relationship between the response and explanatory variables.
But how do you know if you should add an interaction term?
Why would we add something that looks like this into our model?
Let's consider a small example to illustrate this idea.
When adding interaction terms,
you're considering if the way that a variable x1 is related to
your response y is dependent on another variable x2.
As an example, consider that for neighborhood A,
the relationship between the square footage of a house and its price looks like this.
And for neighborhood B,
the relationship between the square footage of a house and the price looks like this.
Here, you can see that the slopes of the lines that
best fit each set of points are the same.
Even though this neighborhood has more expensive homes for the same square footage,
this would be accounted for by the dummy variable,
as this space between the two lines is consistent.
Regardless of the neighborhood,
the increase would be the exact same accounted for by this coefficient here in our model.
However, imagine if the relationship actually looked like this for neighborhood B.
Here, we can see that the slopes of these two lines no longer match.
In order to account for this,
we would want to add an interaction term between
neighborhood and square footage to our model like this.
Here, you can see that the way square footage is related to
the home price is dependent on which neighborhood the home is in,
or the way that x1 is related to y is dependent on the value of x2.
The question of adding an interaction is a question
about these slopes being close enough to equal.
If the slopes are close to equal,
then we don't add an interaction.
However, if these slopes are not equal,
this is an indication that we should add an interaction to our model.