Let's imagine you're looking to invest in a home.
In particular, you would like to purchase a home
where you think it's worth more than the listed price.
We collect information on recently sold homes to use in your pursuit.
Here's a table of the information you collect;
the price of the home, the neighborhood,
which has three categories of neighborhoods, A, B,
or C, the square footage of the house,
the number of bedrooms,
the number of bathrooms,
and the style, either ranch, Victorian or lodge.
In the last lesson,
you learned how to use one of
these quantitative columns to predict the price of the house.
But what if we wanted to use all of these?
What about these columns multiplying a slope of
seven by neighborhood A or home style Victorian,
what would that even mean?
It turns out that we can use linear algebra to predict
the y value using all of these inputs at the same time.
The way we do this is by creating a matrix of inputs,
so these values here,
and we create a vector of the response that we want to predict.
This matrix is often denoted as X,
while this vector for the response is denoted with y.
To differentiate from the notation you saw earlier,
each of these generally is notated as bold.
In order to really grasp all of what's
happening with multiple linear regression and how it works,
you need to understand how these vectors and matrices work together.