You actually are very well equipped to take on fitting
multiple linear regression models as well as interpreting the results from these models.
Let's take a look at an example.
This is a similar dataset,
the housing dataset you saw in the last lesson which is available in the resources,
and in the next concept for you to follow along.
Here, I've written the appropriate libraries as well as the dataset.
Now, to fit our linear model,
let's first create an intercept.
Then, we can again use stats models similar to what you did in the last lesson.
But we'll need to add all of our variables into the list for the X portion.
So here we're adding the intercept,
and we're interested in predicting the price.
And on the right-hand side here,
we need to add all of our variables that are quantitative.
If you try to add the categorical variables,
you'll notice that that breaks.
Store that in LM for a linear model.
We will fit the model.
Now, it's your turn.
Use the environment on the next concept to follow
along with creating your first multiple linear aggression model.