Just using what you know from
the bivariate case of comparing two variables in the last lesson,
you probably know more than you think about multiple linear regression models.
It's essentially the same as with using only one explanatory variable,
except that when you interpret your coefficients,
you'll add the statement of holding all other variables constant.
What exactly does this mean?
Well, if you were to interpret
this coefficient attached to the square footage of the house,
we would say for each additional unit increase in the area of the house,
the price is expected to increase by
345.9 as long as all the other variables stay the same.
Assuming that these houses both have one bathroom, one bedroom,
but one house has one square foot more than the other,
we would expect its price to be 345.9 higher.
This interpretation, which is almost exactly the same in the earlier lesson,
is what you would do for every quantitative variable
in our multiple linear regression model.
Additionally, a quick glance at the P values can provide
some context for whether or not we think
a variable is statistically related to the response.
This isn't the only check you should do,
but it's a great quick check to understand which relationships appear to be important.
Two points for further exploration come from these exercises.
First, notice that even though looking at the relationship between
only the number of bathrooms and
the price showed a statistically significant relationship.
When we added this to looking at
all the variables at once, this relationship disappeared.
There are a few reasons why this might have happened,
and we'll explore those in the next concept.
Second, when adding quantitative variables to our model,
it worked just like you saw in the last lesson.
But what about with categorical variables?
When we tried to add them, everything broke.
Let's explore these two findings a little bit more closely.