So you saw that you can't add categorical explanatory variables into
your X matrix as nicely as you were able to add quantitative variables.
Instead of adding columns like this into your X matrix with values such as A,
B, and C for the neighborhood,
we end up creating what are known as dummy variables.
There are a few different ways to encode dummy variables.
But most commonly used are the ones where you encode one and zero.
The way this works is we create a column for each value in this column.
And for each column,
there's a one if the value exists in the column and a zero otherwise.
So the column we would create for the A values would look like this.
Then, when we want to create a column for the B values,
it would look like this.
And finally, the last column for C would look like this.
You will want to do this for each of
the categorical variables that you want to add in your data set.
Because this last column can be inferred from the earlier two columns,
as the one values are only in the rows
that didn't have ones in one of these other columns,
we actually end up choosing to drop this column.
Which one you drop doesn't really matter too much.
In the next concept,
you will see the mathematical reasoning for dropping a column.
And then, the screencast will show you how this works in practice.