You now have learned about how you can use categorical variables and regression models.
You saw not only how to fit models using
these categorical variables but also how to interpret the results.
At this point, you are familiar with the most common method that's
used in programming languages like Python and R. However,
there's one additional method for encoding
dummy variables that's really common in a programming language called SAS.
For SAS, the default encoding is one zero negative one.
SAS is an extremely popular programming language used in health related fields.
The biggest reason for noting this difference is that it changes
your coefficients that you get back from
the model as well as how you interpret those coefficients.
You solve it using one zero encoding,
your interpreter coefficients as a comparison to a baseline category.
However, if use one zero negative one encoding,
your coefficients are in comparison to the average regardless of the group.
Just so you can see how this will work and how the results will change,
I've added a notebook and a couple of quizzes in the next concept.