When building multiple linear regression models,
there's a number of problems that may arise.
But defining what constitutes as a problem,
is depending on what your model is going to be used for.
Are you using your model to understand how your x and y variables are related?
Are you using your model to best predict the response variable?
Or are you interested in finding
which variables are really useful in predicting your response?
Each of these could have a number of problems that arise with it.
Depending on which aspects you're most interested in,
this can help determine which problems you actually care about addressing.
In Introduction to statistical learning,
the following problems are identified.
First, a linear relationship may not exist between your response and predictor variables.
Second, you might have correlated errors.
Third, you might not have constant variance of your errors.
Fourth, you might have outliers or leverage points that hurt your model.
Or last, you might have more linearity.
There are entire books and courses aimed at each of these potential problems,
so the discussion of these topics and this class will not be exhaustive.
But Chapter three dives into each of the above.
I'm going to take a more industry focused approach towards addressing these problems,
where Introduction to statistical learning takes on a more academic approach.
A summary of the academic approach is provided in the following concept.
But if you want to see how this is applied in practice,
feel free to move on to the applied portion that follows.