Let's first talk about what is GPT and get a very high level overview of how it works.
GPT stands for generative, pretrained transformers.
Generative means that this model can generate text.
Pretrained means that it was trained on large amounts of data.
Transformers is a name of a network architecture that was used to create the GPT model.
Network architecture refers to
how different blocks of a neural network are arranged together.
You should be already familiar with
feedforward networks and convolutional networks
that are commonly used for image classification.
Transformers is another more recently developed network architecture
that was created for processing text.
For example, for tasks like translating from one language to another,
or for text generation,
as the core of transformers is the ability of
a model to generate the next word given some input text.
For example, I've provided input in a shocking turn of events to one of the GPT models,
and it returned a single word it,
which the model considers to be the best next word given this input sentence.
If we add the next predicted word to
the input phrase and pass this new phrase into the model again,
it will provide another word.
We can now add this word again to the input,
and we can repeat this process again and again.
It seems very limited at first,
but if we repeat this enough times,
we can get a meaningful output.
For example, given the following input text,
a model has generated this beginning of
a fictional new story doing this one word at a time.
To define some terminology,
the input we provide to a model is also called a prompt,
and we will use the words input and prompt interchangeably.
It turns out that during their training,
models can learn a lot of information about the real world.
For example, if we give a model a prompt like the capital of Paris is,
It will likely return Paris.
To do it, it should have learned about cities,
capitals, how to answer questions,
and many other things.
Given the large amount of training data,
GPT models became very proficient in a variety of tasks.
Even in tasks, they were not trained for specifically.
For example, I gave a prompt to one of the GPT models to write a poem about transformers,
and it returned this output.
Or these models can generate code.
Like in this example,
where I've asked a model to write a function that calculates a Fibonacci number.
Transformer models are not just limited to generating text.
We can use transformers to convert text into audio,
or we can generate images described by a particular prompt.
The field of AI that allows to generate new data is called generative AI.
There has been a proliferation of new generative AI models,
and they are usually based on the transformer architecture.
These models can generate images,
text, audio, and videos.
In this course, we will learn about so called large language models or LLMs, for short.
These models were trained on massive amounts of data.
Using these models, we can generate text,
use them to answer questions, and so on.
But how we can use these models?
One way is to use a set of GPT models from OpenAI.
These models can understand text,
images, and voice, and reply to users questions.
Alternatively, we can use Gemini models from Google that have similar capabilities.
Another commonly used set of models are called stable diffusion from Stability AI.
These models are very good at
generating images given an input prompt describing an image.
There are also some other popular open source
LLMs that you can download and run on your computer.
These include Llama models developed by Meta and Mistral models developed by Mistral AI.
When we talk about a GPT model,
we're not talking about a single model.
OpenAI has trained a myriad of different models with different versions.
Even a model with the same major version like
GPT-4 has been updated and refined over time.
There is refinements and improvements have their own names like GPT-4 Turbo or GPT-4o.
When using OpenAI products like ChatGPT or their API,
we can select the model version to use.
Although some models like GPT-2 and
GPT-3 have already been deprecated and are no longer available.
Other companies have also produced many different versions of their models.
For example, Meta has trained Llama 2 and
Llama 3 and created different versions of Llama 3.