Once we have tokenized text,
we can start building machine learning models using it.
In this video, we will talk about one of the simplest models we can build.
We will start with simpler models to learn about their downsides,
which will help us to better understand the advantages of more sophisticated models.
In this video, we will start with the bag-of-words model.
The way it works, it receives a binary vector
as an input where every value is one or zero,
and we create this binary vector from input token IDs.
Let's see how it works.
To use the bag-of-words model,
we start with an input sentence and split it into individual tokens.
We then convert all words to lower case,
and remove tokens for words that have very little useful information,
such as a,
the, and so on.
These are also called stop words.
We then convert each token into a corresponding token ID.
Once we have these IDs,
we convert them into an input vector.
The way we do this is that if we have a token ID with values 345,
we set one in the corresponding position,
and we do the same for all other input IDs.
This input vector will have as many elements as we have unique words in our vocabulary.
If we've decided that our vocabulary will have 65,000 words,
our input vector will have this number of elements.
Now, having a binary vector,
we can pass this input to a neural network or use some other machine learning models.
If we train the model based on these input vectors,
our model can learn to classify text.
For example, by classifying messages into SPAM or non-SPAM messages.
Bag-of-words model is one of the simplest models we could build.
It can work in some cases,
but it has a lot of drawbacks.
First of all, it ignores the words order,
which you might imagine is important for understanding language.
It also ignores grammatical structure of sentences,
like it ignores punctuation.
The other issue is that each token representation that
the model uses has very limited semantic meaning.
For each token, it just records if a word was present in the input text.
The final issue we will talk about is that the model
can't handle words if we didn't see them during training.
While this model can work reasonably well on some simple tasks,
in most cases, we need to use more sophisticated models.
Now we will talk about two improvement for this simple approach.
First of all, we will talk about a better way to represent words, and second,
we will talk about more advanced neural network architectures for NLP tasks.