Before we dive into how transformer models the work,
we will cover the basics of NLP.
NLP stands for natural language processing,
which is a branch of AI that aims at
understanding and communicating using human language.
Transformers is of course a part of a much larger NLP field.
Since transformers were not created in a vacuum to understand how they work,
we would need to have some prior knowledge in the area of NLP.
In the next few videos,
we'll cover a few topics that include tokenization,
which is a process of converting a text into
smaller parts that machine learning model can process, embeddings,
which is a way to represent words of a text as a multi-dimensional vectors,
and we'll also look into some simpler models that preceded transformers.
First, let's talk about how AI models can process text.
All machine learning models work with numbers,
so we need to convert a text into numbers first.
If we have a text like this for a machine learning model to handle it,
we first need to split it into individual chunks.
For example, we can split it into individual awards and convert each award into a number.
We need to do this consistently so that
the same word is always converted into the same number.
For example, we can decide that the word welcome is always represented as number 11,
and that the word course is represented as number 45, and so on.
These numbers are called token IDs,
and this is what our models will work with instead of working with words.
It doesn't matter what numbers were assigned to each word as
long as the same word is always converted into the same number.
If we have another sentence,
the way we convert words into numbers should be consistent.
The same words should be converted into the same IDs,
like the word course is converted into number 45.
In order for our model to process any sentence,
we need to know the words we can encounter
and decide what IDs we will assign to each one of them.
To get the list of words,
we need to get a large collection of text and find all distinct words in it.
To demonstrate this process,
I've shown here a small text sample,
but in reality, we need to have a much larger set of text.
We need to split this text into individual words and find all unique words in this text.
Each unique word will get its own unique ID.
This table is called a vocabulary,
and we can now use it to convert a new input text into a sequence of IDs,
our model would be able to process.
Then if we want to process a new sentence,
we need to split it into tokens and find a corresponding ID for each word.
For example, the word large,
has ID 1, the word on has ID 5, and so on.
In practice to build a good vocabulary,
we need to process a lot of text,
like all Wikipedia articles, for example.
This will give us a list of all English words,
as well as misspelled words,
any words that are rarely used,
words in languages we don't intend to process, and so on.
We would end up with an enormous vocabulary,
so to handle it, we will limit our vocabulary to the list of most common words.
Say we would only use the most common 100,000 words or so.
The downside of this approach is that some input text
might include words that are not in our vocabulary.
It can be because we've limited our vocabulary size or
because we simply didn't see a particular word when we were creating one.
For example, if we don't have words from the physics domain in our vocabulary,
our model might have issues processing a sentence like this.
A common way to handle it is to replace unknown words with
a special token that represents an unknown word with its own unique ID,
and pass this as an input to our model.
The downside of this is that
an unknown token does not provide a lot of information for our model.
Splitting an input text into words is not the only option.
We can split an input text into individual characters.
In this case, the process will be the same,
but instead of building a vocabulary of words,
we'll build a vocabulary of characters,
and every character will have an ID,
we will convert it into.
Then when tokenizing a sentence,
we will split it into individual characters,
and each character is converted into its own ID.
Character level tokenization is a simple and useful technique that we'll also use.
One benefit of character level tokenization is that it will be able
to handle new words because it just splits them into individual characters.
However, the main downside is that each individual token is much
less meaningful compared to a token in the world level tokenization process.
The last approach we will look into is called a subword tokenization.
In this case, the input vocabulary consists of full words,
as well as chunks of words.
For example, in this sentence,
similar words like pairs or involves are individual tokens with their own IDs.
While the word quantum is split into two tokens,
each with its own ID.
Using subword tokenization helps with handling unknown words.
If our model finds an unknown word,
it can still split it into multiple tokens and make sense out of it.
This approach is used by real world LLMs, such as GPT.
If you want to experiment with it and if you want to try how it works,
you can use the tiktoken library,
a library that GPT is using to tokenize input sentences.