In the previous videos,
we've discussed a simple way to represent each token for our machine learning model.
We were converting each token ID into a vector where all values would be zero,
except for a position equal to vector ID,
which would be set to one.
There is, however, a different way of representing tokens.
Instead, each word can be represented as a smaller multidimensional vector,
where every value would represent
a certain characteristic of a word relevant to our model.
What are the meaning of these values?
Well, we don't set them upfront.
We only decide on what size of vectors we want to
use and then train a model to create these vectors.
These vectors are also called embedding vectors.
The actual meaning of each particular number is not necessarily interpretable.
However, these vectors have some interesting properties we will discuss later.
Embedding vectors usually contain hundreds or even thousands of dimensions.
Unfortunately, we humans are not good at visualizing thousand dimensions vectors.
Instead, we will display two dimensional vectors in this video,
but the properties that we will discuss will be
relevant in real-world embedding vectors as well.
One interesting property of embedding vectors is that words
with similar meanings will be represented by similar vectors.
For example, if we have vectors for words laptop and computer,
they will have similar values and will be close to
all other vectors representing words related to computers and tech.
On the other hand, if we have another group of words like orange and banana,
they will be close to each other,
but they will be far away from technology related vectors.
Given two vectors in a multidimensional space,
we can compute how similar they are.
To do this, we can use an operation called
dot product that works for vectors of any size.
But we will see how it works using an example of three dimensional vectors.
Dot product is represented using a dot symbol,
and it is computed in the following way.
To calculate dot product,
we take the first pair of values from both vectors and multiply them together.
We then take the second pair and multiply them together as well.
Then the next pair, and then we add the result of these three pairwise multiplications.
This is a result of the dot product.
Mathematically, dot product is the final exist.
We multiply a pair of values for each position,
and then we sum up these multiplication results together.
Now, how do we interpret the result of a dot product?
If the result is positive,
it means that vectors are similar like on the image on the right,
which in turn means that the words have similar meaning.
The greater the value of a dot product,
the greater the similarity between two words.
If the dot product result is close to zero,
it means that the words are unrelated.
For example, these can be words from
completely different domains like technology and food.
If the dot product is negative,
it means that the words have opposite meanings like words hot and cold.
Another interesting property of embedding vectors is that we can
perform mass operation between them and get interesting results.
A classic example is,
if we take a vector for the word woman and subtract the vector for the word man from it,
and then add the result vector to the word king.
We will get a vector that is very close to the vector that represents the word queen.
If we reorder this expression a bit,
we will have an expression that says that the difference between word queen and
king is similar to the difference between the words woman and man.
Other vectors have similar relationships.
For example, difference between mother and father,
also similar to difference between words women and men.
Another interesting relationship is if we subtract Rome from Paris,
it will be similar to the difference between France and Italy,
and if we subtract Europe from euro,
It will be similar to the difference between dollar and America.
There are two ways to get word embeddings.
One way we can use an independent model that was trained specifically to compute
word embeddings for a particular vocabulary, unrelated to transformers.
You can download these models and use them in your applications.
However, when we're training a transformer model,
it will learn word embeddings as part of its training process,
so we don't need a separate library in this case.
To wrap up our conversation of embedding vectors,
let's briefly talk about how we could use them in a simple model.
Having an input sentence,
we can tokenize it and convert each token into a separate embedding vector.
We can then flatten this vector and pass it into a feed forward neural network.
However, instead of using a feed forward network,
we can also use architectures designed
specifically for processing sequential data like text.
This is something that we will look into in the next videos.