Now let's talk about another model architecture that was designed
specifically for processing sequential data like text or audio.
This model architecture is called recurrent neural network or RNN for short.
Previously, in all network architectures,
we were looking into the data was going straight from
inputs to outputs via one or multiple heating layers in between.
Also, all input data was processed at once.
We had to have all input data at once and pass it through the neural network.
RNNs change both of these constraints.
With the RNN architecture,
we take the first input token and pass it through the network.
Once the first token is processed by the network,
we take the next token and pass it through the same network again.
But now in addition to the new token,
we also take the output of the hidden layer from
the previous step and use it as an additional input,
and we do the same thing on the next step.
We keep the output of the hidden layer from
the previous step and use it as an input together with the next token.
The idea here is that the output of the hidden layer that is called the hidden state
preserves some information about the previous inputs that we've already processed.
When the model is processing the next token,
it can access some information about tokens it saw before.
For this to work, we also need to pass
some initial empty state when processing the first token.
RNNs is a great choice if we need to work with text,
but they can also be used with other sequential data like audio,
time series, et cetera.
RNNs are commonly displayed in a compact form like this,
where we have this recurrent connection.
Now, here are some ways we can use RNNs.
For classification purposes, we can ignore outputs from all steps,
except the last one and use the last output to classify an input text,
for example, to classify it into spam or non spam.
We would pass an input text,
token by token, [inaudible] this network,
and on the final step,
we should have some information about
the previously processed words that we can use to make a classification decision.
There are also other RNN variations such as one to many RNN,
where we provide an initial input,
and then the model generates multiple output tokens.
This architecture is good for text generation or music generation.
The other variation is called many to many RNNs,
where we first read an input sequence that consists of multiple tokens,
and then the model can generate multiple output tokens one by one.
This approach can be used to translate text from one language to another.
RNNs worked for many different tasks,
however, they have a few issues.
First of all, RNNs have difficulty accessing previous states.
We have a single state that we need to update on every iteration,
and the model will have issues retaining information from tokens it saw long time ago.
The other issue with RNNs is called diminishing gradient.
This happens when the gradient during training becomes too small in deep networks,
which leads to slow training and the network
can't capture dependencies over large time intervals.
There were a number of improvements to the basic RNN architecture,
such as LSTM or long short term memory,
or GRU, which is gated recurrent unit.
These architectures help with some of the drawbacks of classic cardan approach.
However, the next breakthrough in NLP came from using
the transformers architecture and the attention mechanism it uses.