In this video, we will talk about transformer architecture,
which is the core innovation behind the Generative AI boom.
It allows [inaudible] models to process,
understand, and generate text.
This architecture was first presented in the Attention is All You Need paper,
and was originally designed to translate text from one language to the other.
But in this course, we won't implement the architecture presented in the original paper.
Instead, we will cover a different architecture used by models like GPT,
LLaMA, and other similar models.
In addition to being used by these popular models,
it will be easier to understand and implement,
but closer to the end of this lesson,
we will compare it to the original architecture and learn how does it differ.
Now, let's start with a 10,000-feet overview of how transformer model works.
When we have an input prompt,
we first split it into separate tokens.
We convert each token into token ID
and then convert each token ID into its own embedding vector.
I made here a few details on how the wording embeddings are processed,
but for now, I want to focus just on the core aspects of how it works.
One thing to note here is that the same token ID will produce the same embedding vector.
This is just a simple mapping from a token ID to a corresponding embedding vector.
Once we have the input wording beddings,
we pass them to the attention block that updates embeddings to refine their meaning.
Here is an example of why it might be useful.
Let's consider two sentences.
One is her favorite fruit is a date and the other one,
Kate and Josh went on a date.
Both of these sentences have word date,
but it has different meaning in both sentences.
In the first sentence, it is the name of a fruit,
and in the second sentence,
it is an appointment to meet someone.
However, after we convert input to embedding vectors,
we will end up with the same embedding vectors for the word date in both sentences.
To fix this, the attention mechanism in transformer architecture will update
the embedding vectors based on the context
of the other embedding vectors forming the input.
In the first sentence, it might use the word fruit to update the meaning of
the vector for word date to represent that this is a fruit that you can eat.
In the second sentence, it can use some other words to update the meaning of
the embedding vector to represent that this is an appointment to meet.
The process of interaction between embedding vectors is called attention,
and each embedding vector is influenced by other embedding vectors in the text,
depending on the context of the text.
To update the values of embedding vectors,
the attention block calculates the attention scores.
We will cover how these values are calculated in more details,
but it shows the attention scores between each pair of input tokens.
These attention scores are then used to
update embedding vectors for all tokens in the input.
Once we run the input through the attention block,
we get updated embedding vectors that should better
represent the meaning of each token in the context of the input.
Once we run the input through the attention block,
we get updated embedding vectors that should better
represent the meaning of each token in the context of the input.
The attention mechanism is the most important part of the transformer architecture.
After we get an output from an attention block,
we pass it to the feed-forward network.
This combination of the attention block and
the feed-forward network form a transformer block,
or how it is also called a layer of a transformer model.
We then chain multiple layers together when
output from one layer becomes the input into another layer.
Then we repeat the process again and again until we get
the output from the last layer, and then at the end,
we get the probability distribution for what our model
considers to be the next token you should generate given its input.
Here it gives 68% probability for a token with a particular token ID.
If you're not familiar with the softmax function, don't worry.
We will cover how it works and what is the rationale behind it just a bit later.
Transformers have a few benefits comparing to other models.
First, transformers can process input in parallel.
They can process the whole input prompt all at once.
They can access information in longer text much more
efficiently and they're much easier to train comparing to RNN models.
Most importantly, they perform amazingly well on real-world tasks.
One other thing that we need to cover regarding LLMs is the concept of a context window.
Context window is the maximum number of tokens,
a model can handle at once,
and it includes an input prompt and the output that model has generated so far.
If we have a text that is longer than the context window of our model,
then our model won't be able to see all of it at once.
The size of the context window depends on the model we use.
In a smaller model,
it is limited to just 2,000 tokens,
like in the first version of GPT3.
But there are models with the context window that is greater than
1.5 million tokens like recent Gemini models.
Keep in mind that one word is not equal to one token since
tokenizers can split a single word into several tokens.
For example, in GPT model,
on average, it takes four tokens to represent three words.