A lot of times you'll be working
with projects that require
different library versions or
different versions of python even.
In my experience and in many other
people's' it's really difficult to get
all these versions to play
nicely together on one computer.
To solve this problem we use virtual
environments managed with libraries such
as Virtualenv.
Virtual environments let you
separate libraries required by
different projects, so
you can avoid conflicts.
If you're working with data though,
Anaconda is the way to go.
Anaconda is a distribution of libraries
and software specifically built for
data science.
It comes with Conda, a package and
environment manager that will make
your life a thousand times better.
Now I'll show you a bit
about using Conda.
I generally create a new environment for
each project I start,
this way I can keep the necessary
package versions separate.
For example if I want to start
a new project using Python 3.
Which you should be using for
all new projects,
I can create an environment for it.
Type in conde create,
give it a name, tea_facts.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
It's a bot that tweets
facts about tea and
the python version, three and enter.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
This will create the environment for me.
Now, I can enter the environment
like so, source activate tea_facts.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
This is the command on Mac in Linux,
on Window it's just activate.
Now I'm in the environment,
you can see the name in the prompt.
And you can see here
the packages that are installed,
these are just the default packages.
Now I can start installing
what I want for this projects.
Let's install Numpy Pandas, for working
with the t data and matplotlib for
making visualization.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Then I'll start notebooks which
I like to use to develop code.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
And again looking at
the installed packages.
I have all these ready to use for
my project.
And these are separated
from other environments, so
I won't run into any
conflicting version issues.
Okay, now it's your turn to learn how
to use Conda for your own projects,
because that thing will take
around 30 minutes up to an hour.
Okay, have fun.