In this project, you'll have the opportunity to demonstrate the skills you've
developed in this course by building an object detection system using PyTorch.
To do this project,
you'll need to pull together the new deep learning skills you've just learned,
such as data augmentation and building
neural networks in order to solve a real-world problem.
Here's the scenario.
Imagine you're a machine-learning engineer working for a self-driving car startup.
Your management team is looking for
an object detection algorithm for stationary objects that may be on the side of the road.
They're considering purchasing a computer vision algorithm from Detectocorp,
which boasts a 70 percent accuracy rate on a benchmark dataset called CIFAR-10.
They've asked you to take some time to determine whether or not they should buy
the software or develop something in the house.
Your job is to run your own in-house model on
the same CIFAR-10 dataset used by
Detectocorp to see how the accuracy compares with theirs.
CIFAR-10 is a classic dataset used to benchmark results in computer vision research,
it's a subset of the 80 million tiny images dataset and it was released by
researchers at the Canadian Institute For Advanced Research or CIFAR in 2009.
The 10 comes from the 10 classes that the images are divided into: birds, cars, cats,
dear, dogs, frogs, horses,
airplanes, ships, and trucks.
Each image has an associated label so that you can compare
the accuracy of your image classifier with the known identity of each image.
There are 6,000 images in each of the 10 classes across the training and test sets.
The dataset is built into many popular libraries,
including the one we'll use, torchvision.
As you can see from the images,
the resolution is quite low;
they're tiny images, only 32 pixels by 32 pixels.
As I just mentioned,
one of the keys to CIFAR-10 is it uses
a benchmark for comparing computer vision algorithms.
In this sense, it is similar to other classic datasets you may have heard of,
such as MNIST or ImageNet.
Over the past years,
CIFAR-10 along with these other classic datasets like MNIST and ImageNet,
have been widely used to test and improve scores of different models.
In this table, we can see the progressive improvement from
the relatively modest Convolutional Deep Belief Networks in
2010 with an accuracy of 78.9 percent to the massive network GPipe released in 2018,
which achieved an impressive 99 percent classification accuracy.
Of course, GPipe is one of the largest computer vision models ever trained,
so we should expect a nearly 20 percent increase in accuracy.
Don't worry if you can't beat these results,
these are advanced models with carefully chosen and tuned hyper-parameters
trained by scientists in some of the most well-funded research labs on Earth.
Since there are 10 classes in the dataset,
random guessing gives us about a 10 percent accuracy rate,
so anything over 50 percent is good and anything over 70 percent is really great.
Let's see where you can put your name on the board.