We'll be doing the entire project in a single notebook.
Let's look at the overall process.
First, we'll be using
torchvision.transforms and data loaders to prepare and explore our data.
Next, we'll use the PyTorch functions that you learn during the course,
along with a loss function and an optimizer to build and train our neural network.
Then on the test set,
we will test our neural network's performance.
Then we'll compare that performance with the performance reported by detect or corpse,
and based on these results,
we'll make a recommendation on whether it is better to build or buy a solution.
Now, let's walk through the notebook so you can
see what this looks like on a more concrete level.
At the top of the notebook,
well have some benchmark results on CIFAR-10 that you can feel free to explore,
and we'll include your imports for you.
Next, you'll load your data.
You'll put your code where it says your code here throughout the notebook.
Then you need to create your transforms,
a dataset and a data loader using torch.vision datasets and torch.utils.data.
The data loader is what will actually feed images to your neural network.
Next, you'll need to explore
the dataset so that you can get a sense of what the images look like.
You should check the size of the images,
how many color channels are in it,
and how many images are in both the training and the test set.
To view the images,
we've provided a pre-written helper function called show 5,
which will show you five arbitrary images from the data loader.
Once you have an idea of the size and shape of your data,
you move on to building your neural network.
The size and shape of your data will tell you what your input size
is so that you can specify the right dimensions at each layer.
Once you've built your neural network,
you'll need to specify a loss function and
optimizer so that the accuracy of your neural network improves,
rather than just being a function of random weights.
You'll train your neural network and record your loss at each epoch.
It's important to record your loss so that you can verify your network is
actually learning and the error rate is going down as the network trains.
If your loss starts increasing,
you may be overfeeding your dataset.
To see this change in loss visually,
you'll want to plot your training loss using Matplotlib.
You'll finally go ahead and test your model
on that test set that you specified at the top.
Testing your model will allow you to verify that
your network can classify images it hasn't seen yet.
Ultimately, this is how we're going to be able to compare
our network to detect or corpse model accuracy.
Once you have your evaluation accuracy,
you'll want to save your model using
torch.save so that it can be loaded and reused again in the future.
Finally, at the bottom of the notebook,
you'll want to double-click that last cell to write up why
you made the architectural decisions that you made and what
your recommendation is of whether to build or buy based on
what you know about CIFAR-10 and your model's test set accuracy.
When you're finished with this project,
you will have built a real-world object detection algorithm
and compare its accuracy with an industry benchmark.
Although the scenario in this project is fictional,
it's not unlike the types of problems you might be asked to
solve as a real machine-learning engineer working in the field.