My name is Golois Mouelet.
I'm a field engineer at Microsoft.
Hi, my name is Ann Hoang and I currently work at Raytheon Technologies.
I'm Nathan Anderson.
I work at the Goodyear Tire and Rubber Company as a DevOps engineer.
I'm Chris Vazquez and I work at Udacity as a Curriculum Manager.
What I love most about my job is not only interacting with customers,
but also designing and architecting
scalable applications using the latest Azure services.
What I like most about my job is the opportunities to automate things,
and then a typical day of work for me is interacting with my team
and consulting other teams on automating processes that could be automated.
I love my job because it's challenging.
It's not easy.
I'm looking and I'm surrounded by co-workers who are really good and that pushes me
to work hard to write clean code and also as a coder,
has some value to society.
I believe that everyone should take this ND because it allows you to
gain hands-on experience from topics ranging from Azure services,
a service bus, storage queue and so it just allows everyone depending on your level,
whether you're just entry, or are you advanced?
So everyone should take it to broaden their knowledge on Azure and Azure services.
I think one thing that students will love about this course is
just how easy it is to work with Azure,
as well as the hands-on experience that they'll get
while working through all the exercises as well as the project.
You can build something that takes a lot less time than it used to.
Everything is decouple.
Instead of creating an API,
you have a model that serves an endpoint,
all in one program.
Each endpoint, each service like getNote,
that is his own decoupled code that's running and it makes it very easy to debug.
You're going to find that the market is very
starved for people with these skills right now.
So you're gonna be getting a lot of phone calls and a lot of emails.
Or if you take this back to your current position,
you're going to begin to want more responsibilities.
It actually can be very fun to do and to implement a solution like this,
because at the end of the day,
once that's done and working how you want it,
everyone's going to love it and problems are just going to go away
and know that you've solved a lot of different problems.
It's not just my field that is using this.
I've learned that the person,
the government is really interested in using the same microservice and implementation.
It's very cross-discipline.
This course is awesome because it shows you how to implement a monitoring solution,
as well as hand-off your work to the robots.
As soon as you take this course because it provides the foundational knowledge
of Azure as well as hands-on experience with working with Azure's platform.
If you take this course,
you should be able to implement
all the serverless function and go out and build your own service.
I'm looking forward to you learning about Azure Batch, Azure function, WebJob,
Java services so that you can go back and deploy scalable services to Azure.