We start our exploration of any data set with
univariate visualizations or visualizations of single variables.
By looking at one variable at a time,
we can build an intuition for how each variable is distributed
before moving on to more complicated interactions between variables.
When you start looking at any data set,
keep in mind the goals of your investigation and explore
the variables that will be key to answering your research questions.
If we observe any oddities in the data such as outliers, or missing values,
this can point us to areas where we need to do
more cleaning or otherwise perform further inspection.
It often makes sense to integrate this part of
the exploration process into parts of the data wrangling process.
This lesson will focus on two different plot types,
bar charts for qualitative variables and histograms for quantitative variables.
While both of these plot types take the appearance of rectangles on a pair of axes,
you will see how datatype makes these plots distinct.
You will also learn how to use code to create these plots
as well as how to use these plots to gain an understanding of your data.