The visualizations you create will give you insights into
the data that you can't get from descriptive statistics.
A plot can immediately tell you if your data is symmetric or skewed,
if it is unimodal or multimodal.
Plots can also indicate interesting areas for further investigation and clarification.
Categories in a bar chart with low counts might point to errors in
the data or if you see that bars have values that counter your expectations,
then that might point towards further research or a revisiting of data assumptions.
For example, let's say you're looking at a distribution of user birth months.
Seeing an unusually large number of
January responses might suggest a deeper investigation such as whether
there are a lot of users who are just submitting
default information or if there's something wrong with how the data has been recorded.
In a histogram, one of the most salient bits of information
that you can observe is whether or not there are outliers in your data.
If the plot covers an unexpected range,
this can point to the presence of unusual points that are worth further investigation.
In some cases, like if you have highly skewed data,
you might want to change the range of the data plotted in
order to zoom into parts that are more interesting.
Rather than filtering on the original data,
you can simply make changes to the axis limits to make your observations.
Let's say that we make a plot of ride durations in minutes for a bike-sharing service,
and obtain a plot as shown.
There are a few outliers in the last bar from 1,400 to
1,500 minutes that cause all of the other points to be fit into the first bar.
While we might want to look at those outlier points later,
we could first just change the axis limits
to see the shape of where most of the data points lie.
When we limit the access to 60 minutes,
and use bins of five-minutes wide,
we get a clear picture that
the typical ride length lies between five and 15-minute range.