In this video, we're going to look at how to change access limits and also
examine outliers in our distributions using Matplotlib functions.
As always, the first thing we're going to do is import the libraries we need,
as well as import our dataset.
We'll continue working with the diamonds dataset here.
We're going to start by looking at the diamond price,
the units for this variable are in US dollars.
Let's zoom in around the $2,000
mark because here we see the distribution has a discontinuity,
and I'm curious what might be going on.
In order to zoom in at this area,
we can use the x
limit function xlim to set the upper and lower bounds of displaying bins.
Here, I'm setting the bins or the upper limits to the bins, from $1000-$5,000.
Anticipation of this reduced access limit have
also altered the bin range from what I showed earlier,
from going from $100 step size to 50.
Here, we can see that there tends to be this dip right around $1,500,
and I'm wondering if this might be for some psychological sales pitch.
The reason I think this is a psychological or sales pitch,
is because $1,500 might be a limit between certain grades of diamonds,
and people might feel they're getting a good deal if it's $1,499 versus 1,500.