In this video, we're going to look at how to scale and transform our axis.
We're going to start as always,
by importing the necessary libraries and our dataset.
In this exercise, we'll be focused on the diamonds dataset.
We're going to look specifically at diamond price.
This variable is quite skewed.
One thing we might want to do is we might consider that
this price is logarithmically distributed and not distributed in a base 10 system.
So we're going to transform the axis and take a look.
To do this, we're going to be using the matplotlib xscale function.
This takes a string such as log or semi-log.
In this case, for our histogram,
I am going to collect the axis object and then use the same function set_xscale.
Notice, this plot looks pretty weird.
The x limits themselves are not changed, but they're scaled.
In order to get a more interpretable plot,
we're going to need to modify the bin boundaries
and generate more informative access texts.
Let's start by looking at the bin boundaries.
If we look at the price and do a describe on that column,
we will see that the minimum price is a little over $300.
The maximum price is almost $20,000.
If we're going to assume that price is logarithmically distributed,
we then have to look at the logarithm of this,
which we can use the NumPy.
Now we see the log of these values.
The minimum is two-and-a-half,
whereas the maximum is almost four-and-a-half.
These give us the limits for our bins.
Our bin edges will be 10 to the power values between two and five,
so that they're evenly spaced.
Just what we have right here.
These are now our bins.
This plot looks a lot better.
It shows that in a logarithmic space,
we have almost a unimodal distribution.
However, the tick marks are very hard to see and not quite interpretable.
We can start by writing out the given ticks,
but really, we just want to add a few more.
Here's where we need to do some hardcoding.
Because of the powers of 10,
things aren't nice and evenly spaced as they would be normally.
A three is about halfway between consecutive powers of 10 on a log scale.
Adding these values to a ticks list will complete this exploratory plot.
For example, the x ticks,
ticks we're interested in are a 100,
300, a 1,000 and likewise 3,000,
and ending at 30.
We then also, we'll create our list of
labels by taking each of these ticks and converting them to a string.
Then after we plot the histogram and scale the axis,
we apply the x ticks.
This is much easier to read.
One thing I would like to caution you is if you add the x ticks before scaling the axis,
they will get overwritten.
That's a common mistake.