Great job. You've taken your first steps in visualizing your data.
In this lesson, you'll learned about the plots and code that you can use to
visualize and understand individual variables in your data set.
For quantitative variables, the most common plot type is
the histogram and for qualitative variables,
the most common plot type is the bar chart.
You learned about the limitations of pie charts and
doughnut charts and how they can be used effectively.
You also learned about techniques to help you identify
trends in the data and deal with outliers.
On the vertical axis,
you learned how to report frequencies in terms of
absolute counts or as relative frequencies.
For quantitative data, you also learned how to set parameters in
your functions to set axis limits and to change the scale of measurements.
The observations you make during
the unit variate stage of exploration will help you start to answer
your research questions or generate more specific questions for further investigation.
In the next lesson, you will learn how to create bivariate visualizations so you can
observe the relationships between pairs of variables in your data set. See you there.