Hi there. I hope you're ready to start using Python to visualize your data.
In this course, we will use NumPy and pandas to store our data.
We will also use Matplotlib and Seaborn to create our visualizations.
Now, you might see the abbreviation SB for Seaborn,
but SNS is considered best practice.
I'll be using that.
We will also write and run all of our code using Jupyter Notebooks.
Let's start by importing our normal Python libraries.
Let's introduce our dataset. We're going to load it.
It's called the diamonds dataset,
and it consists of 53 or 54,000 rows by 10 columns,
and each column represents a feature.
Some are categorical and some are quantitative.
They could be things like carat size,
diamond cut, color, or clarity.
Could also include numerical data such as price or table width.
Let's start by creating a bar chart on the diamond cut variable and let's use Seaborn.
To start of with, to create a bar chart,
we want to make sure or we want to make use of the Seaborn function count plot.
Here, we set the data source as our DataFrame and we list that we want
an x-axis variable and it's going to be the variable in the DataFrame called cut.
When we run this cell,
this is what we see.
Now, it's not strictly necessary,
but this semicolon here suppresses printing of plotting object information.
From this plot, we can see that most of the diamonds are ideal cut,
while good and fair are the least common.
One thing that bothers me about the default settings here
is that each bar is illustrated using a different color.
The cut is already encoded by position on the x-axis,
we don't have a good reason right now to
associate each generation with a different color.
It's much better to start by plotting everything in one color to avoid any distractions.
There are several ways to do this.
I'm going to show you two.
One is to choose a color value using Seaborn's color palette function.
This function returns a list of tuples
corresponding to the color palette set in the function's argument.
In this case, I'm just going to use the default.
You can see here, that this is the array or list of the default colors.
Let's just take the first element from this list.
We're going to index of zero.
We're now going to set that into a variable called color.
Now when our count plot,
if we add the parameter color and set that to our variable,
we now see this much better.
Another way to specify the color we want is to just name it.
Here, I select a very common color palette,
the Tableau of a color palette.
Here we set Tableau blue.
Now, one thing we might want to do with the plot is to
sort the chart in decreasing order of prevalence.
This can be done by introducing a new parameter in the count plot function, order.
This parameter takes a list as an argument with the order in which bar should be plotted.
We could hardcode the values into a specific list.
For example, we could create a list that starts with
ideal and premium and then very good, etc.
But this is tedious and we might have
a large number of different categories for the x value.
Instead, it's better to automate this.
We can do that by using the pandas function value counts.
This operates on a series or a column from a DataFrame.
Value counts summarizes the total number of counts for each category of variable.
It does this and produces this list in descending order of prevalence.
In order to get the bar order,
we just want the index and here we set it to a variable called order,
and pass that into our count plot with a parameter called order.
Voila. Now we have a decreasing bar chart.
Now, one thing we might also be interested in is making these x labels be rotated.
For instance, maybe we're looking to catch somebody's eye,
or maybe we have very,
very long x labels.
In order to do that, we can use Matplotlib's x text function.
All we do is pass in the parameter that we're interested in,
which could be like 15 degrees.
We see that here.
Alternatively, we could also just switch
this to a horizontal bar chart instead of a vertical,
and that is very simple.
We just switch the perimeter x to parameter y,
and once again,
Seaborn knows how to plot that.