In this video, we're going to look at both absolute and relative frequency plots.
We're going to start by importing the necessary libraries, numpy, pandas,
matplotlib, and Seaborn, and also read in our dataset, the diamonds dataset.
Now, if we're interested in plotting
absolute values or the total number of counts for a variable,
we can use a count plot, for instance,
we can use value counts to look at
the total number of counts for each diamond clarity grade.
We can use value counts to get the order in decreasing prevalence.
We can use a count plot to make a vertical or horizontal absolute frequency plot.
Here we're using a horizontal frequency plot.
However, if we want to answer the question,
what percentage of diamonds are internally flawless?
That's the IF grade.
Well, here would have to do some mental math and estimate.
Now instead, we could create a relative frequency plot.
In order to do that, we can't use a count plot,
because a count plot requires integer values and we're looking to plot a proportion,
so instead we must use a bar plot.
The first thing we need to do is normalize the data.
There are two ways to do this.
We can still use value counts, except instead,
we can just pass in normalize equals true.
This will provide the normalized values where the total number of
counts for each type is divided by the total number of counts in the dataset.
Then we can convert this series into a full DataFrame,
which is what we're doing right here.
Then we can pass this into the bar plot, just like before.
Now we see the total number of diamonds that are internally
flawless is around 3 and a 1/2 or 4%.
The SI1, which is the most frequent grade,
is almost a quarter of the data.
Alternatively, maybe we could combine
an absolute frequency plot with a relative frequency plot.
This is where matplotlib shines,
because it is so flexible.
Here what we're going to do is we're going to go back to using a count plot,
except we are then going to iterate over
each bar and then we're going to convert it into a percentage.
What we're going to end up doing is creating a string where we look at
the count of that quality grade divided by
the total number of counts in the entire dataset.
Here we see that now we have both access to
the absolute number of
each clarity grade in our dataset as well as the relative proportion.