You're probably familiar with one other plot type that is used for
plotting relative frequencies for qualitative variables, the pie chart.
In a pie chart, each category is indicated by a slice of
a circle with the area indicating the relative frequency of that category.
A variant of the pie chart, the donut plot,
is very similar except that the center of the circle has been removed, leaving a donut.
Most of the time, you'll probably prefer a bar chart over either on these two plots.
It is actually fairly difficult to get an accurate estimate of
relative frequency from a pie or donut plot alone.
If there are a lot of categories,
there are major limitations on how many categories can be plotted in a readable way.
A bar chart will usually be more versatile and should be
your first choice for exploring qualitative variables.
That's not to say that pie or donut charts should never be used however.
If you want to use one of these charts,
then you should keep in mind a few guidelines.
First of all, you only want to use a pie chart if you want to
show how the whole of the data is broken down into parts.
Second, you should plan on only plotting a small number of slices.
A pie chart works best with two or three slices,
so that the relative portions are distinct.
If you determine that a pie chart meet these two criteria,
you should then organize your plot to clearly convey the information in your data.
Usually, you should start planning from the 12 o'clock position and
then mark slices clockwise in order of frequency.
There are other reasonable ways of generating a pie chart,
but you should consider your data carefully about both
whether you should use a pie chart and how best to present it.