If you have a quantitative variable,
then your univariate plot of choice will probably be the histogram.
Similar to a bar chart you have feature values on the x-axis and counts on the y-axis.
However, due to the numeric nature of the data,
bars in a histogram do not indicate counts on
single values but instead counts on value ranges.
In this histogram, we have plotted 30 values with bins of size three.
The first bin on the left counts two data
points that take a value between zero and three,
the second bin counts four points between three and six and so on.
Normally, bins include values on their left end and exclude values on their right end.
So the datapoint with value 6.0 will go into the bin on its right.
The size of the bins can have a major effect on how you interpret the data.
If your bin size is too large,
then you may end up losing a lot of information about the overall distribution of data.
On the opposite side, a too small bin size can
introduce noise that can distract from the main trends in your data.
When creating a histogram,
it's a good idea to play around with different settings for the bin sizes and
boundary points to achieve a good understanding of the plotted variable.