In this video, we're now going to plot numeric or quantitative variables.
As always, we're going to start by importing the libraries we need,
as well as the dataset.
In this case,
we'll continue by looking at the diamonds dataset we've used before.
In particular, I now want to look at the x,
y, and z width of a diamond.
These are given in terms of millimeters.
Now, to plot a histogram,
matplotlib offers the hist function,
like what we've seen before we pass in the dataset to a data variable and then we
can explicitly say we want an x histogram looking at the x parameter.
By default, matplotlib breaks the data into 10 bins,
which is usually too few.
In addition, the bin boundaries are not aligned with the tick marks.
This is somewhat confusing.
Despite that, we can see that this is
a unimodal histogram with a slightly right-skewed distribution.
But because of that number of bins,
we just really can't get much else.
To solve this, we really want to use the bin parameter for the hist function.
The bin parameter can take an integer number of bins,
and then it will automatically break the axis in to that number of bins,
in this case 25.
We see that now we're getting more information.
Also notice that if I remove the semicolon,
we get the plotting objects which previously we had been ignoring.
In this case, it is the actual binning array.
Instead a better way would be to explicitly define the bins ourself.
We can do that by using the numpy arange function to define the array of bin edges.
Here, I'm going to make an array of width bin size 1/4 of a millimeter.
Now the first argument for arange is the minimum value.
Here is 0. The second argument, the maximum value.
In this case, we ask for the maximum value of that column x.
This third variable is the step size,
in this case, 1/4 of a millimeter.
Notice also that for the maximum value,
I go one bin further.
This is because the values generated by arange include the lower bound,
but not the maximum value,
not the upper bound,
only those things that are strictly lower/ by so adding an extra step size,
this means that all values can be represented in the chart.
Now, I take
this variable bins and pass it into the parameter bins of the histogram function.
Now I see something like this.
Now we see that the data is approximately unimodal,
safe for a bit of a dip in these 7-8 millimeter range.
Now, what happens if we try an extremely small bin size like 1?
On the one hand, this bin size is perhaps a bit too small,
introducing a lot of noise.
On the other hand, it does a good job of showing that
many diamonds are probably rounded to some nearest value.
Seaborne also has a function for creating histograms.
This is called histplot,
and it works just like matplotlib.
A couple of things.
One, you'll notice the default bin count is larger than matplotlib.
Second, if you'd like to normalize it to show the percent of each bin to the whole,
you can pass in a parameter stat, short-course statistic.
Then this shows you the total proportion of each bin to the whole.
One other thing that might be of interest is there's parameter kde = True.
This adds a kernel density estimate on top of the plot.
A KDE is an estimate of the density of
the data distribution and the total area underneath the curve is set to 1.
If you're interested in this plot,
you can read up about it more at the extras at the end of this lesson.