This lesson goes into a bit more detail about the concepts of figures,
axes and subplots in matplotlib.
This is an area of much confusion with
new analyst because it's not always made clear what
the difference between a figure object and an axis is and how to interact with each.
But don't worry, it really isn't confusing.
We'll start simple and build up from there.
This is also a good time to note that seaborne is actually built on-top of matplotlib.
These concepts apply to it as well.
Remember, anything you can do with matplotlib,
you can also do to seaborne with a little work.
Let's start by importing our typical libraries and
also the diamond dataset to give us something to play with.
Now, the normal way most people interact with pyplot,
that's the main library of matplotlib,
is through pyplot functions.
Remember, we import these as PLT.
When you begin plotting anything,
the first thing that happens is a figure object is created.
For instance, when plotting a histogram,
it creates a figure that's the canvas that this is drawn on.
Then it draws a set of axes,
and then finally, the histogram on that axis.
It does all of this at once under the hood, so to speak.
We can start just by plotting or creating a figure directly.
Notice I am not plotting the trailing semicolon here,
so we get the plotting artifacts.
We see that it creates a figure of size 400 by 300 pixels with zero axes on top.
If we want to go further,
we can take this figure object and specifically set the access locations.
For instance, when we create a figure,
we can save it into a figure object,
and then we can add the axes locations specifically here.
Then on top of that axes,
we can then plot our histogram.
The Add Axes function is useful if you really want to get into customizing your plots.
Typically during explanatory analysis.
Often though, the default locations suffice.
But it's really worth experimenting with passing in
various locations to get a feel for how this works and what it looks like when you do.
Now, if you want to create two subplots within a figure,
you can use the pyplot method subplot.
This specifies n rows and m columns,
and then you can use it to iterate through each.
For instance, if we'd like to plot a grid of four histograms,
we can do that by creating our figure and then calling subplot.
Here, we'll have two rows and two columns,
and we want to take just subplot number 1.
Now, in this example,
I actually skipped Subplots 2 and 3 to show you what it looks like.
You don't have to plot them all.
Here. I just plot Subplot 1,
which is the upper left,
and subplot four, which is the lower right.
You can see here we created our canvas with four subplots,
but we're only using two currently.
That said, there is another way to interact with
plots and that's interacting with a specific access object.
Let's start by comparing what happens when you call pyplot directly.
Here we call pyplot directly calling the histogram function,
and then we want to set the x-axis label and also call pyplot directly.
Alternatively, we can use the pyplot function,
get current access or GCA to retrieve the axes object,
and then we can use the access function set
underscore x-label to set the x-label directly.
Note the difference is only a slightly different calling syntax.
One can interact with the figure directly using the pyplot functions.
If there were multiple subplots in the figure and
axon whatever the current active subplot is.
Or if you have a specific axis,
like this example, you can just interact or operate directly on it.
I find the axis notation to be convenient for two reasons.
One, if you want to create subplots,
you can act on them individually.
You don't have to iterate through them.
For example, if you use the pyplot function subplots.
Notice this is subplots with an S. You can
specify the number of rows and the number of columns,
and also the figure size directly.
This returns both the figure object and an array of axes objects.
If you want to plot two subplots next to each other,
you can just pass those directly to
seaborne or to matplotlib to operate directly on them.
Just like this.
Alternatively, seaborne typically returns axes objects.
if you don't specify the axes,
when you create a seaborne plot,
you can just retrieve the axis from the function call and then
operate directly on it to set whatever labels or adjustments you feel are necessary.