Have you ever been looking for a hat,
and find out that you're already wearing it.
Or looking for your keys,
and find out there in your back pocket.
Or looking for your backpack,
and you find out that it's on your back.
Turns out losing your remote is the same problem.
This chart highlights the seven places your remote is likely to be.
The top place is in your hand.
The least likely place that it is, is lost forever.
But before you think you are one of those two people,
make sure you check under the couch,
next to the TV, in the fridge,
in your shirt pocket,
and under the rug.
Before you blame the dog for eating your remote or thinking
alien came from space and stole your remote, check your hand.
It's unlikely your remote is gone forever.