Let's try creating another histogram of a different Pokemon attribute, height.
The units for this variable are in meters.
A plot of the statistic shows that it's fairly right-skewed,
with relatively few points above six meters in value.
It might be worth doing a zoom in of the main bulk
of the data through the use of axis limits.
We can use the matplotlib function xlim to set
the upper and lower bounds of the bins that will be displayed in the plot.
This function takes an argument, a list,
or tuple of two values specifying these limits.
In this case, I've set the axis limits from zero to six.
I've also changed the bin size in anticipation of this reduced axis limit.
In this case, there's actually not
that much additional illumination provided by the trimmed axis limits.
Most Pokemon species are human-sized or smaller,
with relatively few that are much taller than that.