Last time, we looked at height.
So, this time, let's look at Pokemon weight.
The units for this variable are in terms of kilograms.
The histogram of this variable is even more skewed than the height histogram,
with some species with value of over 800 kilograms.
Rather than trim the axis limits like before,
we'll try an axis transform instead.
Here, we want to use matplotlib.xscale function.
As an argument to this function,
we want to set a string corresponding to a specific transform that we want to use.
In this case, we're going to use a logarithmic transform.
So, we're going to use the string log.
If we only add this line to the plotting code,
we end up with a very odd looking plot.
The bar heights are still the same,
but they're wide on the left and thin on the right.
In order to get the plot more interpretable,
we need to modify the bin boundaries and generate more informative axis ticks.
First, let's discuss the bins.
The minimum weight is 0.1 and the maximum 999.9.
The Log of these values,
base 10 are negative one at a hair under three.
These give us the limits for our bins.
Our bin edges will be 10 to the of power values between negative one
and three so that they are evenly spaced after taking the logarithm.
The plot looks a lot better now,
showing a unimodal distribution,
but the tick marks could be made more interpretable.
We can start with writing out the given ticks,
but we might want to add more.
Here is where we need to do some hard coding since outside of the whole powers of 10,
there aren't nice evenly spaced intermediate values. We can still get close.
However, a three is about halfway between consecutive powers of 10 on a log scale.
Adding these values to a ticks list completes our exploratory plot.
It's much easier to read that the most common weights are between 10 and 100,
with a peak around 30 using these tick labels.