The bar charts you saw in the previous concept were all encoded with
the absolute frequency or number of data points on the length axis.
However, in some cases,
you might instead be interested in
the relative frequency or what proportion of the data falls in each category.
For example; Let's say that we have daily air quality data from three cities for a year.
If we are interested in estimating the proportion of
days that saw good air quality from our plot,
then trying to do this from the plot of counts require us to do some estimation work.
We would need to estimate the relative area of the Good bar to
all the bars together or have to do some mental calculations of some.
Changing the Count axis to relative proportions makes it
much easier to see how much each category contributes to the whole.
We can just read the height of the Good bar on the vertical axis and
find that almost 70 percent of days had good air quality.