We've arrived at the final stage of data wrangling; data cleaning.
By now you've already gathered your data and assessed it for any issues.
In this lesson we're going to be talking about remediating
these issues so that the data is then cleaned and good to go,
ready to pass the downstream stakeholders for tasks like making
visualizations or training machine learning models out of the data that you've gotten.
Data cleaning is often one of
the most time-consuming steps of the data wrangling process.
Why? Well, there are a number of reasons.
First, it's impossible to clean all the identified issues simultaneously.
You need to methodologically address each dimension of issues in
your dataset and then reassess
those issues to confirm that you've resolved them appropriately.
Once issues in one-dimension is resolved,
you can proceed to tackle the next one in a systematic manner.
Second, many of the issues may surface during the data cleaning phase,
and require you to go back and reassess the data to
ensure that you can address and resolve these problems appropriately.
This iterative process is time-consuming,
but it helps maintain data quality throughout the analysis.
The different types of data can complicate things further.
In this lesson, we'll be going over how to clean
data for tabular time series and text data.
So you can understand how to generalize and apply
considerations for cleaning data to different datatypes.