Now let's briefly go over each of the options to deal with these anions.
You can consider dropping the rows in your data set if there are
only a few rows with missing values and it won't impact your data analysis significantly.
As you made these 96 rows won't have a severe impact on your statistics like
the average and standard deviation and if you see
that they're not absolutely crucial to answer your problem,
you can safely drop them.
In this case, I'd like to drop the rows that have
NA values no matter what column they belong to.
We can quickly do this by using the drop NA function on our DataFrame df.
If we check the results using the.describe function,
we can see the number of rows have reduced.
We can also check using
the clean df isna sum function to confirm that there are zero Na cell.
Consider dropping an entire column when almost all of the values,
like 95 to 98% of the values are missing in a column.
At that point, the values that are present in the column are most likely not
significant for any downstream analysis so the column can safely be dropped.
For example, take a look at this new DataFrame,
which is also consisting of 10,000 rows.
The second column consists of almost entirely missing values.
Using the isna.sum method,
we find that almost 9,900 values of our data had NA values.
At this point, we may determine
the little remaining data that's actually there as part of the second column,
doesn't even add value to us.
We can use the pandas drop function specifying the name of
the column that we want to drop in setting the axis parameter to one,
where zero typically indicates rows and one indicates columns.
Now, with the second column assessment score to being dropped from the DataFrame,
we can see that there are no more NA values with
our DataFrame that's coming in from the first column for this particular dataset.
What if you don't want to drop the existing data just because there are
some missing values or the values are actually important to your question.
You can fill an empty cell in a column with the mean,
median, or mode of that column as an example.
This is also known as imputing.
We can impute NAN values by using pandas fill Na function.
For example, let's revisit the dataset with
four missing values in column one and 92 missing values in column two.
We can impute all missing values in our DataFrame with the mean of
each column using the df.mean and df.fillna functions.
Here what we're doing is providing df.mean to the filename method as input,
which will calculate the mean of each column.
Now if we run the sum of the NA after applying the fill Na function,
that does the imputing,
we can see that there's no more missing values in our dataset.
It's strongly recommended to only impute NAN values when needed, though.
It makes more sense to targetly impute NANs on columns for
efficiency reasons rather than on
the whole dataframe for columns and may not even need it.
To impute one specific column,
we use the same syntax,
but in this case we replace with df indexed on our column for example,
here we're doing it on assessment score too.
Here you can see only the missing values from
the assessment score two column is replaced or filled in with the mean value.
Whereas the missing values for assessment score one is still there.
It's also critical to perform a quick analysis
of your data after imputing missing values,
like get the average of the column for which you impute and then ask,
does the mean change significantly beyond what I'm comfortable with,
due to imputing the data values?
Here's another thing to keep in mind as it can get really confusing.
The only reason that we're able to apply
the describe function on a dataset that still has
NANs and Pandas is because in Pandas describe ignores missing values.
This means if you're trying to compute the mean of
a dataset before and after dropping rows for comparisons,
you're going to get the same result because it describe as
actually doing just that behind the scenes.
We are using describe here when imputing because
we're changing the data samples rather than just
dropping them so we would like to observe
a change in the summary statistics if there is one.
Here because we only have 96 rows with missing values out of 10,000 rows,
the change is not significant in
the statistics between the cleaned and the original DataFrame.
But when you have more missing values,
you're more likely to see more significant changes.
Now another option is to actually just convert your data into categories.
You can also bin values in your columns to create fewer categories.
For many cases, this may not lend you specific advantage when dealing with missing data,
but it's just up to the data wrangler judgment
on whether categories are the best option for your data.
For example, here we're using the pd.cut method to bin
variables in both our columns into four bins each.
Let's take a look at the bins for our second column using value counts.
Note that now in this case we now have four bins that were
created in a fifth bin that's actually still reserved for NAN values.
As we can see when we retrieved the rows that have NaN values
using DF indexed by df.is null.any on axis equals to one.
Now, in order to deal with this further,
you could then apply one of the earlier techniques we just covered,
such as removing the rows that have the NA values on top of this binned data.