Let's talk about cleaning health care dataset.
In this demo, I'm going to walk through techniques for
cleaning each major data quality issue,
and cleaning a few tidiness issues.
While we won't be able to cover how to clean
every data quality issue within this dataset as there are a lot,
you'll get an understanding of
the problem-solving methodology that data wranglers use to approach cleaning data.
For this demo, we're pulling our Phase II clinical trial dataset of the oral insulin.
In almost all cases,
it's strongly recommended to deal with missing data or completeness issues first,
to get those out of the way.
Then you can proceed to resolving messy data issues,
and return back to resolving data quality issues. Let's get started.
After importing our libraries,
and reading in our data frames and tables,
we're going to start with our completeness missing data issues first.
During the assessment freeze for this dataset,
we identify that there are missing records,
280 instead of 350 records in the treatments data frame.
This issue would trigger us to go back,
and check if we gathered the data correctly,
and retrieve the data again.
In this case, we can gather more data to help address missing values.
Let's say, we've now retrieved the missing data,
which we've stored in a separate file called treatments_cut.csv.
It contains 70 additional labels for all of the columns except hba1c_change,
which we'll return to later.
Now we need to get these entries into our original treatments data frame.
We can use the concat function for this,
for which a default parameters will insert the columns from
treatments cut.csv at the end of our original treatments data frame.
Here we are inserting or concatenating treatments_clean,
and treatments_cut, where treatments_clean is a copy of our treatments data frame.
Now take a look at the outputs of the head,
and the info function.
Here we can clearly see that the values for every column,
except this last one, are up to 350.
Let's now actually address this missing values from our hemoglobin change entries.
The hemoglobin level change is calculated, again,
by subtracting the values from the start column and the end column.
In this case, we don't actually have to impute the missing values,
because we do have the original entries for the start and end values,
so we can just calculate these accurately ourselves.
Let's go ahead and create a new column by subtracting the values in
the start column with the end column for our original hba1c_change column.
Now we can see the missing data issue is fixed because our values are up to 350,
and our data frame still looks intact when we're running a.sample method.
Let's now go on to Step 2; tidiness.
Now that we've dealt with the missing data first, in this section,
we're going to deal with three tidiness issues that were identified on this dataset,
plus one more we'll identify right on the spot.
Our first issue that we're going to deal with is,
contact column in the patient's table.
As you can see, our contact column here is containing both the phone number and email.
It should be split into two separate columns.
We also see a potential problem.
Sometimes phone numbers proceed email addresses,
and sometimes vice versa.
We have to be extremely careful with how we deal with this type of cases.
We'll make a copy of the patient's data frame,
and assign it to the patient's clean variable.
Next, what we'll do is,
use regex to extract the phone number and email
variables from the contact column using regular expressions,
and pandas str.extract method.
We'll also want to drop the contact column when done. Let's get started.
We're going to use the str.extract command to extract regex out of the contact column.
We're going to set the expanded parameter to true,
to expand this split strings into separate columns.
Now you're probably wondering what this monstrous regex expression is.
This regex was carefully crafted to detect phone numbers,
no matter whether they're placed before or after the email addresses.
Well, let's now try to detect the email addresses as well.
We can use this particular block of regex to
signify emails in the dataset all start and end with letters,
and again use the expand=True command.
This regex specifically is designed to catch email addresses,
regardless of whether they're placed before or after the phone numbers.
Using expand=True, we should have now created two columns,
phone number and email.
We want to also make sure that the contact column
is dropped after creating these two separate columns,
which we do here with.drop, and setting axis=1.
Let's look at the first few rows of this cleaned data frame.
Visually, we can already see the context column has gone.
We can pull up a quick sample using.sample,
and see in the phone number column that,
there aren't any email addresses.
Now we see clear separation between phone numbers and email addresses.
You can also use.sort_values to confirm that no emails are starting with an integer,
as that regex expression that we used didn't match for this.
Let's move on to tighten this issue number 2.
We have three variables in the auralin and novodra columns in the treatments table;
treatment, start_dose, and end_dose.
We're going to use on pivoting,
and other operations to help us.
Let's go ahead and get started with the on pivoting using melting.
Here, I define id_vars as the given_name, surnames, start, end,
and change columns, which are all columns we want to keep intact.
Then we define our variable name as treatment,
and our value name is dose.
Now our auralin and novodra column headers have been
transformed into the treatment column as you can see here,
indicating the type of the drug that a person took as values.
We also see our dose is a separate column,
and the rest of the columns are intact.
There is still work to do here though.
We don't need these hyphens,
and we need to split the dose into start and end doses and integers. Let's do this.
We first select the dose column from the treatments_clean data frame,
then we use.str.split to split the start and end doses.
We're going to go ahead and split it on the hyphen.
Here we're seeing that, that is the delimiter that's been provided
as the first argument that's going to be used to separate the values.
N=1 is indicating that,
only the first occurrence of the delimiter should be used for the split.
expand=True, again, is allowing us to
return a data frame with separate and values in different columns.
We want to have a data frame in the end with two columns.
We'll call the first column dose_start and the second one dose_end.
Now that it's split into two columns, again,
we want to drop the original dose column using the drop method using axis=1,
to indicate it's a column.
Looking at the data frame after these operations,
we have a treatment column that is neat,
that is showing us which drug the patient took,
and the start, and the end dose.
This is a much better data structure.
Now let's take a look at another issue.
The adverse reaction tables should be part of the treatments table,
because they have the same observational unit in individual treatment.
Let's merge the adverse reaction column to the treatment table,
joining on given name and surname.
In this case, the how parameter is set to left,
which means that all rows from
the left data frame treatments_clean are included in the resulting data frame,
and only the matching rows from the right data frame,
adverse_reactions_clean, are included.
Printing this data frame,
we now see the tables are merged,
with a new adverse reaction column appearing in the treatments clean table.
Let's put aside these two tables,
and focus primarily on the treatments clean and patients clean table,
as part of a final tidiness issue.
The given name and surname columns in
the patient's table is duplicated in the treatments table.
You can see that here, given name,
surname and patients,
and given name, surname and treatments.
But in the treatments_clean data frame,
these names are in lowercase as opposed to the patients_clean data frame.
Our objective is to get the name columns removed and treatments,
and replace them with a single patient ID column,
keeping the patient's name as part of the patient's table,
so the observational units are neatly set.
Note that right now the treatments table does not have a patient ID column.
First, let's get the patients_clean columns here,
from the patients_clean data frame including the ID,
the given name, and the surname.
We're going to assign this to a variable called id_names,
and then use str.lower to convert these to lowercase for the given name and the surname.
Next we're going to use pandas merge function,
and merge the treatments_clean data frame and the id_names variable
that we recently created on our given name and surname columns.
Next, we finally want to drop
the given name and surname columns from the treatments data frame,
because we, again, only want them in the patient's data frame.
Let's now confirm that the treatments table only has the patient ID,
and not the given name and surname,
which we can immediately see here.
With our patient's table,
we have both the patient ID and the given name and surname.
Now we have all our information about patients in one table, the patient's table,
and all the information about treatments in our treatments table,
with the patient ID helping us link between the two.