During the previous demo while cleaning up the missing data and data tininess issues,
we also addressed a few data quality issues.
Notably, we handle the completeness issue where
we were missing some records in the data set.
We also addressed the accuracy and completeness issue with the HPAC 1 change values.
We also address the NA values in the Auralin and Novodra columns
by creating the three new separate columns in the treatments data frame.
Now, let's explore some remaining issues from the data quality side.
Let's take a look at validity first.
The first validity issue is in the treatments table,
the dosage is formatted as two digits plus the character you format.
Ideally, as we've previously recognized,
we do want the values for both these columns to be
formatted as integers to make it easier to access this info.
We want to remove you from the texts in each of the columns.
We can do this using the string.strip method and then use
astype int to ensure that these values are of the integer type.
Let's test that this was successful by ensuring that
the datatypes for the dose start and dose and columns are integers.
We can see this using the dot D types method.
We can also actually use a Python assert statement
to check programmatically that the datatype is correct.
We'll go over more info on how to use Python asserts in a later section.
In the patient's table is zip code is a float, not a string.
This erroneous datatype causes
potential data errors because zip codes are not meant to be treated as numerical values.
When stored as a float zip codes with leading zeros,
which are common in the Northeastern United States will lose those zero,
for example on the row 07095.0,
the current zip code should be 07095.
Let's convert the zip codes column datatype from a float to a string using astype str.
We'll then remove the dots zero using string slicing.
Then we're going to use the third method in order to add
leading zeros to any zip codes with less than five digits.
However, this will also convert missing values 000n.
We'll want to replace this with np.nan.
Now we only have zip codes that are five digits in our data frame.
Let's look at another issue in our patient's table,
we have a few erroneous datatypes,
assigned sex date,
and birth date columns.
We can ensure that
the assigned sex and state variables are represented as categorical variables using
the astype method will also convert the birth date variable to date time object.
We'll discuss more about daytime type later.
As we can see here, we use the astype method
for converting these brambles to categories to_today
time to convert our birthday column to_datetime type
that we can confirm using the deed types method.
Let's now turn to accuracy issues with the patient's table.
One of the issues that we encountered previously is that a patient
Tim Neudorf height is 27 inches instead of 72 inches.
Let's do a quick replace of height for rows in the patient's table that have a height of
27 with 72 using dot replace on archived column.
Let's do a check in our dataset visually to make sure we don't have
any heights below 30 inches to also help us catch any similar issues.
We see that there are no issues after doing the indexing.
No rows essentially that are showing a height of less than 30 inches, which is great.
We can also pull up team's record by indexing using his surname and see that it worked.
Our height is now corrected.
Here's another simple issue where we have
an issue of a name Dsvid, which should be David.
Similarly, we can use the replace method and check
the road to make sure that it went correct.
Let's now briefly go over a consistency issue.
Here we identified an issue where one of the patients reported weight
was actually reported in kilograms is 48.8,
but it should be reported in pounds.
Let's first describe a indexing mask.
During the assessment step we identified the patient's name is Zaitseva,
will use the mask to get the weight of the patient.
Next, we'll use a dot loc to access this row.
In the weight column,
we're going to go ahead and replace the value with the value times
the conversion factor to convert the value to pounds from kilograms.
Now using sort values, we check 48.8.
Shouldn't be the lowest value anymore.
It's not appearing, which is fantastic.
Knowing that none of our patients are below 100 pounds.
We can also use a Python assert statement to check
the minimum value in the dataset for the weight column is greater than 100.
Let's take a look at our final two issues.
Here we'll look at uniqueness and validity issues on the patient's data frame.
In the assessment stage for our patients' table,
we identified six duplicates for the last name Doe and 123 Main Street as the address.
Let's assume a scenario where we communicated with our data provider and they
confirm that John Doe is accurate records are simply non-recoverable,
so we have to delete them all from the patient's table.
Here we're specifying that the rows in which surname is
Doe and the given name is John shouldn't be deleted.
Now, after doing the indexing here accordingly,
and then going ahead and deleting them using
the not equal sign or not including them Essentially.
When we use the value counts function,
we can confirm that John Doe,
his name isn't coming up.
We can also check that his addresses and popping up
anymore by running value counts on the address variable.
Now let's take a look at the final issue.
We have a few records and our patient's table that are nicknames.
These are Jake Jacobson,
Pakistan, and Sandy Taylor rows from the patient's table.
This is an issue because for example Jake and Jakob are
the same person and Pat and Patrick is
the same person because they share the same address.
These nicknames are not in the treatments table and
so we need to be careful when removing the duplicate rows.
Removing the wrong name would create
a consistency issue between the patients and treatments tables.
There's a couple of things that we need to note here.
These records with patients' nicknames are all the second occurrence,
as we can see here, for example,
see here with Jacobson's records where
Jake Jacobson happens after Jake Jacobson's record.
These are also the only occurrences of non null duplicate addresses as well.
Let's retrieve the rows with nicknames by
finding all the rows within duplicated and non null addresses.
We first use the duplicated methods on
the address column to find all rows with a duplicated address.
Then we use the not null method defined rows with nonmetal addresses.
We're using the ampersand operator here to connect
the two methods and ensure that the results meet both conditions,
duplicate address, and a non null address.
We can successfully locate this rows after running this block of code.
Now we want to remove these rows so we can go
ahead and add the Tilda operator that represents the inverse,
meaning we don't want to have these rows with the not null duplicate addresses,
which are the rows that we're seeing above.
Then we assign the results to our patients cleaned data frame.
Now we have excluded all of the rows that have
these types of duplicate values that we don't want.
Using visual assessment and programmatic indexing,
we can see there's no more presence of names in the given name column for Jacobson.
No more Jake here or Pat for Brixton and similarly for the surname Taylor,
we also see no more nicknames.