In this demo, we'll introduce a few scikit-learn
preprocessing tools for key parts of the data cleaning process;
scaling, encoding, and imputing missing values.
Let's start our demo by importing the sklearn package.
I'm also going to import a couple of methods from sklearn and NumPy.
I'm also going to import the set config function
from sklearn setting transform output equals
Pandas so that outputs from the sklearn package of transform and fit transform functions,
which we'll look at in a moment,
will be in the Pandas DataFrame format.
We'll see what this looks like in just a moment.
Let's now turn to one of the fundamental steps to
do for cleaning your data, standardizing it.
In many real-world cases,
the scale or range that applies for one variable in our dataset doesn't apply to others.
For example, one column in your data can contain
values around blood pressure measurements like ranging from
120-150 systolic and another column contains values
around patients income ranging 20,000-100,000.
The large differences in the scale of values for
these variables can make many tasks challenging,
especially machine learning tasks.
We should ensure our data follows
a standard scale and can be easily used to train ML models.
We call this scaling data.
A a popular form of being able to scale data for a given data sample
is removing the mean and scaling the distribution to unit variance.
Take a look at a short snippet here that's
borrowed from one of sklearn's create tutorials.
Here we create an array using NumPy with some random numbers in it.
Now we can apply sklearn's standard scaler to
scale the data and we fit it on our tiny dataset.
Fitting computes the mean and standard deviation to be used for later scaling.
Let's go ahead and run this.
Now we can go ahead and print the mean and
the standard deviation that were generated
for the data using the corresponding attributes.
Finally, we can apply the transform function,
which is actually performing the scaling
using the values prepared during the bidding stage.
There's also a way to fit and transform in one command called fit_transform.
Now, after doing the transform function,
we see that the scale data has zero mean and unit variance.
There are additional types of scalers that sklearn is offering,
like the minmax scaler to scale variables to
lie between a given minimum and maximum value,
often between zero and one.
There's also methods to scale values that have outliers.
Encoding is a popular technique for many reasons,
including transforming categorical data into numerical data.
One of these techniques is ordinal encoding,
which encodes data and categorical features as an integer array.
Let's consider this really tiny dataset with three words;
data, wrangling, rocks.
We can define an ordinal encoder and apply a fit transform to this tiny dataset.
We can see it assigned the value of zero to the word data,
two to the word wrangling,
and one to the word rocks.
Now there's another option for encoding these types of
variables that's popular and that's known as one-hot encoding.
This actually encodes categorical features as a one-hot numeric array.
On our same simple dataset, data, wrangling, rocks,
note how three columns now created for each of the three words.
The word data is represented as 100,
the word wrangling is represented as 010,
and the word rocks is represented as 001.
This makes it easier for computers to understand categorical data and text data.
Finally, after scaling and encoding,
let's look at how to impute missing values in scikit-learn.
This code block is written in Python and uses the scikit-learn library.
We fetched the Titanic dataset from
the open ML repository using the function fetch_openml,
which downloads datasets from our open ML repo.
In this case, our code snippet is actually downloading the Titanic dataset with
Version 1 as a Pandas DataFrame and storing it in variables x and y.
We're then going to use the function train_test_split,
which is used to split data into training and test sets that are
typically used to train and test machine learning models respectively.
The stratify parameter ensures that the proportion of classes
in the original data is preserved in both training and test sets.
Let's briefly understand what this data is taking a peek at the first few rows.
The Titanic dataset is a popular dataset used in machine learning and data science.
The x dataframe here is containing info about passengers on the Titanic,
like their name, age, and gender.
The data series in y is containing info on whether or not these individuals survived.
Zero means they didn't survive and one means they did survive.
Notice how the variables are of different datatypes somewhere numbers,
continuous variables other represent categories like categorical variables.
Now let's look at a number of missing values in each column of the x_test DataFrame.
We can skip over to the isnull function which returns a Boolean DataFrame
with true values for missing values and false values for non missing values.
The sum value is again going ahead and summing up the true values for
each column to give us the total number of missing values in each column.
Our second line of code only selects columns that have more than zero missing values and
then sorts them in the descending order of
the number of missing values so that we can view them easily.
If we print the result of that,
we can see many missing values in different columns of the dataset like body,
cabin, boat, age, embarked, etc.
Let's focus on the age and body columns and look at how to impute
these values for numerical variables using an sklearn solution, simple imputer.
Here we create an instance of the simple imputer class.
We define the missing value placeholders as np.nans and set the strategy to mean,
which means we want to replace the missing values with the mean value of the column.
Then we apply it to the age and body columns of
the x_test DataFrame using the fit transform method,
where we're fitting and transforming all in one and store the result in simple imputed.
Next what I'm going to do to make it easier for us to look at this,
I'm going to replace the age and body columns in
the original x_test DataFrame with the imputed values.
This way we can actually just repeat our earlier block of code
on getting the number of missing values on the x_test DataFrame,
and you can see once we repeat the exact same code,
that the age and body columns are no longer appearing here because there's no
longer any na values that we can see that were generated for these columns.
Let's actually go ahead and put this all together in
an efficient way through something called an sklearn pipeline.
Again, pulling from a short sklearn tutorial.
Pipelines are really handy way of assembling a bunch of
sklearn operations altogether and determine flow.
Here this time we're reusing
our Titanic dataset but the subset that we put aside for the training.
We going to go ahead and define a sklearn pipeline
where we use the simple imputer to impute the missing values,
standard scaler to scale our continuous variables,
and the one-hot encoder for encoding our categorical variables.
Finally, we can also add in a machine-learning model logistic regression to our pipeline.
We can then fit our sklearn pipeline onto the training dataset, as we've done here.
After that, you can do many things.
You can get the performance of your model on the dataset.
You can also remove the logistic regression model and fit
the scaling or encoding and imputing pipeline on our test dataset as well.
This means whatever operations that we performed to get the training dataset ready,
we're now also able to perform on
the test dataset after removing the logistic regression model.