Test data is all around us,
for example in the form of email,
social media posts, and more.
Let's take a look at how we clean data,
and this type of process is actually even typically used by gigabyte layers to,
for example, transmission lines. Let's dive in.
Here's a simplified overview of the process to clean text data.
The first step is called normalization,
which allows us to bring messy raw text data to a needed standard.
As you'll see as part of this step,
we may convert sentences into lowercase.
As part of the additional cleaning,
we may remove unnecessary words like The and a.
The next step is tokenization,
where you divide your text into individual tokens from your dataset.
The final step is vectorization,
where you convert these tokens into a machine readable format so that they can then,
for example be used to train machine learning models.
Let's now look at each step in detail.
To understand normalization, take a look at the very simple dataset on the screen.
In this dataset, we have two columns.
The post column indicating a short social media posts about technology,
and the sentiment column showing us whether the text is a positive,
neutral, or negative sentiment.
The first step towards getting this data to
a machine-readable format is to get it into a standard format,
for example, all characters in lowercase.
This is a popular form of normalization called case normalization.
In Pandas, we can accomplish this using series.string.capitalize,
where series here is our post column in our tiny DataFrame.
Now notice, I've been doing this, how?
All of the texts and the post column is now in lowercase.
Another thing that we can do is remove punctuation,
because punctuation is related more to the tone and not to the actual words.
We want to focus on the ladder during our text analysis.
So we can actually remove punctuation using a regular expression or rejects again,
which is a character sequence allowing us to match items in text.
This string here is for matching different types of
punctuation like periods and exclamation marks.
We're going to use the string.replace method to take in the regular expression and then
replace any punctuation that's being caught by this with an empty string,
as you can see here, for our post column.
Let's go ahead and do that right now.
Perfect. Now, take a look at the output of the post column,
which is all lowercase n does not have any more punctuation like commas.
I'd like to take a moment to show you one other cool thing we can do with
the pandas string method called str.contains.
Let's say we want to create another column based on the texts from our post column.
Here with this command,
we can first access our texts a DataFrame through.loc,
and check if a string in the post column contains data science.
If it does, we can create a new column called
topic and assign the value of that row as data science.
Let's go ahead and run this.
Take a look at the updated DataFrame that has new column topic.
Now, anytime a social media posts in the post column is mentioning the word data science,
this will get populated in the topic column.
We can use similar code to automatically extract character sequences in other texts.
Now, there's a number of other things outside of this
that we would need to do to fully clean the text,
including removing stop words that aren't relevant to us like a,
d, and is which don't really hold any value.
Reducing words, they're rule base,
like turning all mentions of gone to go,
which is called stemming.
Let's skip ahead to tokenization.
Here, we're going to import the nltk library,
a popular library for performing,
cleaning, and manipulation of texts in Python.
We're going to start by indexing or post column with a txt_ data dataframe,
and then using the apply function to apply nltk is
word tokenize method to divide strings into lesser substrings,
allowing us to extract the vocabulary from our dataset.
We then create a new column in our DataFrame called token in our text_ data,
dataframe. Here we go.
Now, we can see that the column now has our neatly tokenized text as a list of strings.
Let's finally talk about vectorizing
the final step to take our tokens and make them machine readable.
For this part, we'll use scikit-learn,
a popular data analysis in science library that's containing a lot of
great preprocessing tools for different types of data as we've already seen.
In particular, scikit-learn or SK learn provides tools from vectorizing text documents,
and this actually takes care of tokenizing under the hood.
Let's take a look at this.
We're going to vectorize the texts in
our post column using SK learns count vectorizer functionality,
which converts a collection of text documents to a matrix of token counts.
We'll first start by creating an instance of count vectorizer.
Then we will call the fit transform function on it,
which does two things.
It first builds the vocabulary based on the input text data, which is the fit.
Then it converts the input text data into
a numerical representation based on the learn vocabulary which is the transform.
Note that since this automatically does tokenization and then vectorization,
we can directly use it on the post column which contains our normalized strings.
Now, let's take a look at the output of the encoded vector,
also known as a sparse matrix using the two-array function.
Here's a prettier formatted version of this by taking this vector into
a DataFrame and using vectorizer.get feature names to actually get the feature names.
You can now see that the posts are encoded with the vocabulary of the texts,
and now we have to count and integers for
the number of times each word appeared in the document.
These words matrix array can be directly pass to a machine-learning model,
for example, to train it to predict the sentiments in relation to the sentiment column.
The vocabulary attribute also shows us the indices of
each word in our vocabulary for our DataFrame across columns.
Essentially, each word is assigned a unique integer index in the output vector.