Time series is another popular data format for storing data over time.
It's a sequence of data points collected at regular time intervals,
often used to analyze trends,
patterns, and forecasting overtime.
Let's take a look at the steps data wrangler is used to
deal with dates and pandas and clean time-series data.
We'll start with importing our Pandas and NumPy packages.
For this demo, we'll be using a hypothetical stock dataset that's modeled
after the popular Apple stock dataset that contains two columns.
The first column is the date for everyday between Jan 1,
2018 to March 1, 2021.
The date is known in the ear of month and date format.
The second column is volume in millions,
denoting the number of shares traded during the trading day.
Let's start with some simple inspection of this data.
As we can see with the results of the describe method,
the volume columns values typically range from 10 to about 600 million.
Using the info method,
we can see that the date column has a date
type object because the dates were stored as strings.
The datatype of the volume column is into 64 as all the values are numerical.
Let's also plot our time series data.
We can do this by running df dot plot on our DataFrame,
plotting the data as the x-axis and the volume is the y-axis.
To visualize our time series data,
we can see that the data has a lot of dips and peaks.
Now let's get started with the wrangling process.
Our first immediate step should be to convert
the date column from an object to a pandas date-time.
We can easily manipulate the date.
We can do this using the two DateTime method on our date column.
Looking at the outputs of dot info again,
the datatype of date is now a day times 64 ns.
Ns means the nanosecond based time format
specifying the precision of the datetime object.
Now, with this datetime object,
we can actually do a lot of interesting operations now on the time.
Let's go two examples.
First, if I want to know how much time is captured by my dataset,
I can use the max and min functions on
my date column to see that the data captures 1,155 days.
If I want to extract information from the date columns such as the year, for example,
for eventually merging this data with another data table that also has a year column,
I can actually use this dt oxidizer by
denoting dt dot year to get the year of the datetime object.
Here I'm assigning it to a new column in our tiny DataFrame.
Now know how much easier this is than having to use
string manipulations to extract the year from the date.
Here I've created a separate year column pretty simply.
Now next comes the critical step with manipulating time series data.
Setting the index as our date column,
which we can typically do right after converting the column to a datetime object.
This turns the date column into a date-time index,
as we can see with the outputs of the dot info method and the dot index method.
Here we use set index and our date column,
turning it into an index.
We can check the type of the index using dot index.
Here we confirm it's a date-time index.
If we don't see any index or date variable for this DataFrame,
we're going to run into a few limitations.
For example, we can do one thing which is called resampling.
A very powerful and popular method that's similar to
a group by but for time series. Let's look into that.
Resampling can do two main things,
provide a time-based grouping with a target frequency and aggregate based on that.
Let's say I want to get the yearly mean volume in my dataset.
We're going to do this by resampling by first using DFS on re-sample Y,
where Y is the year.
This is the rule parameters specifying our target for the conversion.
Then I'll use dot mean on the volume to get the yearly average volume in my dataset.
Take a look at the results.
I can now see the mean volume from my dataset for each year.
We can actually plot these results by simply attaching dotplot to the end of this block,
and now we have a line plot of the results and an yearly rather than daily granularity.
Here's another handy method.
Let's say I'd like to get what day of the week the date falls on.
I can use day of week on my index to get whether the day is a Monday,
a Tuesday, and so on until Sunday,
where Monday is zero, Tuesday one,
Sunday is six, then I can do things like get all the rows for the days are
a Monday as I can do here with isin function and get the mean volume across all Mondays.
Now, what about manipulating our new date-time index further?
We can also convert our date variable to a specified format.
Here I make a copy of my DataFrame so I don't
influence the original date-time index, that's neat.
I then use the string F time on my DataFrames index specifying the following format.
Percent B means full month name,
percent d means day of the month,
then followed by a comment.
Finally, percent Y means year.
For example, we are turning our date format from the year, month,
day to the January 1, 2018 format.
As we can see here, the index is successfully modified.
Here's another cool thing.
If we don't set the index as our date variable for this DataFrame,
we would have been forced to use the.dt accessor.
For example, in order to convert our date variable to a specific format,
we would have had to use DFT date indexing on the date column dt dot strip time.
Let's talk about one last thing with cleaning time series data, missing data.
Take a look at this new DataFrame I loaded.
Again, one of the first types of cleaning time series data is
converting your day column to datetime objects.
We can see that there's a number of NA values by using is na method,
and we can actually sum up the number of values as well.
If you want, you can investigate this missing data further
using few of the methods we discussed above and others,
for example using the day of the week method to figure
out which days have missing data in your dataset.
Let's actually jump to filling these missing values.
We can use the fill NA function,
as we're familiar with,
and specify how we'd like to fill the values.
For example, we could use the mean or the median.
Here, I use the ffill perimeter,
which replaces each missing value with the previous valid value in the same column.
After running this, if we check the number of Na's again,
notice how the number of Na's have disappeared after our filename.
We would typically extend this analysis by then doing
a detailed programmatic assessment to confirm that the Na values are gone.