In this demo, we'll first take a look at how we can assess the impact of data cleaning.
We've already covered ways to do this using
visual inspection with methods like.head and.tail.
But what about visualizations?
While we briefly covered boxplots as a way to visualize outliers,
let's look at heatmaps and histograms as
two other visualizations that data sprinklers typically use.
Here I've loaded my PUMS dataset.
I'm trying to test if I handle the missing data correctly.
First, we have a code block where we take care of a couple of cleaning operations,
starting with making copy of the DataFrame,
dealing with a tidiness issue by defining the zeroth row as our header,
keeping our WRK, SEX,
and SCOP variables and dealing with a data quality issue by
replacing zero values in the word column with np.nan to deal with the completeness issue.
Now that all of the cleaning code is complete,
let's skip over to say,
how do we visualize the missing values in our semi cleaned data?
Take a look at this heatmap visualization that I generated using the Seaborne library,
where we visualize the patterns of missing data
for some variables from the PUMS dataset,
including the occupational code variable,
the SOCP variable,
the gender, and whether or not an individual
worked in the last week indicated by the WRK variable.
Here, in order to create the heatmap,
I'm using the.isna method and transposing
this and then providing it as input to the Seaborne heatmap function,
while also specifying the label for the missing data legend at the side.
The white vertical bars in this heatmap are
representing missing values for a particular variable.
In this case we can actually see a number of missing values for the WRK column.
I'm going to go ahead now and use the Drop NA function
on this PUMS dataset to get rid of those NA values.
Now if we re-run the heatmap,
there's no white lines and the color indicates there isn't any missing data.
Another way to visualize data is plotting a histogram of the distribution of data values.
Let's go ahead and load another dataset,
the OEWS wage data set and similarly do some cleaning.
I'm making a copy of the DataFrame down here,
replacing alphanumeric characters with NAs,
filtering the DataFrame to only contain specific data variables
and filtering to only contain values that are corresponding to California.
Finally, I also drop NA values.
Here now what I'm going to do is plot the age mean or
hourly mean numeric variable in my dataset
indicating the hourly mean wage from my cleaned wage DataFrame.
I'm using the simple plot.hist function for this,
defining the number of bins for my histogram as 12 and
the transparency value for the plot to be 0.5 for aesthetic reasons.
The plot.hist function is from the Matplotlib library.
Now, with this visualization,
I can quickly grasp the range of values for this variable.
For example, ranging from about $10-160 at quick glance.
This seems to be the typical range of the data.
I can also identify if there are any outliers or data
points that seem anomalous in relation to the larger chunk of data.
Like some of these data points here at the far right of the plot.
This can help me with identifying potential validity issues as well and accuracy issues.
How can we test data programmatically including whether
we successfully dropped the NAs for both datasets?
We can actually use Python assert statements to
check if certain conditions we know should hold true for our datasets.
Those are indeed true.
For example, we can use it to check whether our column datatypes are accurate.
In this case, let's say we've determined that we want
all the variables to be at the object's data type in the PUMS dataset.
We can actually go ahead and do that and using the assert statement by accessing
the datatype using the dtype method for each of
the columns and asserting that they're all objects.
Similarly for the OEWS dataset,
we want to check if the datatype of each mean is a float.
Because it's a numerical variable we can do the same thing here.
We can also check if the number of NA values and
our code is set to zero for both datasets.
Here we use isnull.sum.sum in order to calculate the number
of NA values and check that it's zero for both datasets.
We can see that since these assert statements have successfully run and no issues there,
everything is good and there really are
no NA values in this dataset when we use this programmatic check.
What happens if the cleaning code didn't work and the data didn't meet
the condition we specified in the assert statements though?
For example, let's say that I determined that
the hourly mean wage values in the data should be smaller than or equal to 150.
Because any value greater than 150,
as an example, is an outlier to me.
I use the assert statement to test this condition.
You can see now that the assert statement is throwing us an error because we
never removed these outliers that we identified earlier through the histogram.
Assert statements are indeed useful when you need to modify earlier cleaning code to
address new data problems and want to
ensure that previously solved issues remain resolved.
For example, if you want to verify that these NA values
for the two datasets remain at zero as you're addressing other data issues,
you can use assert statements.
These single line statements allow you to confirm that your cleaning code is working as
expected by re-running them whenever you make changes to your implementation.