You're at the final stage of the data wrangling process.
You've gathered your data,
assessed it, cleaned it,
and now it's time to store your good work so
that you can hand it over to other stakeholders.
Let's look into how to do this.
There are some simple ways of updating a local datastore with clean data for example,
saving data using the Pandas.csv function.
Here we see how we can directly
specify the path and the filename as an input to the.csv function.
It's also sometimes typical to specify index equals false to
not store the index column so that when you load your.csv again,
you don't get an unnecessary duplicated index column.
There's also a number of other arguments that you can specify,
such as the encoding in order to ensure your data is stored in the right format.
You can also write data to a database.
For example, with sql light through Pandas to sql function with sql alchemy.
Here, foe example we can specify the table name,
our sql alchemy engine connection,
and additional arguments such as if_exists='append',
where here we insert new values to
an existing table if the table we're trying to create already exists.
Another argument is index label to specify the column or columns to use as the index,
which in this case we want to use ID.
It's critical to also maintain different instances where versions of the data.
At the very minimum,
you should have two versions of your data.
One version should be your raw data stored directly after the gathering stage,
and one should be your clean data.
When storing your cleaned data,
you may create a structure around this data as well.
You may have a location for storing your documentation of
the design decisions and strategies that you
take along the way to assess and clean your data,
as well as your raw data
your source code including your Jupyter Notebooks and the cleaned data files.
This all will make it easier when you decide to create
additional visualizations or analyses on top of your clean data and publish it.
It will also help downstream stakeholders to
understand the process and reproduce your work.