We've reached the end of our lesson.
In the final lesson, you gained an understanding of what data cleaning is.
You're now able to describe the data cleaning
phase and identify each stage of the process.
Then we looked at how to handle typical data cleaning tasks.
We did a deep dive on how to remediate
popular data quality and structural issues and techniques that you can apply.
As part of this, we also discussed how to deal with outliers,
duplicated data, and missing data.
Following that, we looked at how to clean
dirty and messy data with Python for tabular data,
bad time-series, and text data.
Finally, we looked at how to test our cleaning operations and how to store
our cleaned data using font files so it's
ready to be handed over and used for downstream tasks.
Congratulations on finishing this course.
Throughout this course, you've mastered skills that are
in demand around critical problem-solving and
decision-making for dealing with data in a world where
the size and complexity of data is growing at an amazing speed every day.
I'm sure you recognize by now that data wrangling is quite the journey.
There's a lot of steps from just recognizing
the value in data to then being able to gather it,
assess it, clean it,
and store it so that you're able to unlock
the value and the insights that you want to get out of that data.
That way, data is then ready to change the world
after it's cleaned and finished with the data wrangling process,
or at least able to answer some interesting questions for you and your team.
Now, it's your time to put your skills to the test,
solving an interesting problem with your choice and wrangling
real-world data as part of the final project for this course. Good luck.