In the first section, we'll begin with understanding what is data cleaning,
covering how to describe the cleaning phase,
and identifying each stage of the process from an expert's perspective.
We'll also go over why programmatic cleaning is
much more strongly preferred compared to manual cleaning.
Next, we'll dive into tasks like how to solve
common data structure issues programmatically and dealing with outliers and missing data.
Following that, we'll look at how to clean
dirty and messy data with Python for different types of data,
including tabular data, time-series data, and text data.
Finally, we'll look at how to test our cleaning operations.
We'll cover testing implementations visually,
which in a sense requires revisiting the assessment stage to do so.
We'll then take a look at how to do this programmatically.
Finally, to wrap up the entire process,
how to store our clean data using flat files so
it's ready to be handed over and used for downstream tasks.