Experts typically approach data cleaning by following a three-step process.
Before kick-starting this process,
it's critical to make a copy of your original dataset.
All of the cleaning operations are typically conducted on the copy,
so you can still view the original dirty and/or messy dataset later.
If you're working with DataFrames and Pandas,
you can do this by using the copy method
on your dataframe and assigning it to a variable,
for example, in this case, df_clean.
The next step is the definition where we define a data cleaning plan.
We do this by converting our assessments into
cleaning tasks by writing little how-to guides.
This plan also serves as documentation so that your work can be reproduced.
For example, a cleaning task can be removing unnecessary hyphens and variables.
Then we'll actually implement these actions into code and run them.
Finally, you'll test your dataset visually and
programmatically to make sure you're cleaning code worked.
For example, you may inspect the first few rows of the DataFrame
using the dot head method to confirm the hyphens are removed.
In this step, we often revisit assessment to
compare the results before and after cleaning.
Programmatic cleaning is referring to using code or automated scripts in
order to clean your data and it's actually preferred over manual cleaning,
so let's look at a couple of differences between these two methods.
When you manually clean data,
you might typically be retyping data or copying and
pasting columns and rows to correct the issues by hand.
This type of cleaning is inefficient and as datasets grow larger and more complex,
it becomes increasingly challenging to maintain data quality manually.
It's also error-prone.
You might accidentally miss some incorrect values or
introduce new errors while typing or copying data.
On the other hand, programmatic data cleaning uses code to fix data quality issues.
It allows work faster and more efficient handling of
large datasets as the cleaning process can be automated and performed on a massive scale.
It also involves using code or scripts to clean the data,
which ensures a consistent approach and reduces
the risk of human error which can occur during manual cleaning.
This consistency leads to more reliable and accurate results in the analysis.
Programmatic cleaning also enables you to create reusable scripts or
functions that can be applied to similar datasets or future data cleaning tasks.
This makes the process more transparent and allows other researchers or
team members to reproduce the cleaning steps and validate the results.
Data wrangling is taking a tremendous amount of time for data professionals,
so programmatic data cleaning is strongly preferred compared to the manual process.