There are some common issues that make data messy or untidy.
Let's recap these. One,
column headers being values rather than variable names.
Two, multiple variables being stored in one column.
Three, variables being stored in both rows and columns.
Four, multiple types of observational units being stored in the same table,
and five, a single observational unit being stored in multiple tables.
To solve these issues,
we need to know some data structuring and techniques.
Column headers are values not variable names is a common data structure issue.
Let's briefly visit it.
In the dataset on the top we can see
how different ranges of test scores are part of the header.
These should ideally be placed in a single column as values.
What do we do? We can use a function called unpivoting,
also known as melting,
to transform data across columns into a single column.
See the bottom table after unpivoting,
we can now see that the different ranges are now stored in
one column and the frequency values are also in a single column.
Unpivoting is really useful when you need to convert a wide dataset with
many columns into a long format with fewer columns and more rows.
This transformation is helpful for certain types of
data analysis that required data in long format.
What if we'd like to do the opposite?
Pivoting is the opposite of unpivoting and is
a very popular method for being able to get a clearer understanding of data.
Let's take a look at how and why.
Here we have an example dataset of hypothetical products and revenue.
Our simple dataset has four columns.
Product classification, whether the product is an early prototype pilot work product,
the products A, B, and C. The year when the product is built and the revenue in dollars.
Notice how it's challenging to get an idea of the revenue for
the three products over the years since the rows are intermixed.
We can use a function called pivoting to convert
a long dataset into a wide dataset and create useful groupings.
For example here we can now clearly see that products A and C
were an early prototype stage in 2021 and made it $0 in revenue.
The early prototype version of these two products were not continued into 2022 and 2023.
Now, Products A and B were both pilots.
Product B made $3,885 in revenue in 2021,
whereas Product A made $2,193 in revenue in
2022 because it was still an early prototype stage in 2021, and so on.
When you use unpivoting versus pivoting,
use unpivoting to turn a dataset into a standard format for performing analyses.
Use pivoting to turn data tables into easier to understand representations of the data,
for example for presentations.
Transposing is another popular operation that's used for data structuring.
Take a look at the example on the screen where we
have student IDs that are part of the header.
The first row is the student's names.
In the second row is the student's test score.
We see the common issue of column headers being
values not variable names in this DataFrame,
it can be challenging to access
a specific students test score when the DataFrame is in this format.
It's overall a somewhat challenging format for manipulating and navigating the data.
We can transpose this into the DataFrame on the bottom,
which has neat columns for each variable,
for example the ID,
the students, and the test score.
We can also transpose the DataFrame on the bottom,
back into the DataFrame on the top,
if we would like to follow that format instead.
Data merging is another technique for data structuring.
Consider the two separate data tables on the screen that were stored separately,
do separate data collection and poor planning.
The DataTable on the left contains the ID of the movie,
and movie title, and the viewers as part of her viewers dataset.
Similarly, the table on the right contains the ID of the movie,
a review, and an associated rating.
Here we're seeing the common issue of
a single observational unit being stored in multiple tables.
Since the two tables have the same observational unit of an individual movie,
they should ideally be one table with the same observational unit.
We can merge these two tables side-by-side using
the ID column as our key to get one table with all of the required information.
This is a straightforward example of merge,
although there can be various types of merges.
Data appending, also known as concatenating,
is a similar technique today merging.
While merging is joining two tables together
side-by-side by a unique key to align the data.
Appending means taking two tables with
the same variables and adding the data points from one table to another table.
For example take a look at the table on top.
If I wanted to append the second table to it as part of a simple append operation,
I could just add the rows from the second table to the end of the top table.
Group-bys and aggregations are handy Pandas functions to get a summary table of the data.
Group-by allows you to group categorical data together,
and aggregating the values associated with them can be
done using aggregate functions like a sell more amine.
Let's take a look at an example of this.
On the left, I have a simple dataset with a date column listing months, and score column.
If I were to perform a Group-by on this DataFrame to get the sum
of the score and the mean of the score for each month.
The result of the group-by would look like the output on the right.