Let's take a look at now how to implement these data structure and techniques in pandas.
We'll start with importing pandas and reading an Excel file that I created for this demo.
This Excel file has multiple sheets that contain
the multiple datasets that we'll be needing for this demo.
I used pandas, read Excel function and specify
the argument sheet name equals none to reading all of these sheets all at once.
I'm then going to assign the result to example data.
Let's go ahead and start with a demo of unpivoting or melting.
I'm going to access the unpivot example sheet in
the example data variable using the sheets name unpivot example.
Then I'm going to make a copy of the DataFrame which we just reviewed as having
column headers as values rather than variable names as the issue for this dataset.
Remember again that the numerical values in the header,
like less than 50 or 50-70 are binned test scores and
the values in the DataFrame are the number of tests that students have taken.
We have the names of the students in the name column.
Here's how we can unpivot this using pandas.
We'll use the melt function with three arguments.
Id_vars is the column to use as the identifier variable.
All columns other than this column are unpivoted to the row axis.
In this example, the name column is the identifier and we want to unpivot the variable,
which is the binned score, and the value,
which is how many tests taken by a student falls within each score range.
Getting to that var_name is how you want to call the new column with
the variables from the original table before the unpivoting.
In this case, we want to call our new variable binned score.
Value_name is how you want to call the new column
with the values from the original table before unpivoting.
In this case, we want to call these types of values frequency.
Let's go ahead and run this piece of code.
The result here is our unpivoted DataFrame with three columns,
one of them being the name of the students,
the second being the binned score,
and the third being the frequency.
Let's move to pivoting.
I'm loading my dataset from the pivot example sheet from the same Excel.
Again, recall with this example we have a DataFrame with details on products,
revenue, and the years that we want to have
a better visualization of to understand the groupings.
What do we do here? Well,
what we can do is go ahead and use pandas dot pivot method.
We want to produce groupings for two variables here,
the product classification and the product.
These two variables are what we're specifying as part of our index argument.
Next, we want to see the revenue values per year.
We want the years to be our columns and the values
inside the DataFrame to actually be the actual revenue values.
Take a look at the output here that we get after running this block of
code that we're able to easily interpret through the groupings.
Next, let's go ahead and move on to transposing.
Here, again, I'm loading my dataset from the right Excel spreadsheet.
As we just covered previously,
the student IDs with this dataset are in the header and
subsequent rows have info on students and their test scores.
Let's go ahead and simply transpose the DataFrame using the.T method.
Notice a few things have happened after we're able to do this.
The ID header has actually now become the DataFrame's index.
We also see that students and test score are unfortunately part of the values,
but these should actually be our headers.
How can we keep the ID as our index but reset our header?
We can actually use the.set index on our original DataFrame
with the ID column and then transpose the DataFrame.
Now, the ID, students,
and test score variables are in our header and the ID variable is still our index.
Next, let's go over merging.
With this use case, I first load in
two data tables from two Excel sheets for my example,
data variable around movie reviews.
Again, recall that both tables here have
the same observational unit in individual movie,
but were kept separate due to poor planning.
We can merge these two DataFrames using pandas merge method.
Now we can see that the two tables have been merged and we have our review ID,
movie title, viewer, review,
and rating columns all in one table.
By default, merge performs an inner join using intersection of keys from both frames,
in this case the ID column and preserving the order of the left keys,
in this case the ID column from the merging ex_1 table or our first table here.
Let's take a look at another use case for appending.
In this case again, I'm loading in two tables from two Excel sheets.
We want to append the rows of the second table to the first.
We can use pandas concat method specifying the two DataFrames.
We also specify the parameter ignore index
equals true to make sure that the index is labeled 0^n-1,
where n is the total number of rows.
This is so that we don't end up using
the index values along the concatenation access that can be jumbled up during append.
For example, if we run this operation here,
we see a very clean index and both of our two tables appended.
If we don't specify ignore index is equal to true,
we can see here with this example of the index value 0,
1, 2 repeating as we have appended the two tables.
Finally, let's conclude this with a group by aggregation example.
We're going to conclude by loading a very simple dataset with the date and score columns.
We're then going to use pandas groupby function to group our dataset by date
while setting this to work parameter to
false so that the order of the DataFrame is preserved.
We want it to be March followed by April,
rather than sorting the group keys so that April comes before March by default.
Now comes the aggregation.
We want to get the sum and mean of values
in this score column when we group our dataset by date.
Let's go ahead and run this.
Here we get our result where we can see the sum of
our values in the score column for March and April,
and the mean of these values as well.
This is a foundational example of a groupby,
but there are more parameters and inputs that you can specify
the groupbys and aggregation functions depending on your use case.
This method has a lot of potential to help you better understand your dataset.