Data cleaning is centered around strategizing and decision-making
around how you're going to deal with the issues that you
just identified and go about fixing them.
As part of this process,
it's very useful and completely normal to be able
to reuse your documentation from the assessment stage and
continued to add to that so that you have a documentation of
your thought process as you're approaching cleaning some of these issues.
Now let's go ahead and take a look at a couple of
complex issues that data wranglers deal with when they have to clean data.
Sometimes it can be more complicated to strategize data.
Let's talk about a few complex cleaning tasks that you would need to make a decision
on based on your assessment and your experience around the domain and problem statement.
These issues are dealing with outliers,
dealing with duplicates, and dealing with missing data.
Let's start with outliers.
An outlier is a data point that is considerably
distinct and somewhat of an anomaly from other data samples.
For example, take a look at this bar plot on the screen.
Notice how the bar to the right of the plot at a value
of 120 is distinct from the other data points,
which makes it an outlier.
We define outliers as points that are lying beyond the range that we determine.
Some outliers are a result of mistakes and should be removed.
For example, a student's age being 120 is impossible and should be removed.
Notice how the typical range of students ages for this data set is between 12-15.
But what is this data set was reflecting overall human age.
It's possible for a person to live up to 120,
so the outlier would actually be a correct data point.
If you consider outliers as part of your analysis,
it can often skew summary statistics like your mean and prolong your visualizations.
However, outliers can also represent valuable information
about certain groups of your data that just aren't like the rest of the data,
which may be worth further investigation.
Data wranglers deal with outliers by defining the range that they care about.
They may use information such as the results of
the dot info function from pandas to quickly diagnose issues.
For example, from this information,
we can quickly pinpoint that a min-weight of 48 pounds and
a height of 27 inches does not immediately make sense.
We can then use the min function and sort values functions in
pandas to pinpoint which row is causing this issue and take action.
In order to detect outliers programmatically,
data wranglers can establish boundaries of the typical range of data points,
so any points that fall out of that boundaries are outliers.
There are two common methods to detect outliers.
The first approach is using standard deviation.
For example saying mean plus or minus
one standard deviation are the upper and lower outlier boundaries.
Any data points that are falling outside of this range will be outliers.
Second, using the interquartile range method,
we can also detect outliers.
Let me briefly describe how we can use this method
both visually and programmatically through a boxplot.
We can first calculate the interquartile range value by
subtracting the upper quartile or Q3 from the lower quartile or Q1.
We then calculate the lower bound by subtracting Q1 with 1.5,
multiply it by the IQR, and similarly,
the upper bound is Q3 plus 1.5 times the IQR.
Any values that lie outside the range of our lower to upper bound are outliers.
Visually, box plots can help us quickly grasp whether
outliers are beyond the minimum or the maximum values in the range.
Then data wrangler is may remove
the outliers they have determined to be inaccurate completely,
or remove the outliers temporarily in order to get
summary statistics and keep these outliers separate,
or keep the outliers in the analysis and treat them as regular data points.