Let's take a look at a demo on how to set up your range programmatically,
identify outliers and remove them using Pandas,
and finally, we will see the impact on summary statistics.
We start by importing pandas and reading in our data set into a DataFrame.
Next, we're going to use the.describe function.
With this dataset, we have two columns,
student ID, and age,
corresponding to middle and high-school students,
which means our age range is about 11-18.
The dataset has 527 rows.
Now, let's focus on the age column for the outlier detection for this demo.
From the results of.describe,
we immediately see the minimum value for the age column is three and the max is 75,
which is clearly out of our age range of 11-18.
Applying the sort values method,
we can actually start to see that there are many values below
11 and above 18 as part of our age column in this dataset.
Let's go through how to manually create a range for identifying the outliers.
In this case, since we know that the range of ages should be 11-18.
What we can do is go ahead and use indexing to get the list of rows violating our range.
We can use df.loc to access the rows and
specify our conditions as values and the age column being less than 18,
where we can see here there's a small number of outliers.
We can also do the same thing for ages greater than 18,
where we can see there's a larger number of outliers present in the DataFrame.
What if we didn't know this age range should be 11-18?
Let's use standard deviation to figure out our upper and lower outlier boundaries.
We're going to pull the information we need for
the calculation from the.describe function.
Again,.describe as returning a DataFrame,
so we can actually access the mean and standard deviation values from it using.loc.
Now, to calculate the upper bound,
I'm using here the mean plus 1 standard deviation.
For the lower bound, I'm using the mean minus 1 standard deviation.
Notice how here, if we print the values of the upper and lower bound,
since we're assuming we don't know the actual age range,
the upper and lower bound values are slightly off.
The upper bound is about 25,
and the lower bound is about seven.
Again, we can retrieve the rows that are
violating or outside of this boundary using indexing.
Note here how we're using the OR operator or the OR Boolean operator
so we can get rows both below the lower bound and above the upper bound at the same time.
Let's run this to get a list of these violating rows.
To drop these outliers,
we need to first get the index of the outlier rows that meet
or just identifying here and then pass it to Pandas drop function.
Let's take a look at how to do this.
Here, we're getting the index of these rows.
Then next we're going ahead and passing them to Pandas.drop function,
specifying the index parameter as the index of
the violating rows and then assigning this to a new variable newdf.
If we run.describe on this,
we can start to see that
our min value is at 10 after dropping the rows and the max is at 17.
The mean is about 14,
and the standard deviation at approximately two, whereas previously,
if we look at our original DataFrame,
we can see that the mean was about 16 and the standard deviation was about nine.
We can see the dramatic and obvious influence
our outliers had on this standard deviation calculation.
I'd like to revisit one last thing on pandas drop function.
Note how we directly assign the result of the drop function to newdf.
If we specified a argument called in-place equals true when doing the drop,
it would automatically overwrite the values in our original DataFrame df.
We wouldn't even need to assign it to a value.
Let's do that here, where we specify the dark drop function and
the index and have in place equal to true without assigning it to a variable.
As you can see here,
the results from describe on this df variable,
which is the original DataFrame,
are now the same as what we got as part of our newdf variable.
While in-place equals true can simplify
your implementation because it allows you to minimize the amount
of new variables you create and just directly replace values in your original DataFrame,
it can be dangerous because it overwrites your original data.
Be cautious and frugal with its use.