Duplicates are typically handled by finding
the row with the right information that we want to keep.
Let's take a look at a simple way of detecting
duplicated rows for Pandas DataFrames in Python.
First, we import Pandas and Numpy and load a small test scores data-set.
We then make a copy of our original DataFrame using dot copy.
You can see the first few rows of the DataFrame here.
We can then access the duplicated rows for only the name and age columns by
using the duplicated method on the clean scores DataFrame and indexing by these columns.
The method returns a Boolean series denoting if a row is duplicated.
Here, we see false means the row is not duplicated,
and true means the row is duplicated here.
An important thing to note about the duplicated method is that
by default for each set of duplicated values,
the first occurrence is set on false and all others on true.
For example, when we retrieve duplicated data entries
using this boolean series and applying the.log function,
we're not going to see the first occurrence of the value.
For example, Amy Linn has three test A scores as you can see here.
But, only the first entry with the test score of 95 is not showing
up when we try to look at the duplicated grows. Here's an additional tip.
If there are duplicate rows and you want to drop them,
keep a record of two things.
One, the number of duplicate rows in the original dataset.
We can get the number of duplicated rows by running df.duplicated.sum.
Second, you want to keep in mind
additional data around where the duplicates are occurring.
For example, with this data we can make
some informative assumptions around how prone the data is having two duplicates.
For example, using visual inspection of this entire small DataFrame,
we can ask the question,
are all students that are 15 somehow having
duplicate entries compared to students who are 14?
Perhaps this may be because
all the 15-year-olds are in a different class than the 14-year-olds,
and there were data entry issues for the 15-year-old's classroom.
However, there is a question.
In the first scenario,
if the duplicated rows are entirely the same,
including the test score like the first and last row that we can see here,
we know that the same data was probably entered
twice and we can safely keep one row and remove the others.
But in this case,
Amy has different scores on test A.
How do you determine which row to delete?
In these scenarios with duplicated rows containing different values,
we need additional information to help make the decision.
For example, we may need to check with the data providers like their teachers
to understand what rows are incorrect and if they need to be removed,
then you can remove the data if it is incorrect or keep the data if it is correct.
For example, in this case, seeing how Amy has a score
of 95 and 85 on test A at the same time.
Sometimes, the scenario can get even more complicated.
For example, take a look at this new column that popped up test B score,
which contains students scores now on a different test in addition to test A.
They're duplicated rows with different values in both test A and test B square columns.
To make the decision on how to deal with this,
we also need to check the data providers again.
Let's say after checking with data providers,
we confirm that the duplicated data in some of
the test A scores column values are incorrect and we should remove them,
but the test B score column has correct values.
The data has duplicated rows because the students did take test b multiple times,
and all scores should be kept in the table.
In order to do this, you may consider marking the incorrect duplicate values that
we know for the test A score are there as NaNs and treating them as such.
You may also consider simplifying your data structure, for example,
creating a separate table for the repeated values in test B score if
the structure is significantly different from
the test A square and the rest of the columns.
Let's talk about how to implement the code to remove the duplicated rows.
For the data frame with only the test A score column,
in order to drop the duplicated rows,
you can use pandas,
drop duplicates function,
specifying the subset parameter as the columns we want to use to identify the duplicates.
By default, this parameter is set to all columns,
but here we'd like to narrow it down to name and age.
By default, this function will drop all duplicates except for the first occurrence.
For example, the first entry where anyone's test score is 95 where the index is zero,
will be kept but all later entries of hers will be deleted as we see here.
We can also set the key parameter to last four drop duplicates to,
for example, drop duplicates except for the last occurrence of a value in our dataset.
As you can see here, Amy Linn's first entry with index 0 is deleted,
but the last entry with index 11 is kept.
As we can see here now using the.sum method,
the number of duplicated rows after applying drop duplicates is zero.
What if the value you want to keep is neither the first occurrence nor the last?
Drop duplicates is not going to help you here.
For example, consider that we want to keep
the first and last occurrences of Amy's data,
but we don't want to keep the middle row with the index 5.
In this case, you can actually remove this row using the drop method,
and specifying the index of the row,
which in this case is five.
Note how the middle duplicated is gone from
the DataFrame we specifically retrieved Amy Linn's scores.
For this DataFrame that had both the test A and test B scores,
let's say we want to replace the incorrect test A value on duplicated rows as NaN values.
We can first access the index of the duplicated rows using.index to do this.
Here, we see the duplicated rows are indexes 5, 9 and 10.
Then we can locate these incorrect test A values by using the.loc
method and specifying this dupe index variable
as our rows and the test A scores our column.
We then want to set these values that are in
the test A score column that we know are incorrect,
and are belonging to the duplicated rows to a numpy.nan value.
Let's now look at this DataFrame result again
with the test A score and the test B values.
Note how there aren't any ends now in the test A score column for rows 5, 9 and 10.
But the first occurrences of the data,
like Amy Linn's record, is kept intact.
Now we can meaningfully balance between
the NaN and incorrect values in the test A score,
and the meaningful values that we want to keep as
part of the test B score as part of this DataFrame.