What about missing data?
If we have missing data in a particular column,
there's a number of things we can do.
But first, let's talk about formats.
What if missing data doesn't come in the typical NAN format that we're used to?
What if the missing data, for example,
is written down as a hyphen or an asterisk when we were gathering the data?
Let's start by importing our pandas and numpy libraries and reading
in a small synthetic dataset that contains two columns,
Assessment score 1 and 2.
They don't really mean anything and are just columns
containing random values for the purpose of this walkthrough.
The data has 10,000 rows,
as we can see with the describe method.
Notice how the Assessment score 2 column doesn't
even pop up in the described methods numerical summary,
even though the values of this column seem to be all integers.
In additional, checking the info method summary on the dataset,
we see that it suggests that the Assessment score 1 has
four missing values and there isn't any missing values in the Assessment score 2 column.
This is because missing values in
the Assessment score 2 column are represented by hashtag signs.
For example when I randomly pull up some sample data here,
we can see that the last row is using a hashtag sign for this column.
But how many data points are actually having this hashtag sign and where are they?
You can use two methods to identify this.
The is in method,
and then you can use the replace method.
The is in method helps you identify whether
a certain character is in your dataset and returns all the rows that apply.
For example we first select
the Assessment score 2 column from the DataFrame df Assessment score 2.
Then we use the is in method with hashtag as input to check
if the values in this Assessment score 2 column is the character hashtag.
This will then return a Boolean series
true if the value is a hashtag and false otherwise.
Df.loc is used to filter the DataFrame based on the Boolean series generated by is in.
It then only selects the rows where the condition is true, i.e.
rows where this Assessment score 2 column contains the hashtag character,
as we can see here, and neatly displays it to us in a DataFrame format.
Now next, the replace method is helping
us with replacing a specific value in the dataframe.
For this particular second column,
we're going to go ahead and use the indexing again and use the dot replace method for
replace the hashtag with a nan value or not a number value in the numpy format.
This np.nan comes from the numpy library
and it's used to represent missing or null values in a DataFrame.
Then this modified column with the replace the values is assigned back
to the original Assignment score 2 column in the DataFrame.
Running the is in method, again,
we can see there's no more instances of hashtags now
that we've converted these hashtags to np.nans.
When we use the sum function to count the number of
missing values on the.isna method we can
identify assessment score has four missing values and
Assessment score 2 has 92 missing values.