We'll be taking all of our learnings throughout this course to build
a full end-to-end project with datasets that have real-world importance.
This project will test you on your data analysis process,
how to post questions,
investigate problems, and communicate results.
To get started, you will be provided
a workspace which will contain the dataset and then Jupiter notebook.
You can conduct all of your project work in this workspace,
which will make it easier for you to submit your work directly.
If you prefer to do your project locally,
you can download your project files and work on your local machine.
Best of luck, on your project adventures.