Welcome to this next section on the PCP course on Python's built-in exceptions hierarchy.
This is quite an important section of the course,
because we'll be talking about how to write our functions in a way
where if an error pops up or if something unexpected happens,
we'll have a way to gracefully handle
those circumstances dynamically and automatically within our code.
To get started, let's imagine you're the manager of a theme park overseeing rides,
ticketing, food stalls, staff, and guest services.
Everything runs smoothly until a problem occurs.
Maybe a ride malfunctions, a ticketing,
error causes a mix-up,
or concession stands run out of different supplies or food.
Each of these incidents requires a specific response and plan to handle the situation.
Similarly, in Python, exceptions help us handle unexpected events in a controlled way.
They're like predefined responses to issues that arise while your code is running.
This becomes incredibly important for our functions because just like a theme park,
if you have a ride that requires an inspection several times a day,
you would ideally need to know that the ride is
clear to run before accepting people onto that ride.
An exception, in this case,
would tell us that the ride is not ready to run because
dot dot dot to let us know that we need to fix something,
You might think of errors as bad things, but they are, in fact,
very helpful in guiding us away from errors that could occur from various edge cases.
In summary, don't forget the hierarchy of Python's built in exceptions,
which serve as the foundation for error handling as we are coding.
Just as a theme park manager categorizes incidents,
write issues, ticketing problems,
missing inventory, and so on.
Python too categorizes exceptions into
a hierarchy to help developers manage errors effectively.