KeyError is one of the other types of look up errors in the Python exception hierarchy.
To understand the KeyError,
imagine a guest asks about a particular food item like a churro,
but you look up the wrong food stall.
Python raises a KeyError when you try to access a dictionary key that doesn't exist.
Let's see an example of this in action.
Let's talk about KeyError.
If we want to check for a particular food item at your theme park,
let's first define the types of food stalls and how many there are of each.
For example, let's say that there's five popcorn and three pretzel stands.
We'll run a function that takes in an argument of check food for us
to check if the type of food stall is available in the theme park. We'll do this.
Like so. We'll create a food Stalls variable and we'll set that equal to this object,
which will be our dictionary,
and we'll say that there's five popcorn and three pretzel.
Now, we'll define a function,
and we'll say Def check food availability.
We'll say check food.
Then we'll try and we'll print food stalls.
We'll then pass it and check SD to check the key of that dictionary based on the index,
and then we will accept a KeyError as e. Then we'll say print.
We'll do an F string, say KeyError.
Occurred. We'll pass in our e with squiggly braces? We'll close it out.
Then if we want to check,
if a certain food is in there,
we'll pass in as an argument into check food churro.
This is for us to check if churro is one of the food stalls that's in your theme park.
If we were to run this code,
what do you think the output will be?
If we run this, let's find out.
We'll see key occurred churro.
That's because churro does not exist in the list of food stalls in this dictionary.
Now, what if we asked about Pretzel?
See that example.
If we were to pass in Pretzel,
instead of churro,
what do you think the output of this will be?
We'll see a three printed out telling us that there are three pretzel stands
because we are passing in Pretzel to identify the key,
and then this will return the value of what that's set to.
In this case, since churro isn't in the dictionary food stalls,
Python raises that KeyError that we saw,
which is like a guest asking for something that isn't on the menu.
KeyErrors can help us isolate what is and isn't there for
better visibility across a list of items
should someone ask for something that well isn't there.
But if they do ask for something that is there,
we'll be able to get the value of what we ask for.