One of the last exceptions to cover is the typeError.
Suppose you're at the ticket counter,
and someone tries to pay with a photo instead of money.
Python raises a typeError when an operation
is applied to an object of an inappropriate type,
which is Python's way of saying,
hey, we can't do that.
Let's see how typeErrors can help us with ensuring tickets are purchased correctly.
Now, let's talk about typeError.
Our example of ticket purchasing,
we'll define the ticket price as 50 for $50.
Then there will be two cases to check.
The first is if the payment amount provided by
the user is only an integer or a floating point number.
Two, if the payment amount equals 50 or $50, specifically 50.00.
If both of these are true,
then it returns a key error or a message of invalid amount.
Let's build a function to do just that.
We'll define the ticket price as $50 equals 50,
and then we'll create a function called calculate ticket price.
I'll say def calculate_ticket_price.
We'll pass in a parameter of payment amount.
Then in our try case, we'll say,
if not isinstance of payment amount,
and in parentheses, we'll say int, float.
We'll close that out, and then we'll close out isinstance.
We'll do colon,
and then we'll say raise typeError.
We'll say payment must be a number.
We'll have another if statement,
and we'll say if payment_amount == the ticket_price.
That's an equal equals.
Then we'll say print, we'll say purchase,
meaning that the purchase went through,
then we'll have else print,
we'll say invalid amount.
Now, the same level as try,
we'll have our except case,
we'll say except typeError as E. We'll say print.
Then this is where we printed f string,
and we'll say typeError occurred,
we'll pass in our E with squiggly brackets,
close out our f string,
close out our print statement,
and now we can start testing this function.
We can save this function to our Jupyter notebook cell. Pass that there.
Then now, if a customer tried to pass in photo as a payment method,
let's see what would happen if we tried to do this.
If we try to run this function,
and we pass in the payment amount as photo,
a string, what do you think the output will be for us?
Let's go ahead and try it and see.
We'll get a typeError,
and we'll say typeError occurred,
payment must be a number,
which makes sense because we're defining it as an integer or
a float as it must be an instance of one of these two data types.
That's again, because we need the number to be able to calculate this numerically,
and we can't work with strings.
Now, if we were to update this and pass in 10 like this,
what do you think the output of this is going to be?
Well, 10 is not equal to 50 or 50.00.
This will return an invalid amount.
If you said invalid amount, great job.
Now, if we pass in 50 right here,
what do you think the output of this is going to be when we run this cell?
Well, let's run it and see.
If you said purchased, you're right,
because 50 is exactly the ticket price that we defined up here.
Same thing if we were to pass 50.00.
If we do this, this also will work because 50 and
50.00 is covered by integer and float as the instance type for the data structure.
Overall, when we are using the isinstance built-in Python function,
we are type checking whether the payment amount is a number,
which we see up here.
If it's not, like if someone enters a string like photo, which we saw here,
it raises a typeError with a custom message that we
defined to ensure only integers or floating point numbers are entered in.
Then we added some extra logic where if the payment amount passes our type check,
the function then checks if it matches the ticket price right there.
If it does, it prints purchased.
If it doesn't match, it prints invalid amount.
This way, your functions can handle various types of
incorrect inputs and respond appropriately. Great work.