All right, you're doing great.
The last exception for us to look at here is the ValueError.
For this one, let's say a guest tries to
pay using coins that aren't recognized by the machine.
A ValueError is raised when a function receives
an argument of the right type but an inappropriate value.
Let's run through one more example to see where ValueError can help us.
Now, let's talk about ValueError.
With ValueErrors, we might get the right data type,
but the value could be wrong. What does that mean?
Well, let's continue with our example from earlier,
where we're trying to process a payment at your theme park.
It would make sense to use the int built in Python function to turn
a user's amount submitted into an integer to
process a ticket payment or a food stall payment.
But what if the actual payment itself doesn't have
that type checking is instance payment amount int float like we had earlier.
Just because we turn an input into an integer,
doesn't mean that it does, in fact,
become a real integer or floating point or whatever type we're trying to turn it into?
In our function process payment,
the user submits an amount submitted like this and we'll print the amount,
like what we're going to do right now.
We're going to say, def process_payment,
and we'll say amount_submitted,
then in our try case,
we'll say amount = int amount_submitted.
Then we'll print the amount.
Otherwise, we have our accept case,
and we'll say accept ValueError as e. Then we'll print an f string,
and we'll say ValueError occurred and pass in the e,
and the f string,
and then we'll close out the print statement.
Now, if a user submitted fifty,
all spelled out F-I-F-T-Y, well, yes,
that does spell out 50 the number,
but that doesn't get treated as a number in Python,
and we'll get a ValueError.
Let's see exactly what that means.
If we were to run something like this,
where we say process_payment amount_submitted fifty and fifty is a string,
and if we run this, we will get a ValueError.
It'll say ValueError occurred invalid literal for integer with base 10 fifty.
However, if we were to put in the actual number 50 like this,
we'll then see it print out the number 50.
Now, because we're using the int function,
if we were to pass in a floating point such as this,
what do you think the output of this would be?
Let's run it and find out.
If we execute the cell,
we'll see that it'll output 50.
This two will output 50 and not 50.00.
ValueErrors help us make sure what we submit into a function or
process in a function will be what we expect to recognize.
In this case, converting the string fifty, F-I-F-T-Y,
two integer causes a ValueError,
which is like feeding unrecognized coins into a vending machine.
The machine can accept coins,
but not these particular ones,
hence the error, and hence why we see ValueError specifically.