Great job going through all of these exceptions and examples.
Like managing a theme park,
knowing how to handle different types of exceptions
ensures that your code stays functional and responsive,
even when unexpected issues arise.
Each category of exception has its own role.
Much like the specific protocols
a park manager would have in place for different incidents.
Understanding and utilizing this exception hierarchy,
you write more and more Python code.
You gain the ability to respond to a wide range of potential issues in your programs.
From handling user interruptions with keyboard
interrupt to managing unexpected data types with type error.
Each exception type helps you diagnose specific issues systematically,
making your code more stable and reliable.
With this knowledge, you're now equipped to gracefully handle errors and
create Python code that can stand up to real world scenarios,
keeping everything running smoothly.
Great job and keep it going into this next section.