Exception handling is one of the best ways we can ensure our code is complete,
handles various edge cases,
and is also explainable should anyone else be working on or with the code we write.
Now, imagine your back managing your theme park,
keeping everything running smoothly is very popular
and there is high traffic going into your theme park throughout the day.
But no matter how well things are planned, sometimes issues arise.
Big issues can pop up,
like ride malfunctions, tickets getting misplaced,
or food orders going wrong.
In Python, we have a very powerful tool called
Exception Handling that helps us address unexpected issues in our code,
much like having contingency plans in the park for every possible scenario.
Throughout this course, you have been already using exception handling,
whether you've known it or not.
This is how we've handled edge cases like try X Y Z or accept A B C,
which means, run this X Y Z code first.
If there's no errors, that's fine,
but if there are errors,
run the exception case,
A B C. This is,
if else that we learned about previously,
except this is related to whether the code runs correctly or not.
For example, if there's a bug exception, so on.
Now that we know all of the different exceptions that could pop up, in this section,
we'll dive into the core concepts of Exception Handling with Python,
learning how to manage unexpected events in our code with Finesse and Ease.
We'll cover the tri accept block,
ordering exception branches for precision,
propagating exceptions to other functions,
and delegating exception handling responsibilities.
If you're ready to dive into this, let's get started.