The cornerstone of exception handling in Python is the try-except block.
Pictured as a safety net under a high wire act at the theme park.
We wrap the potentially risky code like a daring stunt in a try block.
Then use an except block to catch
any exceptions that might occur and handle them gracefully,
just like catching a performer who misses a step.
Let's see this in action with a simple example.
Let's talk about try and except.
To see an example of try and except,
let's make a function that would serve somewhat a snack.
But in our function, it only serves popcorn
since this is a function for the popcorn food stand.
We'll define the function as serve popcorn that passes in an argument of a snack.
The function will first try to run the code with the
if clause checking if the snack is not popcorn.
If it's not popcorn, we'll get a value error,
and this will trigger the except or exception case.
Otherwise, we'll get a response about serving the snack.
Let's do this right now.
We'll define our function,
so def serve popcorn,
and we'll pass in snack as our parameter.
Then we'll try, so it'll be the first thing that we do,
and we'll say if snack does not equal popcorn,
then we'll raise a value error,
and we'll say, we only serve popcorn.
Then we'll print our string,
and we'll say serving snack,
close out our s string,
and then we'll close out our print statement.
Otherwise, in the except case,
we'll send the value error,
and we'll say value r as E,
and we'll print an F string of an error,
and then we'll pass in that error with the squiggly brackets,
and we'll close out that print statement.
If we were to try and send in the snack of candy into our function such as this,
serve popcorn candy, can you guess what the output of this code is going to be?
When we run this code, we'll see error.
We only serve popcorn.
Here we are attempting to serve a snack that isn't on our menu at the popcorn stand,
so the value error is raised.
The try-except block catches it and
prints a custom message instead of letting the program crash.
However, if we attempted to serve the snack popcorn that is on the menu,
and we did something like this.
Can you guess what we'll see when we run this?
We'll see serving popcorn.
The try-except allows us to handle errors
gracefully and keep the park running smoothly. Great work.