One important concept to note about
Python is that not all exceptions work in the same way,
and some might need to be handled in a specific order.
Think of this as prioritizing responses to various incidents at the theme park.
If a ride breaks down,
you would want to address that before a spilled drink
or running out of one of the 10 many flavors of soda.
Python, ordering our except branches correctly allows us to handle specific exceptions,
first, second, third, fourth,
and so on ensuring that the most critical issues are caught early,
Let's enhance our popcorn serving
function to handle multiple different types of exceptions.
Now let's talk about ordering the except branches.
To enhance our snack serving function that makes popcorn at the popcorn stand,
we can mix in a few different except clauses,
such as one for different types of errors we might expect to encounter.
So, how would we go about doing this?
Well, we can define our function with def serve snack,
and we can pass in a snack and also a quantity,
depending on what we might expect that we would need.
So, in our tri case, we will say,
if quantity is less than zero,
we're going to raise a value error and say quantity can't be negative.
We'll also say if snack is not equal to
popcorn will raise a type error and say unknown snack type.
Then we'll print an F string,
and we'll say serving, and we'll put quantity in squigly brackets.
And we'll say serving quantity portions of and then put snack in squigy braces,
close out our f string,
close out our print statement, and then we're going to say
serving quantity portions of snack.
Otherwise, we're going to have and except type error.
So in this except case,
we're going to say te for type error and then we're going to say print f string,
we're going to say type error then to put it in squiggly brackets,
te, close out the string,
close out the print statement.
And we're going to do another one of these except cases.
Where this is going to be a value error.
And we're going to say that's ve.
Pass that in, and then this will change to be value error.
So we have these different except branches after
our tri case branch to check for different errors that could come up.
Now, if we try to run this function by passing in
a non popcorn snack and a negative number,
what would that give us.
So if we try to do something like this,
where we say serve snack,
pass in Candy and pass in minus one,
what is the output of this going to be?
Well, first, let's save this function to our Jupiter notebook.
And then if we try to run this,
we're going to get a value error that says,
quantity can't be negative.
However, if we try to run this next one,
which is serve snack popcorn.
And four, all the conditions are valid.
So can you guess what we're going to see when we run this?
We'll see serving four portions of popcorn.
By ordering our except blocks accordingly,
we prioritize catching specific issues.
Here, we catch value error for a negative number or
a negative quantity of that snack and type error for an incorrect snack type,
ensuring that each issue gets appropriate responses.