Sometimes an error in one part of your code affects other parts,
much like a malfunctioning ride at
the theme park impacting other areas of the park as well.
Components can often be interconnected,
and the effect from one is felt in one or more places elsewhere.
Python allows exceptions to be passed or propagated to
higher levels in the code where they can be handled more broadly.
This way, an error in a specific function can bubble up and be
managed by a function at a higher level. That's a lot.
What exactly does that mean when we're writing Python code?
Imagine we have a ticket purchasing function
that relies on another function to verify funds.
If an exception occurs in the funds checking function,
it can propagate up to the ticket purchasing function.
This can be a helpful way to make interrelated functions,
while also making sure that if any errors occur,
they can still be found.
Also, since we are decompartmentalizing our code,
instead of making a monolith function with everything in it,
we can make individual functions and
handle them separately rather than all in the same place.
If we run this function such as passing a -10 into purchase ticket -10,
this will return ticket purchase failed.
Funds cannot be negative.
The value error raised in
the check funds function propagates up to purchase ticket where we handle it.
This flow ensures that the ticket purchasing process is robust,
catching any underlying issues and handling them appropriately.