Just as a theme park manager might delegate tasks to staff members throughout the park,
Python allows you to delegate error handling to the parts of the code best suited for it.
This is very useful when multiple functions in a program can encounter similar errors,
and we want a higher-level function to take care of them.
In a sense, we ask Python to escalate up to make an executive decision about what to do.
Let's talk about delegating responsibility for handling exceptions.
Imagine that each attraction at the park might break down.
But we want a central team to handle repairs.
We'll create a function to simulate this where
the attractions pass on the error to a repair team.
First, we'll write a function,
and we'll say def ride_operation.
We'll then pass in a ride as a parameter.
We'll say if ride,
not in roller coaster or ferris wheel,
this will be our list.
Then we will raise a value error,
and that will return an F string,
and it'll say ride the input into the function as an argument is not a valid ride.
Once it's checked against the list that we define there,
we'll then close out our value error,
and that rounds out our ride operation function.
Now what we'll do is we'll define a managed park function,
so we'll say def manage_park,
also passing in ride as a parameter.
We'll say try and we'll say ride_operation,
which is the same function that we have up here.
We pass in ride similarly,
and then we'll print an F statement.
F string, and we'll say the ride is running smoothly.
Close out our print statement.
Then we'll have an except case branch,
where we'll say ValueError as E,
and we'll say print F,
and we'll say maintenance team.
We have an issue ride,
and that's in squiggly brackets,
and then we'll pass in the error,
also in squiggly brackets.
We'll close the F string with the end quote.
Then we'll close out the print statement like that.
Now, if we were to run this,
where we say manage_park water slide,
notice how we're going to invoke this function.
Once we pass and ride,
this is the argument here because we have a parameter here.
This is going to call the ride operation function, which is here.
Then that passes in that same input.
This is going to return information that we can then use in the manage park function.
If we were to pass this into manage park,
can you guess what the output of this is going to be?
When we run this, we're going to see maintenance team.
We have an issue with the water slide error.
Water slide is not a valid ride,
which makes sense because it's not in this list.
But since roller coaster and ferris wheel are both valid rides,
if we were to run something like this,
where we say manage ride roller coaster,
we will see the roller coaster is running smoothly.
Here, the ride operation function checks if the ride is valid in this list here.
If not, it raises a value error,
this exception is then caught by the manage park function in here,
which handles it by alerting the maintenance team because this will
cause the except ValueError as E branch to be invoked.
This method lets us centralize our error handling across our Python code,
making the code cleaner and more manageable. Great work.