Let's talk about base exception.
A great way to show this type of exception in
action is with writing a function that handles division.
In our function, we'll use the built in input function from Python to
allow a user to enter something that will be
used as an input value to run the function with.
We'll first define a function called division function.
We'll say def division_function,
and then we will try,
we'll put value equals,
and we'll use the end function to turn into an integer,
and we'll say input, then in parentheses,
and we'll say enter a number,
put a space, end quote,
and then we have those two parentheses to close everything out,
and then we'll say result equals 10 divided by value.
We'll say print, and then we'll write an F string,
and we'll say the result is and squiggly brackets result.
We'll do end quote to close out the F string,
and then we have that end parentheses to close out the print statement.
Then we'll have an accept statement that we'll say accept
base exception as E. And then we'll say print,
we'll have another F string, and we'll say an error occurred.
Again, we'll put in squiggly brackets E for error.
We'll close out the quote,
and then we'll close out the print statement.
Now when we run our division function below,
let's see what will happen.
This will now run, an input field will
pop up and then we'll be prompted to enter a number.
Let's say that we put in 10,
we'll press enter, the output is 1.0,
and that makes sense because 10 divided by the value which we put in as 10 is one,
so this is 1.0, which makes sense.
Now we know that it's working,
but what if we were to execute the cell and then we put in zero?
Can you guess what the output is going to be now?
We get an error, and it says an error occurred division by zero.
Also, what if we put in Hello World?
We'll press enter, and we'll say Hello World,
now we get an error occurred,
invalid literal four integer with base 10, Hello World.
This code will catch any error that might arise,
whether it's a division by zero which you just saw,
or an invalid input like a string right here,
when we should only enter a number or an unexpected interruption.
Here, we can see that the base exception covers
all possible exceptions in Python with this.
We use the variable E,
like so in the error message to let us know that first an error occurred and then to tell
us what exactly that error message was with E when we passed that into the error message.