Just below base exception is the exception class,
which is like a senior manager overseeing most errors we encounter.
When we refer to handling exceptions,
we usually mean those derived from exception.
It covers a wide range of errors from value error to type error,
and is a great catch all for general issues that don't need special handling.
Similar to base exception,
we can write our except statement and switch base exception to just exception.
Using exception as the default catch in our code is often
recommended because it won't interfere with our system exiting exceptions,
like system exit or keyboard interrupt,
which we will learn about in a little bit.