Next up in our hierarchy of exceptions,
we have keyboard interrupt.
Picture yourself in the theme park and suddenly you hit an emergency stop button.
Keyboard interrupt is raised when a user manually interrupts the program,
usually by pressing control C. It's handy
for halting a running script when you need to stop immediately.
Imagine you need to stop a ride from going further or to close a ride.
There are many times where a user's input could be necessary,
and we'd want Python to handle the rest for us after a human initiates a stop sequence.
This one will also be a bit easier to see in an example.
Let's dive into one right now.
Let's talk about keyboard interrupt.
For your theme park, let's say that the rides need to have a switch to
turn them on and also have a human override to stop them at any time.
We'll create a run theme park ride function,
and once it's running,
it will need a user input to write stop.
If a user does write stop,
then this raises a keyboard interrupt exception,
and then this will shut down the ride our code from running.
Let's write an example of this function and see this exception in action.
We will define this function, we'll say define,
def run, theme park, ride,
then we'll do tr for a tri case,
and we'll say,
this is true, user input equals input.
We'll say type, stop to stop the ride colon space,
and then we'll do quotes.
Then we'll close out that parenthesis for the input.
Then we'll say if g user input dot
lower because we want to convert it into lower case equals, stop.
It's not case specific.
Then we'll raise a keyboard interrupt.
We'll go back to the same level of try.
We'll now write our except case,
and we'll say except, keyboard interrupt.
Then we'll say, Colin here, we'll say print,
say you interrupted and stopped the ride. Close out that print statement.
Then, if we were to run this function,
can you guess what the output is going to look like?
Let's run this code and find out.
When we run this, we'll see an input field,
and it'll say type stop to stop the ride.
Inside this box, we will need to write the word
stop to end this ride and stop our code from running.
Will continue to stay running and continuously prompt you for an input.
If we were to type stop,
this raises a keyboard exception,
which then causes us to execute an end to the function.
This stops the program and then triggers the accept block,
which is why we see this print statement here.
It says, you interrupted and stop the ride,
which is why we see that here.
Otherwise, the code will keep running,
or should I say our theme park ride continuing to operate as expected?