Continuing along Python's exception hierarchy.
There are abstract exceptions.
Think of them as foundational guidelines that help
create more specific types of exceptions we could encounter,
and those we should look out for in our Python code.
Abstract exceptions aren't typically raised on their own,
but rather they serve as a base framework for more detailed error classes.
Examples of abstract exceptions include arithmetic error,
which deals with numeric calculation errors and lookup error,
which deals with issues when accessing
non-existent entities like indices or dictionary keys.
Next, we'll explore index error and key error as they relate to lookup error.