Next type of exception we'll look at is the look up error.
Imagine you're at the theme parks Lost and Found.
Someone comes up looking for a lost item, but it's not in the system.
This doesn't always mean that it's the system or your park's fault.
Perhaps someone believes they left their bag at your park,
but in reality, they never brought it to the park,
and it's in fact still in their car in the parking lot.
But if they request a search through your Lost and found,
it would make sense that the item would not be found.
Not only is it not in the system,
but it was never in the park to begin with.
Look up error acts as a general error
that Python raises when it can't find what it's looking for,
whether it's an item in a list or a key in a dictionary.
This look up error based class covers specific errors like index error and key error,
which we'll explore next.
Let's talk about look up error.
To see this in action,
let's continue with our Lost and Found example from earlier.
In our Lost and Found checker function,
globally define our lost and found dictionary,
where we have one pair of sunglasses,
two hats, and three water bottles.
If somebody were to come up to your Lost and Found asking for a bag,
this item in question of bag would be
an argument sent into our Check Lost and Found function.
So let's write some code to illustrate this.
We'll define our dictionary like this,
where we'll say Lost and Found equals,
and then in squiggly brackets,
we'll say sunglasses with one,
hat with two and water bottle with three,
indicating how many items there are of each of these categories of items.
Next, we'll define our check lost and found function,
or we'll say deaf, check, lost,
and found and then we'll say item in
question as a parameter to pass into our function then try,
and this will say print, lost and found.
Then we will look for the key of item in question for the index.
Then, otherwise, we're going to have a look up error as E,
and then we'll say print F string,
we'll say item, not found in lost and found.
We'll have a E to return that error,
we'll close out our string,
close out our print statement and then what we'll do is we'll copy this function,
and then as an argument,
we'll pass in bag because this is the item that we want to
check if this is in our check lost and found function,
which then checks our lost and found object,
which is our dictionary there.
If we run this function, What do you think we'll see?
When we run this function,
we will see item not found in lost and found bag.
This error is actually a key error,
which we will learn about in a moment as a type of look up error.
But most importantly, the look up error is fired off
because the item bag is not found in the dictionary, Lost and Found.
There's only sunglasses, hat, and water bottle.
Using look up in this way provides us with flexibility for handling
both key error and index error without needing separate except clauses for each.