Index error is one of the types of look up errors in the Python exception hierarchy.
To understand the index error,
let's say you're looking for a specific rides maintenance record,
but you mistakenly check for the record at a non existent position in the database.
An index error is raised when you try to access
an index that doesn't exist in a list or other ordered collection.
What does this look like in practice?
Let's say an example. Let's talk about index error.
To use our maintenance record check example,
let's see we have maintenance records for three rides, A,
B and C, defined in our maintenance records list.
If we wanted to check the record for the ride at Index five,
like we do when we write check ride maintenance record check record equals five,
this will fail and cause an error.
Let's see exactly what I mean.
When we create a list like this,
and we'll say maintenance records equals,
and then a list with square brackets,
ride A, ride B, and write C,
we'll then write a function that says,
check, ride, maintenance record.
We'll then pass in a check record parameter here.
And then we'll try and we'll say print maintenance records.
Here. Copying this up here.
Then we'll check the check record,
and we'll use that as the index to check against that list.
Otherwise, we'll say accept index error as E. We'll
then print in F string and we'll say index ever occurred.
We'll then use curly brackets.
We'll close that out, we'll close out our print statement,
and we'll then run this function.
Specifically, we can pass in an argument here,
and we'll say check record equals five.
We want to check at index five.
Now, what do you think the output will be when we execute this code?
Let's find out we'll run it,
and we'll see index error code list index out of range.
In this case, we're trying to access an invalid index which raises an index error,
similar to someone looking up a ride record that doesn't exist in the database.
However, if we wanted to check the record at index zero,
remember, this is the first item in the list, we could do this.
We could copy this,
and we could write Check record of zero.
What do you think the output of this will be?
When we run this cell,
we now see Ride A,
and that's printed out because there are three rides,
and zero is in the scope of Index 022,
which is Index 0,
Index 1, and Index 2.
We're looking for Index 0,
which is the first item, and that's why we see A right there.