In this lesson, you learned about a number of
different aspects regarding the design of visualizations.
You first learn about levels of measurement.
Depending on the types of data you want to plot,
qualitative or quantitative, discrete or continuous,
there will be different plot types that are best suited for the job.
Your choice of visual encodings such as position,
color, and shape will depend on the types of data you plot.
You will see this in action in the upcoming lessons.
You also learned about design elements that can
interfere with the clarity and accuracy of your plots.
By being mindful of chart junk, data-ink ratios,
and life factors, you can ensure that
your visualizations present their messages at their best.
While these concepts are most pertinent during
the creation of explanatory visualizations,
your awareness of these issues will also be useful during exploration.
This will ensure that you come up with
the proper conclusions before sharing them with others.