In order to choose an appropriate plot for your data,
you need to understand the types of the data you have.
One common method divides data into four data types: nominal,
ordinal, interval, and ratio.
The first two are known as qualitative or categorical types,
while the last two are known as quantitative or numeric types.
Furthermore, quantitative types include a second classification, discrete or continuous.
Features that are categorical are those that act as non-numeric labels on the data.
Nominal data are pure labels without any natural ordering.
Examples of this include things like movie genre or country.
Ordinal variables are also labels,
but unlike nominal variables,
these include an intrinsic ordering.
Examples of this type of variable include letter grade on
a test or ranking at the end of a competition.
While categorical variables might be recorded numerically,
you should not make the mistake of performing numeric operations with them.
For example, let's say that the rankings
above come from a list of the best books of the year.
You wouldn't expect the goodness of
the first and second place books combined to equal that of the third place book.
Or that the second and third place books sum up to the first place book.
You can only say that first place is better than
second place and second place is better than third,
but not by how much.
Knowing the difference between first and second doesn't necessarily
tell you that the difference between second and third will be the same.
Quantitative data on the other hand,
take numerical values that allow for mathematical operations.
For interval-type data, differences between numeric values are meaningful.
Examples of this type of variable include year or temperature in Celsius.
An increase or decrease of one point will
mean the same thing no matter where you are on each scale.
Ratio type data also allows for different comparisons,
but also require an additional property.
For a variable to be considered ratio type,
there must be a meaningful zero point such that ratio judgments are meaningful.
Consider the earlier example regarding temperature in Celsius.
Since temperature is interval,
the difference between five degrees and
10 degrees is the same as that between 10 and 15 degrees.
But Celsius is not a ratio-type variable.
You wouldn't say that 10 degrees is twice as hot as five degrees,
or 15 degrees three times as hot as five.
Examples of ratio type data include the length of a document
by word count or measurement of mass in kilograms.
All quantitative variables, whether interval or ratio type,
can also be classified as discrete or continuous.
Discrete quantitative variables can only take on specific values,
while continuous variables can take on any value.
Year and word count are examples of discrete variables.
They can only take on integer values.
Temperature and mass are examples of continuous variables.
These variables can take on any number of decimal values if we
had instruments capable of recording them with that precision.