Have you ever wondered how a car drives by itself
or how you get a list of products suggested to you that you didn't know you needed?
Maybe you've received an event recommendation that ended up rocking your world.
If you've ever thought about these topics,
then this is the absolute best course for you to take.
In this course, we'll dive into the essentials of Python programming,
helping you understand the fundamental concepts and skills needed to
get certified as an entry level Python programmer, PCP.
Python is amazing because it helps you build all of
these really cool technologies and systems that we use and rely on.
You're interacting with Python every single day,
whether you realize it or not.
The PCP certification shows that you
are familiar with universal computer programming concepts,
like data types, containers,
functions, conditions, loops, and more.
It measures your ability to accomplish coding tasks
related to the essentials of programming in Python,
ensuring that you are well prepared to start
your journey in the world of software development.
By the end of this course, you'll be equipped with the knowledge and
skills to tackle the PCP exam confidently.
You'll understand Python's logic and structure,
be able to work with literals,
variables, operators, data types,
collections, like lists, and dictionaries.
You'll also be comfortable with control flow mechanisms,
functions, and handling exceptions.
I'll be guiding you every step of the way.
My name is Brian Hough.
I'm an AWS DevTools Hero,
Full-Stack Software Engineer,
and Creator of the Tech Stack Playbook.
I've worked with companies like AWS, Harvard University,
freeCodeCamp, the Motley Fool,
Boston University, and more.
Before I became a software engineer,
I worked in public relations,
social media, and marketing,
and taking a Udacity nanodegree program gave me life changing
skills that inspired me to actually pursue a career in tech.
Whether you already have programming skills and you're looking to get certified,
or if this is your first introduction to programming,
I want to welcome you here.
I'm excited to help you learn Python and
further your career goals and dreams wherever they may lead.
Becoming PCP certified is your first step toward
a career in Python programming and related technologies.
It helps you stand out from other candidates and can
open doors to junior level jobs in the IT sector.