Now that we're getting more comfortable with Python and how to structure our code,
data types and variables.
Let's dive into operators.
These are the commands that allow Python to do
all sorts of numeric and math based actions for us,
all without needing to break a sweat.
Operators are symbols that perform operations on variables and values.
When we add numbers, subtract numbers,
multiply, divide, and so on,
we're doing specific operations with these numbers,
and Python has symbols for performing these numeric operators that we can use.
I'm sure you've seen many of these numeric operators before.
But if these are totally new for you, that's great too.
Let's check out which operators we're going to be
going through in this section, exponentiation,
multiplication, division, modulus, floor division, addition and subtraction.
Let's go through each of these examples one by one together.
First, we'll define two variables.
A=10 and b=3.
Exponentiation raises one of these numbers to the power of another number.
Such as a**b.
Here, 10^3=1,000.
Multiplication. This multiplies two numbers together, such as a*b.
Here, 10 multiplied by three equals 30 or a*b.
For division, this divides one number by another,
resulting in a float or a decimal,
such as a/b or a divided by b.
Here, 10/3=3.333 repeating.
Modulus returns the remainder when one number is divided by another.
Think of it as what's left over after dividing.
A and you'll use that percent sign with b.
Here we see 10/3 leaves a remainder of one,
so only one will be returned.
We know this because three goes into 10 3 times 3,
6, 9, and then ten minus nine equals one.
So that's how we get the modulus out of that.
Let's say we have another example,
c=5 and d=10 we will write c%d.
Here, the modulus would be zero because five goes into 10 two times evenly,
and then there's no remaining numbers left.