You might be thinking, Yikes,
when would I ever need to know something like this?
Let's take a real world example.
To make it make sense a bit more clearly.
Imagine you're writing a Python application to organize a game night,
and you want to split participants into two teams,
team A and team B.
To make the process fair and random,
you decide that even numbered participants will go to
team A and odd numbered participants will go to team B.
To determine if a participant number is even or odd,
you can use the modulus operator to accomplish this.
If the participant number divided by two leaves a remainder of zero,
it is an even numbered participant.
Otherwise, that participant is an odd numbered participant.
Let's build out the code for this together.
First, we're going to list out the participant numbers.
We'll create a variable called participants in a list or array going
1-10 to indicate the number of participants that we need to split into groups.
Next, we'll separate the participants into two teams
or two lists as a arrays based on their numbers like this.
Team A will be set to this empty list,
and team B will be set to this empty list right now.
Next, we're going to write a four loop to put the participants into each of these groups.
We'll start this off with saying four item in group,
so participant in participants.
For any item in participants right here,
we're then going to do an even check.
If part and I'll actually copy this there.
If participant, we'll use the modulus operator to divide by two and then equals zero,
then we're going to add them to Team A.
Team A, and then we'll use the append method.
Then we're going to take this item, and drop it in there.
Otherwise, we're going to do the odd check.
Else, meaning if they're not even, they must be odd.
If odd, then we're going to add that participant to team B. We'll say team B.
We'll use append method.
We'll drop in participant. Close that out.
Then after we run this loop,
we'll then say, which in team A, which are in team B.
So we'll say Team A.
Do a comma and then we'll write out all the members of Team A.
Then I just copied that line.
To do, the odd numbered participants,
and we're going to change that to Team B.
Now, when we execute this,
we see that 2, 4, 6,
8, 10 are team A,
which is the even numbered, and team B is odd numbered, 1, 3,
5, 7, 9,
which is exactly what we would expect.
The output is again,
two lists, but they're sorted by even numbers and odd numbers.
What we just did was combine the ultra powerful utility of four loops with crafty,
if else logic, and a handy modulus operator
to sort a list of participants easily and quickly.
By using the modulus operator,
we can easily divide the participants into
two teams based on whether their numbers are even or odd,
ensuring a fair and random distribution.
Sorting and filtering algorithms are some of the most important types of functions,
such as when we think about returning search results
or highlighting certain information that a user filters for.
Now you're well on your way to Python Mastery.