With floor division, this divides one number by
another number and returns the largest whole number less than or equal to the result.
It's like regular division but without the decimal part.
We write A, backslash, backslash, B,
and here, 10/3 equals three without the remainder.
Three is what is returned rather than the modulus, which would return.
In addition, this adds two numbers together,
such as A plus B.
Here ten plus three equals 13.
Finally, with subtraction, this operation subtracts one number from another,
such as A minus B.
Here, ten minus three equals seven.
One quick tip, make sure that you're watching
the demos and actually practicing these exercises.
It's so critical that you get practice watching the code
and then writing your own code to succeed in becoming a Python expert.