By now you should be familiar with variables and basic operators,
such as addition and subtraction.
Now we're going to get a little more advanced and talk about shortcut operators.
Shortcut operators, also known as compound assignment operators,
combine an arithmetic operation with an assignment.
These operators make the code more concise and readable.
For basic assignment, let's start off with the simplest implementation.
This operator assigns a value to a variable,
for example, x = 10.
This assigns the value 10 to x.
In the addition assignment,
this operator adds the right operand to
the left operand and assigns the result to the left operand.
Is the equivalent of x = x + 5,
x = 10, x += 5.
This is equivalent to x + x + 5.
X now becomes 15.
In the subtraction assignment,
this operator subtracts the right operand from
the left operand and assigns the result to the left operand.
This is the equivalent of x = x - 3.
You have x = 15,
x -= 3,
and this is the equivalent of x = x - 3.
X now becomes 12.
Now, let's look at how to combine numbers together,
either individually or by each other.
In the multiplication assignment,
this operator multiplies the left operand by
the right operand and assigns the result to the left operand.
This is the equivalent of x = x *2.
We have x = 12,
x * = 2,
and this is the equivalent to x = x * 2.
X now becomes 24.
In the exponentiation assignment,
this operator raises the left operand to the power of
the right operand and assigns the result to the left operand.
Take note that an exponent is asters asterisk,
whereas multiplication is just one asterisk.
An example of exponentiation would be here.
This is the equivalent of x = x asters asterisk 2.
X =3, x asters asters equals 2,
and this is the equivalent of x = x asters asters 2 as x now becomes 9.
Now, let's look at ways to divide numbers into each other.
In the division assignment,
this operator divides the left operand by
the right operand and assigns the result to the left operand.
It is the equivalent of x = x / 4 x = 24.
X / = 4.
This is equivalent to x = x /4 as x now becomes 6.0.
In the floor division assignment,
this operator performs floor division using
the left and right operands and assigns the result to the left operand.
It is the equivalent of x = // 3.
We'll have x = 10, x // =3.
This is the equivalent of x = x // 3 as x now becomes 3.
In the modulus assignment,
this operator takes the modulus using
the left and right operands and assigns them to the result in the left operand.
It's the equivalent of x = x % 5, x =6,
x % = 5,
and this is the equivalent of x = x % 5 as x now becomes 1.
That was a lot of new operators to learn.
Great job. And don't worry if this is still fuzzy.
By practicing your use of these shortcut operators,
you will get much more comfortable with them so you can write
more concise and readable code when you need to
perform these common arithmetic operations and patterns.