Let's now add some special operators to
our toolkit for dealing with specific types of numbers.
When we want to change the sin of a number from positive to negative,
we can use something called a unary operator.
Imagine you're tracking financial transactions,
and you want to represent a refund,
which would be a negative transaction,
as money would be leaving the company as
opposed to coming into the company, which is profit.
Here, the unary dash operator helps us quickly
represent a refund by negating the value of the original transaction.
We'll write the transaction as a whole number to represent the price of the refund.
Then we'll set the refund to a negative number with a unitary operator dash.
This then makes the number negative so that it's
a deductive negative number of the revenue of
the company rather than an additive positive one,
all thanks to our unitary operator in Python.
Now, let's talk about the opposite,
where we want to add numbers together.
Binary operators are crucial for performing
arithmetic and logical operations such as combining numbers together.
Imagine you're calculating the total price of items in a shopping cart.
In the above code, we have two shopping cart items,
and in the third line,
we're using the binary plus operator to add
both variables together to create a sum variable, called total price.
This allows us to calculate the total price by
adding the prices of individual items together.