As we write our Python code,
we'll need to make sure we avoid errors when going through our calculations.
Operator precedence tells Python
the order in which our operations should be performed in our code.
For example, multiplication and
division have higher precedents than addition and subtraction.
This means that they will be done first before any other operations in our code.
A handy phrase to help you remember these numeric precedence rules is PEMDAS.
Please excuse my dear Aunt Sally,
which stands for parentheses,
exponents, multiplication, division, addition and subtraction.
In the order of operations,
P for parentheses means we'll perform these operations first.
E for exponents includes powers and roots, which we'll do next.
Multiplication for M goes from left to right.
Same with the vision. We'll check these operations from left to right.
Then with addition, we'll check left to right and then subtraction from left to right.
A handy pneumonic device,
please excuse my dear Aunt Sally,
helps us remember this order.
Remember, use PEMDAS to guide the correct order of calculations in our code.
Keep this in mind as you go about numeric calculations for these handy strategies,
so you know the order of operations,
and so your Python code does too.
Imagine you're calculating the total cost of items with the discount.
You'll need to ensure that the multiplication for
the quantity happens before subtracting the discount.
Let's write some code that would emulate
how we would calculate the cost of something like this.
What we'll do is that we grade a variable,
and we'll call it price per item,
and we'll set that equal to 50 for $50.
We'll then say the quantity equals three for three items,
and then we'll say that the discount as another variable is set to five for $5.
Now when we are calculating the total cost,
we'll say total cost as a variable,
and we'll set that equal to this function that we're going to write.
We're going to first put the first part in parentheses,
and we're going to say price per item times the quantity.
Given this price per item,
multiplied by the number of the items that there are,
and then we're going to subtract the discount from that.
Then, of course, we'll print our total cost here.
Now, what is the output of this when you run your total cost function?
Did you get 1452? If so, you're right.
Great job. This is because the calculations inside the parentheses go first right here.
Then outside the parentheses goes next, this part.
Without proper precedence, which is defined by our parentheses here,
you might end up with incorrect results.
For example, if you mistakenly calculate the discount first and then multiply,
it could look something like this.
Now if we run this, we'll get -100.
This is just an example, but this leads to
an incorrect calculation due to improper precedence.
If we do not define our parentheses,
and we try to run this, Sometimes you might get the right answer,
but also sometimes you won't.
That's why it's really important to
define exactly what we want to define with precedence.
Because in the incorrect example that you saw a moment ago here,
when we ran this, the discount is subtracted from the quantity first,
which is here, and this leads to a completely wrong result,
because now we're subtracting five from three,
and then multiplying that negative number by the price per item,
which does not make sense here.
By understanding and using operator precedence correctly,
you can ensure your calculations are accurate.
Can you see why this is so important?
Because when we do it correctly,
and we run this, we get the right answer, 145. Great job.