Bitwise operators are used in low level programming,
such as manipulating, which means changing or transforming data at the bit level.
They are important in tasks like setting or checking
the status of specific bits in a byte.
This can be useful in scenarios like managing feature flags such as
make something show or not show in a web application, or device settings.
Think about the settings that you set for your favorite applications.
Wow. That's a lot of technical speak.
Let's think about a real example,
turning on and off specific features in a device.
In this example, we're going to write,
we're going to use the bit wise or operator,
and that will be used to turn on specific features represented by bits.
Each bit in a binary number represents a feature.
By using the or operator,
we can set a desired bits to one enabling those features.
Let's see how this would work.
We'll define a variable called features,
and we'll set that equal to zero b one, two, three, four.
And this is going to be for all features off.
Now, if we want to turn on feature one and three,
what we could do is that we could say features equals features or 0b01 01.
Now, if we were to print bin features.
We're going to get the output of 0b101.
To review, in this demo example here,
we're using a bitwise or operator to set
the variable features to itself combined with 0b01 01,
which turns on specific bits features one and three without changing the others.
Bin function, then prints the binary representation
of features showing which features are on or off.
Python displays this as 0b10 by removing any leading zeros.
In binary, 0b01 01 and
0b101 represent the same number five in decimal.
As the leading zero doesn't change the numbers value.
Python automatically removes unnecessary leading zeros when displaying binary numbers,
so 0b01 01, and is shown as 0b101,
as they are the same number.
Bitwise operators are also useful in optimizing performance.
In systems where memory and processing power are limited.
They allow efficient data manipulation and storage,
making them valuable in embedded systems and other resource constrained environments.