Next, we're going to go through examples of these operators in action.
To note, you don't need to memorize all of the bit equivalents.
That would nearly be impossible without a computer.
But we're going to be explaining this just to
show you what is happening behind the scenes.
Let's see some practical examples of these in some techy Python code.
First is not, and this inverts all the bits of the operand.
The result is the bitwise negation of the value,
which flips all the bits from 0-1 and vice versa.
In brief, let's take a value and then find its polar opposite.
For example, a number that is positive,
this would make it a negative number.
In this example, we have binary,
0101, which is five,
and we have that equal to a.
To invert that, we add the tilde or the squiggly line,
which you'll see on the left of your keyboard.
Front of a variable a to get an output of -6,
which is actually binary 1010 in two's complement form.
In, this performs a bit wise and operation,
where each bit in the result is one,
only if the corresponding bits in both operands are also one.
In this example, the result is 0001 because only the last bit is one in both operands.
Do you see how each number goes across four digits,
operand number 1,
we have 0, 1, 0, 1.
For operand 2,
we have 0, 0, 1, 1.
Because of the end operation,
the only times they match is the last item,
Index 3 for both operands.
We will have zeros for the first three bits because index
01 and 2 are not both 1 between both operands.
However, the last item is,
so it becomes 0001.
With or, this performs a bitwise or operation,
where each bit in the result is 1,
if at least one of the corresponding bits in each operand is also 1.
In this example, the result is
0111 because at least one of the corresponding bits in A or B is also 1.
With operand number 1, we have,
0, 1, 0, 1.
In operand 2, we have,
0, 0, 1, 1.
For the or operation,
each bit in the result is 1,
if at least one of the corresponding bits is also 1.
We get 0111.
This one is more inclusive in
the bit construction as opposed to just a matching operation.
With Xor, this performs a bit-wise Xor operation,
where each bit in the result is 1,
if the corresponding bits and the operands are different.
In this example, the result is
0110 because the corresponding bits in A and B are different.
For operand number 1,
we have, 1, 0, 1.
In operand 2,
we have 0, 0, 1, 1.
For the Xor operation,
each bit in the result is 1,
if the corresponding bits are different,
resulting in, 0,
1, 1, 0.
With left shift, this shifts the bits of the left operands to
the left by the number of positions specified by the right operand filling with zeros.
In this example, this shifts the bits of a 0101,
one position to the left,
resulting in 1010, which is 10 in decimal.
For operand 1,
let's take operand 0,
1, 0, 1.
Shifting left by one position would yield 1,
0, 1, 0.
Now, with right shift, this shifts the bits of the left operand
to the right by the number of positions specified by the right operand.
In this example, this shifts the bits of a 0101,
one position to the right,
resulting in 0010, which is two in decimal.
Let's take operand, 0,
1, 0, 1.
Shifting right by one position would give us,
0, 0, 1, 0.
Great job making it through all of the definitions and examples of bitwise operators.
If this feels overwhelming or too technical,
do not worry, you're doing great.
Focus on understanding the logic of the operators rather
than getting bogged down by the bits and the operands themselves.
Remember, there are countless binary operands for every number.
So the key is to grasp how these operators manipulate binary bits.
By mastering these basic principles,
you'll be able to use bitwise operators
effectively in your Python programming tasks and be well-prepared for your exam.
Keep practicing and you'll gain confidence with these concepts in no time.