To add to our growing list of operators,
in addition to the numeric ones,
there's also ones for strings.
If you remember from the previous section,
strings are packets of text characters surrounded by single or double quotation marks.
To work with strings, we can,
of course, declare them as a variable.
But some other nifty calculations we can do are these two types of operations.
Concatenation, which uses a plus that unites strings together and repetition,
which uses an asterisk that repeats a string by a certain number of times.
Let's look at what this means for our Python code next.
With concatenation, this operator joins two strings together, effectively adding them.
For example, if you have two strings,
Hello and World,
using the concatenation plus operator,
will combine them into Hello World.
Here's how that looks in code.
Can you tell what this would output?
If you guessed Hello World, then you're right.
In this above example,
String 1 is Hello,
and String 2 is World.
The plus operator concatenates them with a space in between,
resulting in Hello World with a space in the middle.
With repetition, this operator repeats a string a specified number of times.
For instance, if you have the string, Hello,
and you want to repeat it three times,
you use the asterisk operator to specify number three, like this.
Can you tell what this will output?
If you guessed, HelloHelloHello, you got it right.
Notice that we aren't adding a space in between the strings.
So it will be Hello times three, quite literally.