Python is really exciting,
because you can do so many important operations
and types of work with this programming language.
At a high level, Python is an object-oriented programming language,
meaning you can work with different types of data.
But what does that actually mean?
When we think about data science, for example,
Python comes with numerous libraries and
packages to help us analyze and visualize datasets.
We'll be doing that in the project for this course.
You'll see that in a little bit later.
This helps us really understand and analyze the world around us,
like predicting weather patterns or understanding global trends.
Additionally, machine learning and
artificial intelligence are two areas that are very exciting,
and Python is uniquely created to work with them.
You can work with AI models to predict and classify information.
Think about autonomous driving cars,
recommendation systems that suggest movies or products,
or personalized social media feeds.
These are all important use cases for AI,
and Python is optimized for this process.
App development is also very hot right now.
There are powerful and popular frameworks like Flask,
Django, and Streamlit.
These frameworks provide great ways to build applications.
For example, you could create a website to display
your favorite recipes or build a tool to manage your personal finances.
Python is also great for creating different types of automated tasks.
For instance, you can set up scripts to back up your photos
every week or send yourself reminders for important events.
There are many great use cases for Python,
and we're going to work on some of those in this course.