Python is a language,
so we need to think about the words and the phrases that make up Python's vocabulary.
These are known as Python's Lexis.
Think of it as a dictionary that tells you what types
of tokens or words Python will understand.
Python has about 30 keyword identifiers,
such as and,
is, for,
while, del, class,
continue, finally, accept, and many more.
Don't worry about memorizing all of these right now. There's a lot.
We'll get more familiar with these through an iterative approach across this course.
So these will become second nature to you the more that you're reintroduced to them.
Just know that there are specific keywords that tell
Python how to do very specific commands and actions.
Also a fun fact about Python is that
the print statement was considered a keyword in Python 2,
but then it became a function in Python 3.
This shows how languages evolve,
just like any language, and Python is no exception.
Usually, when you learn a programming language for the first time,
you'll write hello world as a fun introduction.
So we're going to do that in a demo momentarily.