To understand Python's logic and structure,
we need to start thinking about Python's lexis
and keywords that are a part of that vocabulary.
This will allow Python to know what types of
specific commands it's baked into and understanding what we want to use those for.
Think of these as the little blocks that you stack on top of each other.
These are how you create your functions or your scripts in Python.
There are several reserved keywords, phrases,
or words that have special meaning in the Python language,
and you've already gotten some exposure to some of those from the earlier videos.
But we're going to dive into what those specifically look like.
When we start thinking about these types of keywords,
if is used for conditional statements,
else specifies a block of code to be executed if the condition is false,
elif stands for "else if" and is used to check multiple conditions.
For is used for loops to run a specific action while a condition is true.
While is used to create a while loop
where an action will run as long as something is true.
Def is used to define a function,
and return is used to return a specific value out of a function.
You don't need to memorize all 30 of these keywords right now.
You'll need to know them, but don't feel like you need
to memorize all of them immediately.
You want to practice using these keywords in actual implementations like you'll be doing,
and it will make a whole lot more sense how
these keywords work together when you write your Python code.
Just keep that in mind as you continue to learn in this course.
Let's see an example to understand how syntax and
lexis work together with keywords in Python.
We will create a new Notebook,
and we will say, my_variable = True.
We'll then write an if statement that checks if my variable is true, so we'll say,
if my_variable: print ("Hello world."),
otherwise, it prints "World, Hello."
If you press Enter with holding down Shift,
we'll see "Hello world," because my variable is true.
If we were to change this to false and then hold down Shift,
then press Enter, we'll see "World,
Hello," because now the else statement is in effect.
My variable is now false. It is not true.
This is basically shorthand for if my variable equals true, do this.
Otherwise, if it's not true,
which means that it's false, print this,
which is why we see this below.
While we don't want to memorize all of these keywords because there's a lot,
we're going to include a cheat sheet for you so that as you go through this course,
you can save this and refer back to it as you write more Python code.