When getting used to Python,
one of the biggest gotchas that can catch many by surprise,
even folks who are very familiar with Python is how an out of
alignment tab or space can make your Python script fail to execute.
Curious what I mean by this.
Welcome to Indentation with Python.
It's much easier to see this individual.
So let's see an example.
In this example here,
we're going to write a function that will be a greater function called Greek function,
and that will take in a name as an input.
If there is a name, it will print Hello with that name.
But if there isn't a name provided,
it will print Hello World.
So let's write this function right now.
We'll define the function as define Greek function.
This will take in a name.
If there is a name,
this will print Hello with a name.
So I'll write an F string to pass in a variable, say, Hello.
We'll pass in squiggly brackets,
and we'll pass in name.
We'll close this out with quotes and parentheses.
Otherwise, else, print Hello World.
Close that out. Tap back.
So if we were to call this function directly,
pass in Alice, we'll see Hello Alice is printed.
Now, if we were to not pass in a name,
and this is going to be an empty string,
so there's no input here for the string,
this will say, hello world, meaning there's no name.
If you also notice,
this is indented in a specific way.
So you'll see here with these indentations,
this is how Python works with functions with these types of statements.
However, if one of the indents was off,
such as the examples we're going to go through,
Python will complain and throw errors.
Let's say some of these examples.
So if we were to take print and move this back, Here,
we see that the else is not matching the indentation level of B if statement.
So this is all the way to the left,
but this is all the way to the right.
The print statement needs to be indented under the ls clause,
but we'll see it's not.
So if we were to run this,
and let's put a name back in here.
This is going to say that it's expecting
an indented block after ls on line 4, which is right here.
That's where we get that indentation error.
Again, if we back the di.
We'll see that that now works.
However, if we were to take print here and move this back in this example,
because the if is indented too much,
it throws off the rest of the script,
cause Python is expecting the function to execute everything under the def keyword,
but the indented print statement throws off the function.
So if we were to try to run this,
it we'll be able to execute, as we see here.
That's the indentation error on Line 2.
If we bring this back, we'll be able to run this.
We get our function working again.
So hopefully this is helpful to see how indentation works with writing our Python code.