When you're writing Python, you might want to make
references in text to what certain parts mean or do.
Especially as you work on Teams and with
other engineers who wrote code for various parts of a project,
certain actions or methods might be unfamiliar to you and others.
Fortunately for us, Python has a very handy way to let us write text in our code.
The best part of comments,
besides letting us provide human readable documentation in our machine code,
is that comments are ignored when Python actually runs.
Meaning the comments will have no impact on the execution of the functions themselves.
If we wanted to add comments to our greater function from earlier,
we'll use the pound hashtag sign to then
write out into the function some plain text references, like this.
We can explain what the function does,
for example, function to greet a friend.
Then we could help add some clarity around
the if statement and let other developers know,
if a name is provided, then run this.
We could then also define the L statement and say,
if a name is not provided, do this instead.
Then we can add some clarity around the execution of the function.
Pass in the name,
getting the function like this.
Now, let's remove these comments for a moment.
We can see how this makes our code so much more understandable when we have comments,
especially if you didn't write this code out yourself.
Without these comments, our code is much less understandable.
We probably would need to go and review this code to really understand it.
Sometimes you might want to write more text than just what can fit on a single line.
For this, we can use either three quotation marks
or three large quotation mark blocks to create a block comment, like this.
We can define it with 1, 2, 3.
One, two, three, and we could write a note like this,
and we could help explain the arguments that would be
expected for this function to run such as the name which is a string,
or we would expect it to be a string.
That's the name.
Great. Then we could help define what is returned to the function.
What's returned is a print statement.
But it does not have any return statements.
It just prints hello name or hello world.
Also, as you'll see here,
we could also do 1,2,3 and 1,2,3.
If we hold out shift and enter,
we'll see that our function runs and ignores
the note here that we have as a comment block.
We can write these comments and they won't be included in our execution.
As we mentioned before,
we can also do the double quotes and do three of those,
and that will also execute.
The same. The multiple lines of code in between here under
the function definition is a specific type of multi line comment called a doc string,
and this is used to describe the purpose of a function,
method, class, or module right after its initialization,
definition line, and follow a similar style to this,
explaining what the function does,
describing the arguments, and also what is returned from that function.
Between the first function which does not have any comments and
the second function which does have comments,
which one do you like more?
Which one do you feel is the most helpful for you as an engineer?
This is the power of comments and explaining
how code works and why it was written in the way that it was.
You might be thinking, Well,
when would I use comments?
The answer is everywhere.
Think of comments as your instructions that can help you or
future engineers understand what is happening in the code and why.
Now that we have some of the basics down,
it's time to start taking a look at storing information,
using variables, and the data types for those variables.