So far, we've only worked with returning a text value or printing a statement.
As we start to write more Python code,
we will encounter different types of information that aren't strings like names,
but could be different types of numbers or
different data types or different types of information.
Some of these could be Booleans,
integers, and floats.
In Python, literals are fixed values that you can use directly in your code.
They represent the simplest form of data and can be of various types.
Let's explore some of these.
Booleans are the simplest type of data.
They can only be true or false.
Think about if you're holding a pencil in your hand.
You either are or you aren't holding that pencil.
Think about a light switch.
It's either on or off.
One tricky thing to remember about Booleans is that they are case sensitive.
Always make sure to use a T for true and a F for false.
When using them, they look like this.
Booleans are often used to control the flow of a program, such as in loops.
Let's combine our knowledge of loops with Booleans using an example of keeping
a browser window awake based on user activity and log in status.
Think of a browser you are using right now,
and let's say that your company is developing a browser plug in.
In order to not waste resources when the user isn't actively using the browser,
we will want to create some logic around when the plug in is working and make it sleep.
Really go inactive when the user isn't actively using their browser window.
Let's see how a while loop can work with Boolean conditions to achieve this.
In our Jupiter notebook,
we will import time because we're going to be using
time to let the while loop know when and when not to run.
We'll then define three different Boolean values.
We'll have is active.
We'll set that to true is logged in,
set that equal to true, and then run,
plug in, and we'll set that equal to false.
Then we're going to start defining our while loop,
and we'll say it while is logged in.
While this is the case,
if is active is true,
run plug in equals true.
Then we're going to say print,
keeping the window awake.
Then we're just going to create some mock logic around making,
basically, something check activity.
I'm just going to write a comment just so that we can remember this.
We're going to say simulate activity every second.
We're going to use the time package,
and we're going to say sleep and set that equals to one for one second.
Otherwise, with else, run plug in equals false.
We're going to print, user is inactive,
putting the window to sleep and then we're going to break and then have it stop.
Then we're going to add a final print statement. We're going to say browser.
Window is now a sleep to save resources.
Let's discuss what's happening here.
In this example, we start with the is active state to true,
is logged in, which is set to true,
and then run plug in,
which is set to false.
The while loop continues to run as long as is logged in right here is true.
Inside the loop, if is active is true,
the script sets run plug in to true.
Prints a message to keep the window awake and simulates
a check every second using time.sleep 1.
If is active becomes false,
then the script sets run plug in to false,
prints a message to the window to sleep and breaks out of the loop.
Just to note, we are leaving out the logic that would, actually,
be checking if the user is actively engaged in the browser session,
as there would be another function that would be changing that is active.
Right here value when it's no longer true,
but this helps us get the message across.
This blends really well with our latest learnings around loops.
Can you start to think about how the condition of true, for a loop,
to run makes it actually run,
and when the statement is no longer true,
it is false, and therefore, the loop stops.
This is the underlying data structure.
Booleans help us accomplish all of this fancy logic behind the scenes,
and without us really knowing it.
If we try to execute this,
we'll see a message pop up on the window.
This is happening because keeping
the window awake is set by this active state, which is true.
That's what's going to keep this polling indefinitely because this state is true.
Now, if we were to change this to be false, and we set that.
We'll cancel this. We'll press Stop.
We rerun this.
User is inactive, putting the window to sleep.
Browser Window is now asleep to save resources.
Now we see that the else clause is fired off if run plug in is false,
because is active is false.
Now, we're not logged in anymore. We're not active.
We're checking if they're logged in,
and then if they're active.
Now once that becomes false,
then the S clause is fired off.
Then we say run plug in shouldn't be happening.
Then we're going to break.
That's why this doesn't keep saying,
keeping the window awake.
We see these two messages printed out because the if statement is no longer true.