Now we're going to transition into how we work with numbers in strings in Python.
The first stop is integers.
These are whole numbers,
both positive and negative without any decimal points.
Think about counting objects like apples or cars.
If you're counting the cars in a lot or apples in an orchard,
this doesn't include decimals or fractions.
We only care about whole apples and whole cars.
Another great example is counting time,
such as watch time when you're streaming a movie or TV show.
When considering minutes watched or hours watched,
you're only interested in the whole number in this case.
When you think about integers, think counting numbers.
Some examples of integers can look like this with age, year, cars,
and books, and notice the lack of comma where we define the integer of books.
We don't need to worry about commas when we define our integers in Python.
These data types are numbers and do contain decimals.
They are used to represent values that are not whole numbers,
such as measurements or prices.
When purchasing a coffee at your local store,
and you see the price at $4.99,
that is a floating point number.
Something important to note is that Python default to
the integer type when you write a whole number without a decimal point,
and to the floating point type,
when you include a decimal point,
even if the number is a whole number like 5.0.
In Python, when you work with numbers, the type,
whether it's an integer or a floating point,
depends on how the number is written.
Integers are whole numbers without a decimal point.
For example, 5 is an integer.
Floating point numbers are numbers with a decimal point.
For example, 5.0 is a floating point number.
Also, something tricky to note is that floats can be negative.
Here are a few more examples of floats with price, temperature, and length.
Scientific notation represents very large or small numbers to the power of 10.
Take, for example, 1 million.
That is a one with six zeros.
In scientific notation, that would be 1*10^6.
In Python, a lower case E is used to signify the 10 to the power of.
In our example, this would be 1e6.
These numbers can be negative as well,
0.0004 would be written as 4*10^(-4) or 4e(-4).
Quick note, 0.0004 is the same as 0.0004 in Python.
You've already been using strings in this course, if you can believe it.
Strings are sequences of characters used to store text.
For instance, first_name=Alice.
They can be enclosed in single quotes,
double quotes or triple quotes for multi line text,
so whether we are setting something equal to something else in quotation marks,
that is what we call setting a variable as a string.
When you see these examples,
you'll go, oh, yes, I remember seeing this.
That seems pretty familiar.
You probably have seen these messages in applications you use or software you download.
Log in successful, software upgraded to the latest version x.xx.
Whether you see these types of messages of text or characters,
remember that these are strings.
Since this is Python, after all,
there are methods to write machine readable code.
Up until this point, we've been going through a lot of
human readable code methods that help us write the code that we need Python to perform.
But there are ways to define
machine readable code that Python will understand at the byte level.
These are different ways to represent numbers in various bases.
Let's go through some of them.
With binary, this method uses digits 0 and 1,
prefixed with 0b, such as binary_value=0b1010.
This is binary speak for 10 in decimal.
With octal, this method uses digits 0-7,
prefixed with 0o, such as octal_value=0o12.
This is octal speak for 10 in decimal,
and of course, decimal base 10.
This is the standard number system we use
every day and one that I'm sure you'll recognize.
Remember, this data type is, what do we call it?
That's right, an integer,
such as decimal underscore value equals 10,
and of course, that means ten.
Hexadecimal, base 16 is a method that uses digits
0-9 and letters A to F, prefixed with 0x.
If you've ever seen block chain or crypto wallets,
you might see something like this where the wallet has a 0x...,
followed by a series of random characters,
or you might see hashes that start with Saw 256,
which is an encryption algorithm,
and that leverages hexadecimal numbers to represent values that a computer program
can understand easily and efficiently, such as hex_value=0xA.
This is hexadecimal speak for ten decimal.
It's okay if you don't fully grasp these concepts right now.
The goal here is just to introduce you to these numeral systems,
not to necessarily master them at this point.
As you continue learning and practicing,
these ideas will become much clearer.
If binary octal, decimal,
and hexadecimal seems confusing to you, don't stress out.
This is something that you will gain exposure to
if and when you begin programming with these various systems.
For the PCP exam,
just make sure that you are aware that they exist and what the value looks like.