Through our iterative approach to learning Python,
you have already been using variables in this course.
But we haven't quite had a deep dive yet into what a variable actually is.
You might even remember what a variable is for math class.
For example, x = 2,
y = mx + b.
If these ring a bell, great,
if not, no worries at all,
we're going to be going through these together because variables are
so important to add to our pythonic tool kit.
Already in this course, we have been using and depending
on variables to store info for another value.
Variables are little packets of data used to store information.
In Python, you can assign a value to a variable using the equal sign.
They can be created, updated, deleted, recreated,
and stored across your Python environment so
that you can keep track of all of the information used.
Imagine if you were keeping track of items in a cart to check out at the store and you
had to write the complete list every single time you added a new item to the cart,
change an item in the cart,
remove an item from the cart.
It would take forever, right?
A variable allows us to store information about our items.
We can keep track of how many items there are,
their names, their prices,
or anything else that we're interested in.
Then when needed, we can recall that information,
allowing us to avoid rewriting massive amounts of
information every time something in our code base or our cart.
For example, changes.
Some examples of variables are these,
which you see on the screen,
and we can create any number of variables,
name them however we want,
and set their value equal to whatever we need them to
be like x = 100 or user name = PythonExpert,
or ready_ to_ learn = true.
When naming variables, it's important to follow
certain conventions to make your code readable and consistent.
Python recommends using snake case for variable names with brackets.
We cannot use spaces for variable names,
so we need to make the variable name of a string of
characters with no spaces or certain special characters like this.
We make a cell, you can take user_name,
which is Snake case equals PythonExpert.
Or is student.
Again, that's in Snake case. Is true.
We could also put PythonExpert space equals to because that is in between quota marks,
but since it's a user name, we probably wouldn't do that.
But something we could not do is say user name space name equals that.
This needs to be one full concise,
complete element, and we use underscores instead of spaces.
This is the best practice for a Python variable.
Now, here's a little inside tip.
When I was just starting out programming,
I thought you needed to put an underscore.
Every time you declared a variable,
but this isn't actually true.
You could get away with writing variables like this,
readyToLearn with lower case,
and then mixing that with the uppercase equals true.
That will work. Or BOOKS = 12345.
Both of these values will work.
But Snake case like this is the tried and true method.
If you're going to write variables,
make sure to remember Snake case for Python.
In the Below example,
do you see how the E is a variable,
but it's just a single letter?
Meanwhile, the error message is set to a function string.
We'll learn about those a little later,
and we can assume that num1 and num2 will
be integers or float number values for our divided numbers function.
Let's say this in action.
When we define this function,
we'll use a tri block,
take a result, and then take num1 / num2,
and then return the value.
Otherwise, except there'll be a zero division error.
Otherwise, a regular exception, we'll overturn that.
Can you tell what this function is doing?
Can you see what it will output?
Let's go through it together.
The function divide numbers attempts to divide num1 by num2.
If a zero division error occurs, right here.
It catches the error and assigns it to the variable E. The variable E
isn't used to create a more detailed error message right here.
If any other exception occurs,
it also catches it and assigns it to E,
and then creates a general error message. Right here.
The function then returns the appropriate result or error message.
Overall, there can be many ways to declare variables and work with data types in Python,
but it will become second nature,
the more Python you write.
You got this. Remember early when we were
learning about the Lexicon vocabulary and style guide of Python.
Well, there are additional guidelines for writing clean, complete,
and concise Python code called the Python enhancement Proposal eight or PEP 8 for short.
PEP 8 is the style guide for writing Python,
and such recommendations are use four spaces per indentation level.
Limit lines to 79 characters.
Use blank lines to separate functions in classes,
and use spaces around operators and after commas.
Keep these in mind when you are writing your Python code,
so that it can be as optimized,
readable, and efficient as possible.