Last time, we used a violin plot to look at
the relationship between vehicle class and fuel efficiency.
Now, we'll use box plots to summarize that relationship.
Just substitute violin plot for box plot, and we've got our output.
The bottom of each box,
indicates the first quartile and the top of each box, the third quartile.
The central line is the median of each group.
Whiskers branch out toward the min and max and each group,
with outliers depicted as individual points past a maximum whisker length.
That depends on each group's box height.
The taller each box, the wider the whiskers can be.
The box plot supports the observations that we made in the last video,
regarding the relative order and variability in fuel efficiencies by vehicle class.
If we move back to the violin plot,
now you can understand what was plotted in each violin area.
The thicker black region represents the interquartile range,
with the white dot in each violin, the medians.
I actually prefer the inner equals quartile parameters setting.
Which only plots the quartiles as dashed lines.
The line with the larger dashes are the medians,
and the lines with the shorter dashes on either side, the quartiles.