One way that you could think about clustered bar chart is that it's really a set of
side-by-side univariate bar charts on different subsets of the data.
This technique of creating multiple copies of the same type of
plot but for different subsets of the data is called Faceting.
We can use this for any type of plot,
not just for bar charts.
A violin plot for example could be thought of as very similar
to a set of histograms faceted by a categorical variable.
As a general technique,
faceting is good for breaking down potentially complex patterns into simpler parts.
This is especially useful if you have a categorical variable with a lot of levels.
For example, this plot shows user registration dates
faceted by month and arranged in a three by four grid,
separating things out into multiple bar charts instead of
a single long bar chart makes it easier to
see the unusual number of January first registrations.
One thing to be careful of when faceting is that
your axis scales and limits are consistent across each subplot.
A failure to have the same limits on each subplot we'll make it easier to have
misconceptions about the overall frequency or value range for each subset of the data.
Take for example these two plots.
The plot on the left suggests that the two groups have approximately the same frequency
and range but only if you don't pay attention to the axis ranges.
The plot on the right fixes both subplots to the same axis ranges and clearly
shows that there are more points of type B and
that those points are generally of higher value than A