In this lesson, we're going to look at
another numerical slash categorical plotting type called a box plot.
These are very similar to violin plots,
but a little bit easier to interpret.
Let's start by as always,
importing our libraries and our dataset.
Just like violin plots,
box plots are used to depict
a relationship between a quantitative and a qualitative variable.
Both matplotlib and seaborn have a method boxplot.
Here we're going to use seaborns.
It takes for the data parameter,
the data frame we're interested in.
Our x-variable is going to be vehicle class,
our y parameter is going to be combined
fuel efficiency and the color I'm setting to tableau blue.
I'm also rotating our x ticks to make our x-label easier to read.
In a boxplot each distribution includes descriptive statistics for each category.
For instance, each line of a box denotes a quartile range.
For instance, this line on the box for sub-compact cars is the first quartile,
meaning 25% of the data falls below that line.
This middle line here is the median,
50% of the data lives below that line, 50% above.
Up here we have the third quartile, or 75th percentile.
Seventy five percent of the distribution falls below that line.
Whiskers are extended from the top and bottom of
the boxes to indicate the largest and smallest values.
Any outliers are indicated by these black diamonds.
One thing to remember is that while boxplots do a fine job of summarizing the data,
there are some distributional details that can get lost.
In some instances, violin plots might provide more information,
such as if distributions are bimodal or multimodal in general.
However, filling plots can be deceiving or confusing to those not familiar with them,
so when it comes to explanatory data visualization,
you might want to choose a box plot for simplicity and focus.