If we want to look at the relationship between two categorical variables,
then we have to go beyond simple positional encodings.
Earlier in this lesson,
you saw how heat maps depict a 2D histogram across two numeric variables.
A similar strategy can be used for two categorical variables,
analogous to creating a 2D bar chart.
However, if we want to avoid the imprecision of using color to encode numbers,
then the standard plot choice is the clustered bar chart.
A clustered bar chart starts out the same as the univariate bar chart with
the levels of one variable on the x-axis and counts to be plotted on the y-axis.
However, instead of just one bar being plotted at each exposition,
we instead have multiple bars,
one for each level of the second variable we want to plot.
Typically, we apply a color or texture encoding to each bar
in each cluster to distinguish between the levels of the second variable.
Thus, the counts depicted by the height of each bar are associated with
the general exposition for the first variable and the color for the second variable.
This correspondence is easier to see when we
put the heat map next to the clustered bar chart.
Comparing the two visualizations,
you can see the increased precision and understanding the ranking and
differences in frequency counts when you look at the bar chart compared to the heat map.