In this lesson, we're going to now look at
relationships between two qualitative variables,
vehicle class and vehicle transmission.
We're going to do this by using a clustered bar chart.
To get started, let's load our Python libraries and
Visualization libraries as normal and our fuel economy dataset.
Now, the first thing we're going to do is a little bit of feature engineering.
We need to extract the transmission type.
Now, there are many different kinds of transmission types that our dataset looks at.
But we're really only interested in the broad categories of automatic and manual.
To do that, we're going to extract that by using
a Lambda function where we just look at the first word of each transmission type.
For instance, you can see here that in the original DataFrame,
the trans variable includes many types of
automatics and we only want to take the first word in our Lambda function.
We go all the way to the end.
We now see we have a new feature called trans type,
which includes automatic, but also manual cars.
One way of depicting this relationship could be with a 2D Histogram Heatmap,
like we saw before.
However, there's actually a Seaborne function for this type of categorical heatmap.
It's called the heatmap function.
However, this function takes as an argument,
a 2D array or DataFrame with the values to be depicted.
The calling syntax is slightly different.
This means we have to do some summarization work ourselves before we can create our plot.
To strike the summary process.
First, I use group by to take our DataFrame
and group by vehicle class and transmission type.
I want to know how many of each are in combined categories.
I use the size method.
We can see here,
our DataFrame has now broken down by vehicle class and
transmission type with a total number of count in each of these.
Now, this group by object is technically a series and we want to make it a DataFrame.
To do that, we're going to use a reset index and then rename this last column to count.
Finally, we're going to use this pivot function,
this DataFrame pivot method to rearrange the data.
We're going to pass it in the index that we're looking for,
which is the V Class column.
The column is going to be transmission type
in the values for each cell is going to be count.
Then we can put this directly in to our Seaborne heatmap object.
This looks cool, but it's disappointing.
It's really hard to compare the counts and transmission ratios from the colors alone.
You can see that manual tends to be less popular than automatic,
but beyond that, it's really hard to tell.
One option we have is to add annotations with the cell counts in each cell.
This will make the representation more tabular in nature.
Let's do that. Here,
we have a parameter called annot for annotation.
We're going to put that to be true.
The fm 't' is a formatter parameter and we're
going to put d to ensure that all of the counts are listed as decimal values.
This is much better.
We still get the interpretation that we had before
that there tend to be fewer manual cars than automatic.
But now we can see quantitative variation much easier.