One additional option that we have for plotting one quantitative variable
against one qualitative variable is the adaptation of bar charts.
Instead of showing counts on the vertical axis,
we can show the mean of a second variable.
To do this, we need to make use of
a different function than the count plot function that we had before.
Instead, Seaborn's bar plot function will be what we want.
I'll add a label to the y-axis so that it's
clear that we're plotting the means on the y-axis.
Since we have a bar plot,
the bottom limit of the y-axis has been set to zero.
The black lines on each bar indicate uncertainty about the mean as a confidence info.
Since we have a lot of data available,
the uncertainty whiskers are quite small.
If we want to leave these whiskers out of the plot,
we can do so by setting air width equals zero.
Alternatively, we could change the bars to represent the standard deviation of
data points by setting the parameter ci equals sd.
If having the zero lower bound isn't of interest,
then you can choose the point plot function instead of the bar plot function.
We actually don't need to set the base color in
this case for everything to show up as the same color.
Note that by default,
the points are connected by a line.
This isn't a problem in this case since vehicle classes ordered from smallest to largest.
But if we were plotting a nominal variable instead,
we could turn off the line by setting line styles to an empty string.