In this lesson, we're going to look at heatmaps.
These can be thought of as a two-dimensional histogram or even color-coded table.
In fact, hist2d is the calling syntax.
Let's start by doing our normal imports and also loading in our data.
This is the car fuel economy dataset and a heatmap.
The field is divided into grids of cells,
much like a two-dimensional histogram.
The number of data points in each cell is counted up.
Now, each cell is given a color based on the counter values.
In this example, we're going to use matplotlib.
We're going to pass in the dataframe and specify we want engine displacement and
liters on the x axis and y to be the combined efficiency.
That's a combination of highway miles per gallon and city miles per gallon.
We're also going to add a color bar because we're
leaving this empty will just be the counts in each bin.
Then finally, we're going to add labels for the x and y axis.
You can think of a basic heatmap like
this like a two-dimensional version of a histogram,
looking at the data from a top-down perspective.
We can't see bar heights in this case,
so color is the best way to really encoded.
What we can see here is that the cell with
the largest value has a combined fuel efficiency a little under 25 miles per gallon,
and has about a two liter displacement.
We can assign bin widths to heatmaps.
Just like histograms, you need to be aware of
the impact of bin size on the interpretation of data.
Too large of bin size,
you may fail to see a major trend and too small a bin size,
you may just end up distracted by noise.
Here, I found a bin size that looks about right to me.
We set the bin size just like we did in the univariate case using numpy.arange.
For the two-dimensional histogram,
I also added a color minimum perimeter cmin that
says any cell with less than this value is not plotted with a color,
it's just left blank.
I also passed in a color palette,
viridis reversed, and the bins that I'm interested in.
Here we find this plot,
which is just so much cleaner, easier to read.
Since assigning values based on colors imprecise,
you should consider adding count annotations on top of each grid cell,
especially if you only have a limited number of cells.
In this view, the heatmap is a lot like a table with additional coloring for emphasis.
For annotated 2D histograms,
you'll have to loop through each cell to display the value.
This can be quite tedious, but that's okay.
You can reuse this code when making other similar plots.
Here, after assigning and plotting the histogram,
we are then going to go through,
look at the counts for the entire histogram,
and then loop through starting on the x axis and
then the y axis and plotting on top the actual text that we want to see in each bin.
Here, for the text function,
I also include horizontal alignment,
meaning the center of the bin,
and the vertical alignment,
and also plot,
choose the color for the text.
Notice, if the number of counts is greater than 100,
we put the text color is white and if it's just greater than 0,
we put it as black.
This makes it much easier for us to read.
Now, a heatmap is favored over a scatter plot if you have two discrete variables
since the associated jitter can be imprecise in a scatter plot.