As we saw previously,
when we have two numeric variables,
at least one of them discrete,
jitter and transparency can be used to make the trends in the data clearer.
If we want to plot a quantitative variable against a qualitative variable,
we could take the same approach,
just mapping each level of the qualitative variable to an arbitrary number.
For example, let's say that we have a number of game scores from three different teams,
North, Central, and South.
If we associate one with North, two at Central,
and three with South, then we could use a jittered scatter plot
with team on the x-axis and score on the y-axis.
A more common visualization for this quantitative
versus qualitative comparison is the violin plot.
Instead of plotting data points individually,
we have a curve for each level of
the categorical variable whose area depicts the distribution of points.
Where the curve is wider,
there are more data points.
It's basically a smooth histogram or density curve turned on its side.
For North, you can see that they scored more points in the 50's than the 60's.
You can also see that Central tends to score more points than either North or South.
Compared to the jittered scatter plot,
having the distinct curves makes it easier to remember that the variable is
categorical and easier to compare their distributions.