In this lesson, we're going to look at a new type of plot called a Violin Plot.
Violin plots look at numerical data or
numerical distributions for a set of different categories.
Let's start this lesson by importing our required libraries for analysis and plotting,
as well as our fuel economy dataset.
In this lesson, we're going to look at the relationship between our fuel efficiency
variable against a qualitative variable vehicle class.
We're going to start by defining a new datatype.
For categorical data.
This is an ordered datatype,
meaning that our plots should hopefully plot them in order.
For instance, we're interested in
the Sedan classes from mini compact cars to sub-compact cars,
all the way to large cars.
Then we're going to define a categorical datatype and that
datatype we can put ordered equals true and our categories are defined up here.
Then we can use a Pandas method called as type to
re-interpret vehicle class has these data class variable types.
We do this, so that way seaborne should be able to
interpret that ordered parameter and recognize that these are ordered.
To plot a violin plot,
we use the seaborne function, violin plot.
Like most seaborne plots,
we hand in the data looking specifically at our Data-Frame.
We also define the x-variable is v class and
the y vehicle as our combined fuel efficiency.
We end up getting something like this.
Now, we should really clean this up a little bit.
As seen before,
we're going to make all the colors the same.
The x-axis labels are also overlapping.
It's very difficult to read,
so we need to rotate them slightly and additionally,
violin plots have these busy internal sections here.
I'm going to set them to none and make them disappear for now.
I'll make them reappear in just a moment.
Doing all these things.
We add the color.
We set the inner perimeter of the plot to none,
and we rotate our x-ticks,
we end up seeing something like this,
this is so much better.
How do we interpret a violin plot?
For each vehicle class and area is plotted that shows
the approximate density of each value.
For example, let's look at sub-compact cars.
What we see here is essentially
a probability density function or PDF that turned on its side.
This tells you that most of the data is plotted right
around 23 or 24 miles per gallon for sub-compact cars.
Comparing to large cars,
we see that large cars are on average much lower than sub-compact cars.
But we have a very large number of outliers.
For mini compact cars.
We have a bimodal distribution.
Many are around 20 or 21 miles per gallon.
But we have another common mode right under 30.
Going back to that inner plotting artifact,
what is going on there?
Now instead of inner equals none,
Let's set the parameter to quartile.
When we do that,
we see that are plotted the three quartiles for each of these classes.
The lowest is the 25th percentile,
the middle is the median,
or 50th percentile, and the top is the 75th percentile or third quartile.
This gives us a better idea of how
the distribution is changing in the center of the distribution.
For example, for large cars,
we have a very few number of outliers
that are really pulling the distribution away from the center.